Date: 21-04-2011

Introduction to blogs.perl.org + Text::Table

Hello, Perl bloggers! I decided to start blogging about a most of my exclusively Perl-related stuff here on blogs.perl.org, in hope of getting more comments from active Perlers. (Until now, I've blogged about it on my technical LiveJournal blog and previously on use.perl.org Journal.). You can learn more about me on my home site - www.shlomifish.org .

OK, having put that aside - let's move on to the main topic of this post.

Many months ago I wanted to use the Text::Table CPAN module to present a table related to the meta-scan heuristics construction scheme of Freecell Solver. Now, I wanted to present nicely formatted borders, using the Unicode box-drawing characters (which some people would recall from DOS). However, I found it difficult to specify the separators in the rulers properly based on their indices - they were assumed to be the same globally. As a result, I've written a patch, and placed the modifications in a github repository.

The author of Text-Table (ANNO) told me he was working on a new version of Text-Table, which will contain many improvements. However, I was still interested in an enhanced version of the old Text-Table codebase with my patch, and after talking on #perl, ANNO said I could have co-maint on Text-Table-1.x and continue to improve it. The new Text-Table will be released under a separate namespace - Text::Table2 or so.

Many thanks go to ANNO for agreeing that I further develop Text::Table.

Using my git repository, I did many cleanups, like add pod.t and pod-coverage.t, tweak the author information, add more strict and warnings to the file, etc. ANNO 's original licence is "Same terms as Perl", but since it is an iffy licensing, I decided that all further changes will be under the terms of the Public-Domain/X11L/etc.. People who send me pull requests on github may wish to add their names to the credits (in the changes or even in the core module) but must not claim copyrights to their changes.

OK, now for some output of the Unicode table:

┌───────╥─────┬──────┬─────┬────┬──────┐
│ Place ║ 1   │ 2    │ 3   │ 4  │ 5    │
├───────╫─────┼──────┼─────┼────┼──────┤
│ 1     ║ 68  │ 317  │ 15  │ 3  │ 381  │
├───────╫─────┼──────┼─────┼────┼──────┤
│ 2     ║ 171 │ 482  │ 31  │ 14 │ 594  │
├───────╫─────┼──────┼─────┼────┼──────┤
│ 3     ║ 275 │ 867  │ 42  │ 22 │ 1007 │
├───────╫─────┼──────┼─────┼────┼──────┤
│ 4     ║ 458 │ 1442 │ 125 │ 30 │ 1630 │
├───────╫─────┼──────┼─────┼────┼──────┤
│ 5     ║ 640 │ 1715 │ 137 │ 47 │ 1730 │
└───────╨─────┴──────┴─────┴────┴──────┘

Future plans are:

Convert the remaining test scripts to Test::More.
Go over the code and clean it up
Add CPAN keywords to the META.yml. (Perhaps this will require defining a Module-Build-based Build.PL file).
Add URLs to the META.yml - to the module's homepage, to the github repository, etc..
Possibly implement some future features.
Add some more tests.

Contributions are naturally welcome, just fork the github repository and send me a pull request. (Or patches are also OK.)

Date: 20-06-2011
YAPC

Transferring a Ticket to YAPC::Europe::2011

I originally planned to attend YAPC::Europe::2011 in Riga, Latvia (on 15-17 August, 2011), and so bought an early bird ticket, but will no longer be able to attend due to personal reasons. As a result, I'm now seaking to transfer the ticket to someone else, for the right price (which will be cheaper than what I bought it.).

If you are interested, please contact me and we will negotiate a price. I hope everybody enjoys the YAPCs.

Date: 20-06-2011
XML, libxml, CPAN

Resuming Maintenance of XML-LibXML

For a long while, work on the XML-LibXML CPAN module halted as the existing maintainer was busy. After a discussion on the Perl-in-XML mailing list, some people and I were given co-maintainer status and we resumed its maintenance inside a Bitbucket.org Mercurial repository.

So far what I did, was fix some low-hanging fruit bugs, apply some patches, as well as start the long process of converting the test suite, which still uses Test.pm to Test::More . There are still many bugs lurking there, and some of them are XS bugs that are still beyond my reach, and I could use some assistance there. But it's a start.

If you're interested in helping, the clone the repository, write a patch and send me a pull request.

Text::Table Update: I've written about resuming the maintenance of Text::Table in April, and it progressed nicely: the tests were converted to Test::More, a lot of the code was cleaned up, the build system was converted to Module::Build, and keywords and resource URLs were defined, and some bugs were solved (along with tests). I'm still looking into ways to clean up the code, and if anyone has an idea for a cool feature, then they should drop me a line (or provide a patch).

Date: 23-06-2011
QA, PPI, Perl

PPI-Based Script to Convert Test.pm-based Test Programs to Test::More

Some CPAN modules I inherited used the old Test.pm for some of their t/*.t scripts instead of the more modern Test::More. This annoys me to no end because Test.pm is very limited. When I worked on Config-IniFiles, I did the conversion manually, which was a lot of work. More recently, I started working on XML-LibXML which has over 40 of those pesky Test.pm scripts, and I did not have the nerve to do all the manual and menial work.

As a result, I ended up spending a few hours studying PPI (the Perl Parsing Interface), and writing a script to automatically convert Test.pm-based scripts to Test::More. The main issue at hand was that in Test.pm, a single argument ok() tests for the scalar's truth, while a double argument ok() tests for simple equivalence (similarly to Test::More's is()). Eventually, I got the script working, with some limitations (see the page).

So what was my impression of PPI? It naturally seems more robust than using regular expressions and hacks to process Perl code, but there were a few quirks. For example, a PPI list contains an array of its contents, and the commas are part of them, as are the various other tokens in the sub-expressions. Therefore, divining the count of the arguments is pretty hard. I would have expected to get a more abstract syntax tree of the arguments, and since I didn't I had to work around it with an ugly kludge.

Furthermore, after stringifying the document object, the contents of the here-documents were not included in the output from some reason. However, I may have done something wrong. I also wish the PPI PODs contained more meaningful examples.

Nevertheless, my script is mostly working now and I can utilise it to "test-lift" legacy test programs. You might find it useful too, so it's there in case you need it, and patches to fix its limitations would be welcome.

Date: 09-11-2011
Perl, QA, XS, Inline, C, ctypes, gcc

My Experience with Inline::C

I know I didn’t write here for a long time, and I apologise for it, but I have this entry and another one in mind and I hope they can compensate for it.

For my work on Freecell Solver, I’ve written some code for encoding and decoding game positions into a compact format, by encoding them as a delta from the position of origin. I first wrote it in Perl, in order to prototype it, and later translated it to C (which is the language that Freecell Solver is written in). I have written some rudimentary unit tests for it, but also wanted to test the code against a large number of positions, by runnign it over the solutions of many Freecell deals.

The encoding rearranges the order of the card columns and the freecells, so testing that the output test is correct requires calculating that arrangement. This was also done by the Perl code. I decided to write a small wrapper for an encoding+decoding round-trip in C, and use it from a Perl program I was writing. So far so good.

I first looked at the Perl version of Ctypes, but it failed a large number of its assertions on my system, so I could not really trust it. Then I looked at Inline::C. I could not understand from its main page, how to return an SV * containing a string from it, but this was covered in the extensive Inline::C cookbook and I wrote this Inline::C function:

extern char * fc_solve_user_INTERNAL_delta_states_enc_and_dec(
    const char * init_state_str_proto,
    const char * derived_state_str_proto
    );

SV* enc_and_dec(char * init_state_s, char * derived_state_s) {
    SV * ret;
    char * s;
    s = fc_solve_user_INTERNAL_delta_states_enc_and_dec(init_state_s, derived_state_s);

    ret = newSVpv(s, 0);
    free(s);
    return ret;
}

I don't need to use “sv_2mortal” there because Inline::C does that for us. Then I tried to test it. It failed with this error:

perl: symbol lookup error: /home/shlomif/progs/freecell/trunk/fc-solve/source/_Inline/lib/auto/Mega_Test_for_C_delta_states_pl_9385/Mega_Test_for_C_delta_states_pl_9385.so: undefined symbol: fc_solve_user_INTERNAL_delta_states_enc_and_dec

I was familiar with errors like that, but it took me over an hour of playing with the various Inline::C configuration options, and trying to figure out why it didn’t link against the relevant Freecell Solver library to realise what the problem was. It was that the library in question did not export the symbol, and gcc realised it didn't give the XS extension anything and omitted it.

After fixing this line in my C source:

char * DLLEXPORT fc_solve_user_INTERNAL_delta_states_enc_and_dec(

To this line:

DLLEXPORT char * fc_solve_user_INTERNAL_delta_states_enc_and_dec(

Everything worked properly, and I was able to run the so-called “mega-test”.

If you’re having similar problems with Inline::C, you should try to add CLEAN_AFTER_BUILD => 0 to its configuration. It ended up clarifying a lot for me.

Cheers!

Date: 09-11-2011
exec, perl, portability, whitespace, windows, unix

exec's portability

Pop quiz! What does this perl 5 program prints when executed with no arguments?

#!/usr/bin/perl

use strict;
use warnings;

if (! @ARGV)
{
    exec($^X, $0, "hello world");
}
else
{
    my $arg = shift(@ARGV);
    print "Got <$arg>\n";
    if (@ARGV)
    {
        print "Other args are <@ARGV>\n";
    }
}

The answer is “it depends.”. On my Linux system it prints “Got <hello world>”, while on Windows, using Strawberry Perl, it prints “Got <hello>” and later on that the other args are “world”.

I would expect the Linux behaviour were every argument passed to the list exec arrives as one argument to @ARGV regardless of whitespace as the correct. It also the behaviour exhibited on both operating systems using system. Is this a bug?

perlport only has this to say about whitespace: Whitespace in filenames is tolerated on most systems, but not all, and even on systems where it might be tolerated, some utilities might become confused by such whitespace..

I discovered this strange mis-behaviour when working on a commission for a client who is Windows-based.

Date: 03-12-2011
Perl, Mongers, Tel Aviv, Israel, meeting, DBI, DBIx-Class, local-lib, perlbrew, cpanminus, CPAN, Firebird, SQL

Report on the Latest Tel Aviv Perl Mongers Meeting

I attended the latest Tel Aviv Perl Mongers (TelAviv.pm) meeting the other day, and am writing this report in order to encourage more people to come. We didn't have meetings in September or October due to the Jewish holidays and some renovations on the site, so it was good to finally have a meeting.

Before the meeting, I had helped publicise it on various online news channels, and thankfully quite a few people (about 20-30) came. I had a previous appointment that day at 12:00, and so returned home where I ate, worked on the computer, and rested before the TelAviv.pm meeting.

After I rode the bus, I arrived there a few minutes earlier. I met a fellow Perl monger on the way. We found the room with some difficulty, as there were very few signs outside the doors of the various rooms in the building. Several people including Gabor were already sitting in the room. They were discussing the upcoming Israeli Perl Workshop in February. In any case, I decided to walk to the nearby grocery store to buy some refreshments for the meeting, and when I returned there were more people in the room.

Quite a few people arrived relatively late, but the talks started mostly on schedule. The first talk (by Erez Schatz) was short, and it discussed some recent tools that facilitate the Perl programmer’s life: local-lib, perlbrew, cpanm and pm-uninstall. The talk was very fun, and he ended up covering some other tools in brief in the last slide. I’m still not convinced that I should use CPAN-Minus instead of my CPANPLUS (especially given CPANPLUS-Dist-Mageia and friends), but I still like perlbrew and local::lib and pm-uninstall seems useful.

Erez mentioned that on Perl forums there were several very common and hated questions like “How do I uninstall a perl module?” or “How can I use CPAN without root?” and that these technologies address these needs precisely.

After this talk, Erez gave a longer talk about DBIx-Class, which is an Object-Relational Mapper (ORM) for Perl. For the demo, he used a company whose employees are dogs, and the slides featured many pictures of dogs in suits (some of them pretty scary). There were a few glitches in the demonstration, but they were promptly overcome, and the DBIC_TRACE=1 flag was a big help. One bug in the code was that instead of updating the employee's department (by looking it up by name), the department's name was updated (globally). I any case, it was an enjoyable talk, but the person who sat next to me said that she didn’t like it because she used to be a DBA, and she was worried about performance.

Erez mentioned that DBIx-Class was the “Elephant in the Room” of Perl ORMs, which I had concluded was the case as well.

After that talk, there was a break, where people got to eat more of the cookies I bought and to chat. Afterwards, Ido Kanner presented about Firebird SQL. It was a good talk, and Ido drew some comparisons between Firebird and SQLite, MySQL and PostgreSQL. Firebird looks interesting and it also has embedded (like SQLite) and read-only modes.

One problem during the talk was that the projector kept shutting down, and it took us some trouble to restart it. We hoped this problem would be resolved in upcoming meetings.

After the meeting, some of us (about 10) went to Spaghettim (a pasta/etc. place) and had dinner. We chatted about Atheism, Cable company tech-support, GNOME 3 and KDE 4, and lots of other stuff. This time I had a pizza, which although not too bad, made me realise I will be ordering pasta there from now on.

To sum up, it was a very enjoyable meeting, and I’m looking forward for more future ones. One thing notable about it is that this time Sawyer did not deliver a talk, which made him happy because other people volunteered to do so instead.

Date: 26-12-2011
perl,debugger,debugging,refactoring,features,sopa,telaviv,mongers

Breaking the Perl Debugger for Fun and Profit

Before I cover the main topic of this entry, here are some short news and action items:

If you have not acted against SOPA - the proposed online blacklist/censorship bill, you should. Follow the link for information on how to act against it.

I have announced the next Tel Aviv Perl Mongers meeting on my technical journal on LiveJournal.com. It will take place this Wednesday, on 28 December, 2011. More information in the link.

Anarchy Golf is a new server for Code Golf, which are online programming competitions for implementing code as shortly as possible. It supports Perl 5, Perl 6 and many other languages. There is an active challenge, where the only Perl 5 submission so far is mine, so I could use some competition.

Now for the main topic of the post. Recently, three patches were integrated into the perl-5 core implementing new features in the perl debugger:

Add "b <filename>:<line> <cond>" to perl -d by me.
Add enable/disable commands for breakpoints in perl -d also by me.
"Trace to max depth" by Peter Scott.

When Father Chrysostomos tried to apply the first patch, he noticed its tests started failing. Apparently, the breakpoint functionality (irrespective of the patch's added functionality) became broken in bleadperl, due to a change in the internals, and it wasn't caught by the debugger's existing tests. I ended up submitting another patch to add a test for some of the existing breakpoint functionality.

The other two patches passed all of their own tests and the existing ones, but that wasn't the end of the story. A short time afterwards a regression was reported in the debugger, which was caused by one of the patches that I introduced. While, I fixed it with a test, it was soon followed by other reports and fixes. None of these bugs were caught by the test suite of the perl debugger, which is incredibly incomplete.

Another E-mail that caused an active discussion was my proposal to add strict and warnings to lib/perl5db.pl, in which someone kept arguing against it, and eventually said he confused it (it being the defualt command-line debugger front-end) with the debugger's guts, and ended up also supporting adding "use strict;".

I ended up working on adding "strict" to the debugger on a git branch, and was eventually successful (though I temporarily broken no-strict code on the debugger evaluated lines, to which I added a test.). RJBS (the current pumpking) said he'd like to integrate this patch only after perl-5.16.x is released.

The morals of this story is that the perl debugger needs more tests, and that trying to enhance it can easily break it. I started a branch on GitHub where I've been committing more tests to the perl debugger to enhance its coverage.

There's also a Google Code-In task for devising a strategy to do that, and I've volunteered to mentor it. All this will hopefully result in less breakage in the future.

Happy Holidays, and a Happy New Year.

Date: 27-03-2012
perl, workshop, israel, events, 2012

Report on the Israeli Perl Workshop 2012

Well, I've got a lot of stuff I’d like to blog about in the various blogs of mine, and so I’m starting with this report on the Israeli Perl Workshop of 2012, which had taken place in 28 February, 2012. Moreover, April Fools' Day is approaching, and I had an idea for a Perl-related April Fools' gag, but after telling it to RJBS (the current Perl pumpking), he and I agreed that it would hit too many nerves. (PerlJam on IRC said he liked it, though). Maybe I’ll publish it on 2 April with a big disclaimer on top, just for kicks.

Anyway, here is the report. I had originally posted it to the Perl in Israel mailing list for review, but did not get any reviews, so it may not be too letter-perfect, but I guess that’s life.

This is my report about the Israeli Perl Workshop of 2012 . It was a fun and educational event, and I'm glad I was able to attend it. For better or for worse, all the talks I attended were in Room 1, but I was still able to hear the ends of a few talks in Room 2 (because the corresponding talks in Room 1 ended before them).

I set up an alarm the night before in order to wake up early in time for the event, and ended up waking up some time before it (and even the alarm time was much earlier than what I was used to). Then I made some preparations, ate breakfast, and caught the appropriate bus. After I walked from the bus station to Shenkar, it took me some time to find the place, because it wasn't the same entrance as our normal rooms, and the signs were confusing. What I needed to do was to take the stairs down to the yard, and then go to the organisation room, but it was hard to find.

There I got my name sticker, the schedule, and some swag from booking.com. I’d like to thank Booking.com for sponsoring the Israeli Perl Workshop 2012 (as well as having a presence there and giving some swag and chocolates), and they are looking for software developers with Perl experience to relocate to Amsterdam, so please consider working for them.

In the yard, I met a few people including Florian Ragwitz (a.k.a "FLORA" on CPAN or "rafl" on IRC - he has many cool modules there, including quite a few XS ones), who was one of the workshop’s visitors from Germany. Despite being German, his English accent sounded English to us. Later on we discussed accents in English and he noted that the accents of some Israelis he met sounded like French to him (while ours seemed less so). This is strange, because Israelis can distinguish between a French accent in English and an Israeli Hebrew accent in English.

Anyway, Florian told me that he is planning on reviewing and pulling my Test::Aggregate GitHub pull request Real Soon Now™, a fact which has brought me some relief, because I've tried to contact him on IRC and ask him if he remembers.

For better or for worse, all the talks that I preferred to hear took place in room #1 (while sometimes visiting Room #2) to hear the ends of talks. I still would be happy to hear many of the talks that took place in Room #2 in the normal Tel Aviv Perl Mongers meetings, or alternatively, those talks in room #1 which lacked enough time to be conveyed satisfactorily.

The first talk in the day was Ran Eilam’s talk about "Syntactic Sugar causes Cancer of the Semicolon”, which had to be trimmed towards the end, because the introduction may have taken too long. The talk was interesting starting from an example of ptr->val being sugar in the C programming language for (*ptr).val and continuing to further examples. Ran raised the issue of whether syntactic sugar was important or not, which turns out to not be a straightforward question. He then demonstrated some modules for syntactic sugar on CPAN.

I hope Ran can give a rerun of it on one of the mongers' meetings with more time allocated for that.

After that I attended the talk of Stefan Hornburg (“racke”, known as HORNBURG on CPAN) who was another visitor from Germany, about Template::Flute which is a designer’s friendly template system. In this template, one uses an HTML file with standard HTML attributes for designating the fields that needs to be replaced, and then an XML specification file that specifies how to process the HTML (and in addition one uses Perl to give it data). As a result the designers can manipulate the HTML with their own tools, while still allowing the programmers to populate it with data.

This seems like an interesting and potentially useful tool, but it’s less expressive than template systems such as Template Toolkit. After the talk, another attendee whom we talked in private questioned the need for both the HTML file and the XML specification, but I didn't find a way to avoid it given the constraints that the HTML will be valid HTML 4/XHTML 1.

The next talk about Time Management in Software Projects was cancelled because the presenter did not come (due to lack of time management as we joked then). I was able to catch a glimpse of the end of Dotan Dimet’s “Perl and JavaScript: bioinformatics in a browser window” talk, but I don’t remember a lot of it except for a small amount of demonstration.

The talk about Zero to CPAN was eventually given by Sawyer instead of by Erez Schatz. It was a nice one, and I’ve learned about the CPAN-Changes module there (after Florian mentioned it, though). Sawyer covered the way to get to a working CPAN-like distribution from scratch using tools such as module-starter and explained what every file in the CPAN module hierarchy does, and demonstrated some test-driven-development. I knew most of it already, but it was still a fun talk.

Amir Friedman‘s talk about software configuration management (SCM) came next, and he discussed some open-source solutions for the various parts of SCM, which include version control, release management, task management, and project management. He recommended Gitflow (which we had a talk about on the Tel Aviv mongers mailing list) for version control and release management, and a different solution called Jenkins for issue tracking (if I remember correctly). I then asked what he thought of integrated “all-in-one” solutions for SCM, and he said that those were pricey and he did not have any significant experience with them.

The lunch break came next and I overheard a talk between two other people about teaching English to speakers of non-English languages. One of them said that he once worked with some Spanish Electrical Engineers and that they were “completely isolated” from the rest of the world because they didn’t read the literature in English. Then we discussed whether it was economical to teach English to hundreds of millions of speakers of Spanish, or whether we should expect most things to be translated. It was compared to the “give a man a fish” vs. “teach a man to fish”. We also discussed the fact that Dutchmen tended to have very good English, and one of the other people commented that it was true, but that they still tended to prefer using software with Dutch localisation.

I’ve also talked with Sawyer about his upcoming “CGI.pm MUST DIE!” talk. He said that he needs to become mentally energised for that talk because he feels strongly about it and wants to convey the energy. He passed an anecdote from a conference in Europe, in which he had given a talk about Dancer, and said he was so emotional then that people said “You must see him” and rushed to see his other talk. Moreover, afterwards, when asked who were the two best presenters in the conference, they said “[Someone very famous] and that Dancer guy”.

The anti-CGI.pm presenting was indeed energetic and emotional, but kinda fell below my expectations due to the yard talk that preceded it. It was still pretty informative. Dotan Dimet later took the stage for the rebuttal of “CGI.pm - the only web development framework you’ll ever need” which was less emotional but still interesting. I was not convinced that CGI.pm’s HTML generation routines were a good way to do output HTML (I never really liked them), so I may have been more convinced by Sawyer.

Ynon Perek’s talk about “Implementing Perl (Moose) Design Patterns” came next, which was interesting, but again lacked adequate time to cover everything, and I hope will be given with less time constraints. One anecdote from there was that Ynon said there where three primary ways for polymorphism in Perl: Inheritance (“is-a”), Roles/Traits (“does-a”) and Containment/Delegation (“has-a”) and that he could no longer recommend inheritance (but did not get to explain why not from what I recall).

In any case, I was surprised at Ynon’s implementation of the Factory pattern, and don’t remember the implementation given by him.

Next came Tamir Lousky’s talk about generating vector graphics with Perl and SVG. Its slides contained a lot of very nice eye candy. The introduction to SVG and generating it was quite rudimentary, and did not cover the full potential of SVG. The demonstration and explanation of the module for generating random trees using SVG was interesting.

David Tabachnikov’s next gave an interesting talk called “Scaling Up”. He contrasted optimisation (which makes your code run faster with the existing resources) to vertical scaling (= buying faster computers) to Horizontal scaling (= buying more hardware). He also noted that there’s some speed difference between the various SQL databases, but he did not encounter a situation where it would have made too much difference.

The last feature of the evening were the lightning talks. I recall a talk by Florian Ragwitz about Google Code-In and Google Summer-of-Code. I also recall Gabor’s talk about surviving in an uncooperative workplace. He said that if the workplace does not practise best practices such as using version control systems or writing automated tests, one can create their own small island of sanity where they make use of that on their own, and gradually convince the rest of the organisation that it’s beneficial.

After the lightning talks, some people went to a local restaurant for dinner, but I decided against it because I was too tired from waking up early. As a result, I found someone who drove up north to drive me home, and got home.

In the schedule I noticed that one could go to a certain URL at O’Reilly and receive a free E-book of their choice. I used this opportunity to get the book Beautiful Code , which I have started reading.

The day was exhausting but very fun, and I enjoyed all the talks I attended. I’d like to thank the organisers of the event and most notably Gabor Szabo and Sawyer X, Shenkar college for providing the venue, Booking.com for the sponsorship, O’Reilly for the free book presents, the foreign guests who came to present and to attend, and all the other presenters, who volunteered to give talks.

I hope we can repeat this the next year.

Date: 09-04-2012
perl, april fools, joke

The Perl April Fools' Gag That Could Have Been

On my last entry, I told you that I have had an idea for a Perl-related April Fools’ day gag, and that I would possibly reveal it on 2-April with a big disclaimer on top, just for kicks. Well, it’s already 9-April, but I guess it is better late than never, right?

OK, here is the big disclaimer: THIS IS A JOKE. IT’S NOT SERIOUS. SO RELAX - IT IS NOT GOING TO HAPPEN SOON (AND HOPEFULLY WILL NOT EVER HAPPEN)..

OK, now let’s move on to the gag itself:

1 April 2012, Tel Aviv, Israel: the Perl foundation has announced today that by inspiration from Mozilla Firefox, the perl-porters (formerly known as perl5-porters) will adopt a schedule of a quarterly major release.

“Since version 6 of Perl has been claimed by a malevolent project that amounted to very little, we will release Perl version 7 next Summer, followed by Perl 8 in next Fall, and Perl 9 next Winter.” said the designated Perl pumpking.The Perl foundation commented that it is sure that users will appreciate the accelerated release schedule, despite the fact that a lot of backwards’ compatibility will be broken in each release to further the language’s improvement.

Some prominent Perl porters have added that they are looking into ways to automatically upgrade the Perl version automatically upon new releases, similar to the approach followed by the Google Chrome browser. “We are tired of people using outdated versions of Perl, which results in a maintenance burden for us, to say nothing of the security risk by bugs in old Perl versions. So we think the best way to mitigate that would be to simply force people to upgrade.”

The Perl porters are hard at work on perl-7.0.0, which will implement the upcoming Perl 7 specification with many new and exciting features and incompatibilities.

Well, like I said, after discussing this idea with RJBS (the current Perl 5 Pumpking), he and I agreed that it would be too cruel, given that many people are sensitive about upgrading their versions of Perl 5. Comparisons of how old the perl that your workplace/client/etc. has deployed on their systems is a common source of discussion among perl mongers (and someone told me one of his clients still used perl 4), and many people would have found such an announcement alarming instead of funny. But I hope you enjoyed reading it, and hope you're also looking forward to perl-5.16.0, which should be out soon.

Date: 09-07-2012
perl, begin, beginners, perl-begin, learn

What’s new on the Perl Beginners’s Site

The last update on the news feed for The Perl Beginners’s site was almost a year ago. While the site continued to improve, I neglected writing a new entry until now, so I hope this one will compensate for that.

So without further ado, here is what is new:

We now have a page about Perl Humour, which was restored from a page in the now offline perl.net.au wiki.

Also originally from that wiki is the Freenode’s #perl channel Frequently Asked Questions (FAQ) List, which is well worth a read.

Another restored page is the list of CPAN Wrappers for Distributions.

We added a page about web automation in Perl, and one about manipulating files and directories.

The Perl on Windows page was enhanced with new links to Strawberry Perl and DWIM Perl.

We have a new page about Perl Training Providers, which currently only contains a link to the Perl Training Directory.

The “Perl Elements to Avoid” page contains many new entries.

Our mirror of the book Modern Perl by chromatic was updated to its latest edition.

We hope you find these additions useful or enlightening.

Date: 22-07-2012
perl, cpan, dancer

Announcement: the App-Notifier CPAN Distributions

I would like to announce two new CPAN distributions of mine: App-Notifier-Service and App-Notifier-Client. These are derived from a few simplistic scripts I've written in shell and Perl, to allow me to notify when a task has finished (e.g: make ; finish-client) or a certain time has elapsed (e.g: sleep 240 ; finish-client), and I decided to create something more serious as CPAN modules.

App-Notifier-Service implements an HTTP service (using Dancer), which listens for requests, and once one arrives, implements a callback, which notifies the user on the localhost that the event occured. App-Notifier-Client complements it by implementing a client that connects to the service and sends the event.

Currently documentation may be lacking, and there are almost no automated tests in the distributions, but it appears to work nicely. To get started, read the documentation and you may wish to peruse some of these files from my home directory. First of all, the .app_notifier.yml file:

commands:
    default:
        - /home/shlomif/bin/desktop-finish-cue
    cookie:
        - /home/shlomif/bin/desktop-finish-cue
        - "--song"
        - "/home/music/Music/dosd-mp3s/Cookie.mp3"
client:
    targets:
        default:
            url: "http://localhost:6300/"
        lap:
            url: "http://lap.shlomifish.org:6300/"

The desktop-finish-cue file:

#!/bin/bash

song="/home/music/Music/dosd-mp3s/Theme - Eurovision.mp2"

param="$1"
shift
if test "$param" = "--song"; then
    arg="$1"
    shift
    song="$arg"
fi

xmessage "Your task has been finished! Go check it out." &
mplayer "$song"

And the finish-server script:

#!/bin/bash
cd "$HOME"/progs/perl/alert/http-based/hg/App-Notifier-Service &&
    perl ./bin/app.pl --port=6300

Otherwise, if you're in the Tel Aviv or vicinity, you are invited to the next Tel Aviv Perl Mongers meeting on Wednesday, 25 July 2012. Otherwise, I wish to note that I have written my first Java golf program as part of Anarchy golf’s “Alphabet Texture” challenge (Anarchy golf accepts challenges in many languages). At 167 bytes, it is over 3 times longer than the shortest Perl entry which is only 50 bytes (my Perl solution is 52 bytes). But it was fun to write. For your information, code golf is a challenge in which, participating programmers are challenged to write the shortest program that achieves a certain objective. I find it fun and addictive.

Date: 16-08-2012
perl, cpan, tip, tech, tech tip, mageia, linux

Tech Tip: How to Package and Maintain CPAN Distributions in Mageia

Mageia Linux is an RPM-based Linux distribution, whose repositories contain over 3,000 CPAN packages, and part of the reason why it has so many is because Jerome Quelin and the other maintainers have worked on tools to facilitate creating Mageia packages for CPAN distributions and maintaining them.

However, I was a little confused about using magpie, so I'd like to share my findings here:

In order to import, upload and submit a new CPAN package into Mageia, along with all of its dependencies, one should not use magpie, but rather cpan2pkg. Its use is very simple: make rpm and urpmi sudoable, and type cpan2pkg Package::Name from the command-line inside an X terminal. This will start a Tk window where one can monitor the progress of preparing new RPM packages and it has an entry box to create more packages (which saves time on re-initialising CPAN.pm or CPANPLUS.pm).

In order to upgrade a package, one can type eval $( magpie co -s perl-[PACKAGE_NAME] ) and then magpie update. magpie requires minicpan to be installed and updated.

In order to install packages, one can do sudo urpmi 'perl(Package::Name)'. My Module-Format module facilitates the translation from other notations for writing modules:

up()
{
    sudo urpmi --auto $(perlmf as_rpm_colon "$@")
}

Date: 01-09-2012
perl, foundation, tpf, grant, debugger, cpan, ruby

Grant for Improving the Perl Debugger + New CPAN Distributions

First of all, I am glad to announce that the Perl Foundation grant committee has accepted my grant proposal for adding tests and refactoring the built-in perl debugger. Here is the announcement for which grant proposals were accepted. My grant manager for this grant is Alan Haggai Alavi, whom I've been talking with online and have collaborated on a few projects, so I'm really happy to work with him again.

I have already made some progress with the grant (and this post is part of it), and sent a log for Alan Haggai to post as a grant update.

That put aside, I'd now like to publicise some of the new distributions I have uploaded to CPAN, as I had some ideas for new ones, and am also contemplating making enough uploads to have 100 CPAN distributions or more:

WWW-LinkChecker-Internal is a distribution wrapping a script that checks for internal broken links. I released the first three versions of it in a day, and it uses WWW::Mechanize. The reason why I wrote it was that the WDG HTML validator reported some broken links in one of my sites, but not their origins, so I had to trace them in a different way, and ended up writing that.

Inline-Ruby is an Inline:: distribution I adopted that allows to embed Ruby code inside Perl programs. I applied some fixes for it (some of which were not released to CPAN yet and some are ugly workarounds), and am planning to maintain it further down the road.

Test-TrailingSpace is a Test:: namespace distribution for verifying that your code does not contain trailing space. Death to trailing space!

A final anecdote is that when working on one of my CPAN modules I found the b [filename]:[line_num] feature that I implemented in the perl debugger to be of great help, and can be content that I'm eating my own dogfood.

Cheers for now.

Date: 09-09-2012
tech, tip, tech tip, perl, eumm, compiler, gcc, clang

Tech Tip: Overriding the C compiler with ExtUtils::MakeMaker

In order to override the C compiler with ExtUtils::MakeMaker, one can do something like:

perl Makefile.PL CC=/usr/bin/clang

Which will make the "CC" variable in the generated makefile be set to /usr/bin/clang instead of the default. Apparently, setting the CC environment variable does not work like it does with CMake.

Thanks to Sisyphus for the tip.

Date: 18-10-2012
lwn, lwn.net, events, perl, conferences, yapc

Please Publish Perl Events on the LWN.net Calendar

As I read last week’s LWN.net’s Announcement Page (LWN.net is a news site for open-source-related news, formerly standing for “Linux Weekly News”), I noticed that there were few if any Perl events featured in its upcoming events calendar. However, these events appear in the Perl Weekly, and there are many upcoming Python events featured in LWN.net.

So, please, if you are organising a Perl-related event (or any other major open-source event), make sure you put it on the LWN.net calendar.

Date: 14-11-2012
cpan, perl, command, line, cli, bash, gnu, parallel, sleep

Three Command-Line Utilities

So, November is NaNoWriMo (“National Novel Writing Month”), and I was hoping to get some serious writing done (instead of coding), but I kept being distracted with coding and random writing in various Internet forums. Well, hopefully this blog post will compensate a little for that.

In this post, I’d like to cover three command-line utilities - two of them new and were written by me, and one of them somewhat older, but also written in Perl.

The first utility is GNU Parallel, which allows one to run several command-line jobs in parallel, using forking and/or ssh remote logins. I used it to speed up some processing I've been doing on my computer. For more information and some examples of usage, see my post about it to the linux-elitists mailing list, and also read Thomas Sattler’s response which provides some further insights.

The second utility is countdown, which is similar to the UNIX command-line sleep command, but displays the remaining time on the console. I wrote a prototype for it in Perl 6, only to discover it consumed far too many resources. The second prototype, as a Perl 5 program consumed close to zero resources of my computer. Yesterday, I converted it to a modulino (a Perl application implemented as a module) and uploaded several versions to the CPAN.

The third utility is something I have placed in my ~/.bashrc file in order to implement reminders when the shell starts. The code for it is:

reminder_file="$HOME/.local/share/shlomif/reminder/reminder.txt"
if [ -s "$reminder_file" ] ; then
    perl -Mstrict -Mwarnings -MTerm::ANSIColor -E 'my $x = colored("===", "bold red"); say "$x Reminders $x"'
    cat "$reminder_file"
fi

Cancel_reminder()
{
    rm "$reminder_file"
}

I wrote it because I wasn't prompted in time by Thunderbird+Lightning due to a strange bug, and because I had to ditch KOrganizer because it consumed too many resources here. This displays the Reminders whenever you start a new shell, which happens quite often with me, so it's OK. I use cron jobs to append stuff into "$reminder_file", and the Perl code displays a header in colour.

That’s it for today. App-Countdown is one step closer for the count-up (pun intended) towards the coveted 100 distributions under “SHLOMIF” on CPAN, so that's another plus.

Date: 06-12-2012
cpan, perl, xml, 100, hacktivity, hacktivity log, javascript, llvm

Count-up to 100 CPAN Distributions: Test-XML-Ordered, SDLx-Betweener, and more

Well, it's no longer a secret that I’m craving to join the “100 CPAN Distributions Club” by releasing some code that is hopefully not too useless. Here I would like to blog about the two new additions to my CPAN page which are the 83rd and 84th distributions respectively. The story is a bit more complicated than that.

The first upload is SDLx-Betweener, which allows for creating high-performance and smooth animations in SDL by making use of Perl/XS. Almost all of the coding (and a related YAPC::Israel talk) was done by Ran Eilam, who is a very cool guy, a good friend and a former boss of mine, and I've just done (with his permission) some last-minute cleanups and did the initial upload to CPAN. So I kinda feel like the frog that sat on top of the elephant who crossed the river and said “We did it!”.

However, I needed SDLx::Betweener for something I've been intending to work on, and wanted it on CPAN and packaged in Mageia Linux, so I did that. If you run into any problems with it, drop me a note or file a bug report, and hopefully I can resolve these problems (possibly with some help from Ran).

The next distribution is original, but its story is more complicated. It all started when I decided to resume work on Qantor, which aims to eventually be a modern and saner alternative to TeX/LaTeX and Troff (although it is still extremely far from that now). I noticed that the parsing was still done by Regexp::Grammars, and so decided to convert it into Parser::MGC. Parser::MGC worked eventually and I was impressed from the straightforward way to do stuff with it, but it was time consuming to get there (like most other parser generators I tried, only a bit better), and involved writing some Moose 'around' code to debug the method calls, and also sometimes delving into the code. Parser::MGC is still not perfect (and some of the code I read there had gems like die $e if $committed or not eval { $e->isa( "Parser::MGC::Failure" ) }; which I found hard to parse, and made me want to drown a kitten), but I think it sucks less and is more transparent than other parser generators I tried.

Anyway, after I got it working, I noticed that the Test::XML::Ordered code (then still unreleased), generated a some memory problems and I suspected either XML::LibXML or libxml2 to be the culprit. This involved a long investigation process with valgrind, gdb, perl -d and other tools which culminated in a very small change and more lines of test code. This was released in XML::LibXML. After that I received a report that the tests got stuck, but that turned out to be due to external loading of DTDs and was easily fixed. There's another report for a problem with perl-5.8.8 (ouch!) on Red Hat Enterprise Linux (ouch again!), but I'm not too motivated to do a lot about it (see this fortune cookie).

Well, after I fixed the problem with XML::LibXML, I decided to release Test::XML::Ordered. I'm well aware of Test::XML, but found it hard to rely on it, because it uses XML::SemanticDiff (the latter I adopted) and which attempts to rearrange the order of the nodes when it sees fit (so <ul><li>One</li><li>Two</li></ul> and <ul><li>Two</li><li>One</li></ul> may be considered the same), which was not what I want and not what other people who contacted me about XML::SemanticDiff wanted.

After Test::XML::Ordered, I decided it would be a good idea to finally work on the release of XML::GrammarBase which aims to provide “base classes and roles” for facilitating creating XML validators and processors. Work on it was pretty straightforward after I had Test::XML::Ordered available, but required some refactoring the classes from using Any::Moose to using Moo per advice of the people on #moose, and I have yet to convert the XSLT role into a parameterised role.

I have some other code I'd like to release on CPAN after all that.

Another related hacktivity was a set of patches to the core Vim that I've written to improve support for DocBook 5. Since I wanted to maintain compatibility with DocBook 4 documents (because DocBook 4 is still popular), this involved writing a Perl, Bash and Python Amalgam to generate the Vim code in question with a list of common, DocBook 4-only and DocBook 5-only tags. You can find it in its BitBucket repository. It is very hacky, but it works. Using the Python code gave me an idea for a missing XML::LibXML feature - DTD introspection - which I'd like to implement in the future.

Well, that's all for now - just wanted to get it out of my system. Enjoy the holidays, and Cheers!

Date: 07-01-2013
cpan, perl, sdlx, xml, 100, hacktivity, hacktivity log

Count-up to 100 CPAN Distributions: Quality *as well as* Quantity

Going over the previous count-ups to 100 CPAN distributions in this blog, I feel I have been carried away: I tried to release a lot of new distributions to the CPAN, while neglecting all the existing distributions I have, and not tending to their pending problems and their lack of software quality in several aspects (See an older essay I have written about it).

I was reminded of it when working on a few new or existing distributions using Dist-Zilla. I ran into a few places where some of its plugins or features were underdocumented, and non-exemplified (in the SYNOPSIS sections or wherever), which consumed many hours of my time, sometimes made me need to read or grep the code, and made me frustrated. While I sent the maintainers some pull requests for better documenting this (and some of them were applied), I would have prefered for them to be properly documented and exemplified in the first place.

While I believe most of my CPAN distributions are in better condition, there are some aspects that are lacking, and I would like to fix them: more examples outside the SYNOPSES, and better SYNOPSES; documenting all methods of the super classes as well as the classes themselves for XML-LibXML; adding support for DTD introspection and the oft requested DOM elements annotations for it; more kwalitee; etc. and naturally also better publicity and advertising (Freecode.com (formerly known as Freshmeat.net), Reddit, blogs.perl.org, video screencasts, etc.) because people should see how cool your code is. I’m not sure if any of these things would be as blog worthy as new CPAN distributions, but it will make CPAN a bit better.

(Now that I think of it, perhaps a CPAN janitors initiative, which will submit pull requests and patches for existing distributions to improve their quality will be a good idea.)

Anyway, I am going to split this report into sections:

XML-GrammarBase

After some work (and misunderstanding of some of the Moo / MooX documentation, which resulted in some pull requests), I released XML-GrammarBase which aims provides roles and base classes for easily writing wrappers around XML schema formats and XML translation languages. So far only RELAXNG and XSLT are supported. Here is the synopsis from the docs:

package XML::Grammar::MyGrammar::ToOtherStuff;

use MooX 'late';

use XML::GrammarBase::Role::RelaxNG;
use XML::GrammarBase::Role::XSLT;

with ('XML::GrammarBase::Role::RelaxNG');
with XSLT(output_format => 'html');
with XSLT(output_format => 'docbook');

has '+module_base' => (default => 'XML-Grammar-MyGrammar');
has '+rng_schema_basename' => (default => 'my-grammar.rng');

has '+to_html_xslt_transform_basename' => (default => 'mygrammar-xml-to-html.xslt');
has '+to_docbook_xslt_transform_basename' => (default => 'mygrammar-xml-to-docbook.xslt');

package main;

my $xslt = XML::Grammar::MyGrammar::ToOtherStuff->new(
    data_dir => "/path/to/data-dir",
);

# Throws an exception on failure.
my $as_html = $xslt->perform_xslt_translation(
    {
        output_format => 'html'
        source => {file => $input_filename, },
        output => "string",
    }
);

perform_xslt_translation supports myriad options and formats, and you get it all for free.

I've also been contemplating something like App::XML::GrammarBase or XML::GrammarBase::App that will allow for easy registry of such formats from the command line and for processing them.

At first, I believed that Moo was “almost-completely-unlike-Moose”, but «use MooX 'late';» makes it much more Moose-like and I enjoy it, and it is now recommended over Any::Moose or maybe even plain Mouse. Mouse is very fast as well and has a far smaller startup time than Moose, but it does not interoperate very well with pure-Moose classes, which Moo does well.

HTML-Widgets-NavMenu-ToJSON

As I was working on my homepage, I noticed that after I placed all the sub-navigation menus inside the main navigation menu, it increased the size of the navigation menu considerably, having it consume over 40,000 bytes. I decided to put only a subset of it as HTML, and load and populate the rest using an AJAX call to a common and static .json file. So I needed a way to convert the input of HTML-Widgets-NavMenu

So enter HTML::Widgets::NavMenu::ToJSON, which serialises a navigation menu structure as JSON. I also implemented a persistence layer for it, currently with only one backend - a YAML file, so the IDs which jqTree require would be, well, persisted. This is a bit of an architecture astronautics, but I ended up with something concrete at the end so it's under control.

Here is the synopsis:

use HTML::Widgets::NavMenu::ToJSON;
use HTML::Widgets::NavMenu::ToJSON::Data_Persistence::YAML;

my $persistence =
    HTML::Widgets::NavMenu::ToJSON::Data_Persistence::YAML->new(
        {
            filename => '/path/to/persistence_data.yaml',
        }
    );

my $obj = HTML::Widgets::NavMenu::ToJSON->new(
    {
        data_persistence_store => $persistence,
        # The one given as input to HTML::Widgets::NavMenu
        tree_contents => $tree_contents,
    }
);

use IO::All;

io->file('output.json')->println(
    $obj->output_as_json(
        {
            %args
        }
    )
);

It could be made a bit simpler using an abstraction, but I feel it's not too bad. You can write custom HTML::Widgets::NavMenu::ToJSON::Data_Persistence child classes by implementing the load() and save() methods - I did not document the process yet, but you can base your efforts on HTML::Widgets::NavMenu::ToJSON::Data_Persistence::YAML.

Dist-Zilla-Plugin-TestRun

Since I'm used to running ./Build runtest instead of ./Build test for my distributions, I sought a way of doing the same using Dist-Zilla. It turned out there wasn't an easy way, and Dist-Zilla-Plugin-TestRun is the best I could do. I hope to write a patch to make the test command more configurable.

Test-XML-Ordered

Test::XML::Ordered makes a non-“semantic” diff of XML files and tells you if they are equivalent (up to differences of whitespace and namespace prefixes). It grew out of my frustration with XML::SemanticDiff, upon which Test::XML is based, and which I maintain. A quick CPAN search revealed other modules for testing XML in a similar manner, but since I have already written my code, I decided to release it.

One tip is that with the current API, one should use something like:

my @common = (validation => 0, load_ext_dtd => 0, no_network => 1);

is_xml_ordered (
    [ string => normalize_xml($results_buffer), @common, ],
    [ location => "./t/data/xhtml-results/$fn_base.xhtml", @common, ],
    "Testing for Good XSLTing of '$fn_base'",
);

In order to test XHTML documents for equivalency.

Vered-XML

I thought that Vered-XML (currently only available in the Perl Beginners’ Site’s repository was probably the most ad-hoc and tailored to match XML grammar I have ever created, and was used to convert the markup of the “Perl Elements to Avoid” page from hacky Website META Language markup to XML, so it will be easier to translate to different (human) languages and also somewhat easier to maintain and render. Currently it renders to DocBook/XML, which allows translation to many other formats.

So why did I call it Vered? Since it was so ad-hoc, and I didn't know what else it would be useful for, I wanted to give it an artsy name, and considered using a random Hebrew feminine name. Then I thought that “a rose by any other name would smell as sweer”, and thought of calling it Rose, but translated to Hebrew it was “Vered”, which is also a Hebrew feminine name. I still have to tie up some loose ends, but expect XML-Grammar-Vered at a CPAN mirror near you Real Soon Now™.

Vered-XML supports a subset of XHTML, as well as some specialised tags such as <pdoc /> (perldoc), <pdoc_f /> (perldoc -f), <cpan_self_mod /> (CPAN self link to module), etc. and contains a RELAX NG schema and an xsltproc/libxslt2-compatible XSLT 1.0 stylesheet. Here is an excerpt from the “Perl Elements to Avoid” source XML:

<item xml:id="slurp">
<info>
<title>Slurping a file (i.e: Reading it all into memory)</title>
</info>
<p>
One can see several bad ways to read a file into memory in Perl. Among them
are:
</p>
<code_blk syntax="perl">
# Not portable and suffers from possible
# shell code injection.
my $contents = `cat $filename`;
# Wasteful of CPU and memory:
my $contents = join("", &lt;$fh&gt;);
# Even more so:
my $contents = '';
while (my $line = &lt;$fh&gt;)
{
    $contents .= $line;
}
</code_blk>
<p>
You should avoid them all. Instead the proper way to read an entire file
into a long string is to either use CPAN distributions for that such as
<cpan_self_dist d="File-Slurp" /> or
<cpan_self_dist d="IO-All" />, or alternatively
write down the following function and use it:
</p>
<code_blk syntax="perl">
sub _slurp
{
    my $filename = shift;
    open my $in, '&lt;', $filename
        or die "Cannot open '$filename' for slurping - $!";
    local $/;
    my $contents = &lt;$in&gt;;
    close($in);
    return $contents;
}
</code_blk>
</item>

I'm not sure if Vered-XML will have much utility outside that use case, but I think that putting it on CPAN won't hurt much.

Improving perlresume.org

I filed a few issues and sent some pull requests for perlresume.org for some problems I ran into, and vti fixed or applied them promptly. Thanks!

Beginners’ Sites

I invested more work into the Perl Beginners’ site and also, after some encouragement from the good people on #vim began work on the Vim Beginners’s site, which I publicised on my tech blog, on Reddit, and on some mailing lists. While in the past I used my own static site generator called “Latemp” based on Website Meta Language for sites like that, I used Jekyll this time, at least for the first prototype. I did so in order to evaluate it for use in a different site (The Israeli Linux Portal which is currently implemented using an awkward custom PHP-based system, that mostly just reads stuff out of XML data files and outputs a constant static HTML as XSLT.). While at first I was impressed with Jekyll, I then realised that it was quite opaque, often required many plugins to get some basic functionality and that one plugin I looked at lacked examples and was otherwise under documented.

There is a list of many more static site generators / offline content-management systems around (which does not include my own Latemp), and it may be easier to roll up something on my own based on Template Toolkit or its ttree. All this just confirms my (and Su-Shee’s) suspicion that every self-respecting web programmer has written at least one.

Freecell Solver for JavaScript - ☺

I have been distracted for many hours trying to port Freecell Solver to JavaScript using the very cool Emscripten LLVM bitcode to JavaScript compiler. The mostly final result could still use some work, and is still under optimised (in large part due to what appear to be an Emscripten bug) but it's working.

The Emscripten wiki contains links to many, much more impressive, demos including a JavaScript version of the open-source graphical game “Me and My Shadow”.

Two Anecdotes from ##programming

I enjoy chatting on ##programming (on Freenode) and along with all the rants about how much every popular programming langauge in existence sucks, and trying to help various students with their often badly indented and badly formatted homework code, there are often some insightful discussions by some smart people. I’d like to share two Perl-related anecdotes from there.

The first one was that someone there who has taken studying programming, before starting to study in university, seriously, and also read the Camel book and other books and resources about Perl, asked me to look at my code to see how readable it is. I referred him to the source code of HTML::Widgets::NavMenu, which will being an early code of mine (and still not fully modernised), was written in a modular manner, and he said he found it to be well-factored and yet very readable . He noted that he suspected that Perl would be less believed to “hard to understand” or “unreadable”, if it sandardised on using my preferred style - Allman style - instead of its default style with the opening braces on the same line as the opening clause (e.g: if ( COND ) {).

The other anecdote was that someone else there, who is working in Visual Basic and Visual Basic for Applications for a living (for lack of good alternative for software development job prospects in his homeland), told us that he found the CPAN documentation to usually be superior than the MSDN (Microsoft Developers Network) one. I found it a little strange, because I recall finding the MSDN documentation to give detailed examples for almost every subroutine and a page of prose and explanation for each one, and reportedly large parts of it were also translated into some non-English languages by Microsoft. Then I showed him the “SYNOPSIS” sections of some of the .pm files in CPAN and he was even more impressed and said it was useful (because you can copy+paste it and tweak it), but naturally commented that not all .pm files had those.

Conclusion

I currently stand at 87 CPAN distributions, some of which a bit lacking, and I still have some in the pipe. One of them will require quite a lot of cleanup work to do, but it's not a high priority. I also have to juggle some other endeavours, and also recently started contracting for an Internet friend as a Drupal developer (and in the future possibly one for Moodle as well), which may consume even more of my time (but on the bright side pay a little money). It’s no secret that I am not a big fan of PHP, but Drupal seems impressive so far, and hides away a lot of PHP’s ugliness. It took me some time to get acquainted with it, so I hope now things will be smoother and easier to do. It seems that there's quite a bit of demand for converting sites into Drupal, setting up new sites, or maintaining them in Israel (and possibly elsewhere as well) so it is probably a useful skill to have under my belt.

Hope you enjoyed this hacktivity log, and see you next time. Byeeeee!

Date: 07-01-2013
tdd, tests, philosophy, essay

Essay: “Just write the God-damn tests, motherfucker!”

(I originally wrote this in a post to qa@perl.org, and I apologise for the profanity in the title, but I felt it is needed in this case.)

So why am I writing this? I used to feel guilty about not being conscious of the distinction between the various scopes of tests, like unit tests vs. integration tests vs. system tests vs. functional tests etc. when I wrote the tests. I just noticed that I need a test here (as a regression test for a bug, or to TDD (= test-driven develop a new feature, or after implementing a new feature, etc.), and wrote it using Test::More or whatever. However, now I feel that trying to philosophise about the distinction between all those is not so useful for the people who are actually trying to write the tests.

Tests are good, mmkay? Just freaking write them!

chromatic has expressed some sentiments against the so-called “Behaviour Driven Development” (BDD) Domain-specific-languages (DSLs) such as cucumber.

One thing that he notes in a comment there is:

Our clients are the parents, guardians, and teachers of children between the ages of eight and twelve inclusive.

The intent of Cucumber is to make readable testcases, just as the intent of COBOL and AppleScript and visual component programming is to enable non-programmers to create software without having to learn how to program.

It is impossible to have people who are non-programmers write structure code without learning how to program, at least until we get sufficiently intelligent Sci-Fi-like artificial intelligence (not the current crop of artificial ultra-stupidities) that will be able to perform programming like humans do, and will be willing to do so, while not having free will and still be obedient to us, and that will perform adequately. I feel that you need to write some kind of code, however formatted, to write tests, just like HTML and CSS and spreadsheet programs, involve writing some kind of *code*.

If you want to have your clients write tests, my best suggestion is to either instruct them in the proper methodology and discipline of coding, or alternatively have them show you how to reproduce the problem (using screenshots, screencasts, shared remote desktop sessions, etc.) and then you should write a test for it.

Some people fear that teaching laymen how to code will create competition for professional programmers, and dilute the profession. However, this is not true, because there's always a difference between a casual dealer in a craftsmanship or art, and someone who invested a substantial amount of time doing it. E.g: lots of people can cook well, but not everyone is a professional Chef, and Chefs still often teach other people cooking, or share their recipes, because that does not dilute their profession.

So I think the distinction between the various tests may be useful for methodologists and software engineering researchers (people who try to guide other people how to code) more than the people who are actually coding. To quote Picasso: “When art critics get together they talk about Form and Structure and Meaning. When artists get together they talk about where you can buy cheap turpentine.” ( taken from Ori Peleg’s blog ).

Similarly, literature critics and researchers have very little to say that is of use for most writers and even authors. I hated studying Literature (what Americans might call “English” although naturally in Israel, we study Hebrew texts) with a passion, and didn't do too well on the tests (in part because out of personal honesty, I refused to write a lot of extraneous text, which the teacher seemed to have preferred), only to become a writer of fiction and essays (see Paul Graham’s “The Age of the Essay” for why they are not only about literature) after graduation. Furthermore, most people I talked with seem to have liked and appreciate the textual works I have written (although I admit they are certainly not letter perfect), and I could usually find some value in the criticisms of people who did not, even if expressed very destructively, and often was able to improve my works accordingly.

Similarly, I'm now struggling with this tome which seems like I cannot see the forest for the trees from it, while I really enjoyed reading the much shorter and much more hands-on Test Driven Development by Example (by Kent Back).

The time we talk about how to write tests is often better spent writing tests (or production code, which is, naturally, what tests are aimed to support and are meaningless without it), so I think we should just “freaking write them”.

Just write the god-damn test, motherfucker!

( Note: the title of this essay was inspired by the “Programming, Motherfucker” of Zed Shaw, which is very amusing, even if it seems to be written in a somewhat ironic tone, and that contains the useful huge list of free books for learning programming. )

Licence

As opposed to most of my previous essays, this work is Copyright by Shlomi Fish, 2013, under the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported licence, with a deliberate exemption for using the text on web pages with web commercials. For more information, see my interpretation of the licence. If you wish to use it under any different licence, then drop me a line.

Date: 07-01-2013
cpan, perl, philosophy, humor, humour, hacking

ANN: My Transition From Software Developer to Writer/Entertainer/Amateur Philosopher/Internet Celebrity

I’d like to make an announcement: after some serious thought, I decided that from now on, being a software developer (which I am not too bad at) will only be the means (but the absolutely necessary ones) to me being a writer / entertainer / philosopher / Internet celebrity (a little bit of all those and then some) whose main pride and passion is his personal web site, which is full of a lot of material, and various pages and material is constantly added to it.

Note: I am not going to “quit” from the Perl world or am going to stop programming completely. In fact, programming in HTML, XHTML, CSS, XSLT, Website Meta Language, Perl 5, Bash, Vim/gvim, and many other general purpose and/or domain-specific languages, is absolutely necessary for what I do on a daily basis. Furthermore, I have little patience for laymen who do not wish to learn HTML, and just require more and more of our (= my peers and mine's) time to be wasted in a typical “Parable of the broken window” fashion. I think even most of our sisters, mothers (and yes, I'm being facetiously sexist on purpose, because a lot of the most clueless people we can think of are male), etc. can learn some basic programming skills and even be good at that with the right attitude. When put in a corner, they will be forced to learn it. and that programming is becoming more and more essential for everyone to know. Furthermore, clients who wish to remain ignorant (and often hostile) forever should be avoided, with a clear honest and sincere explanation telling them why and how to improve.

Anyway, as is evident from my first story, I have already made a gradual transition from being a mathematician and a mathematical logician, to being a software developer and web developer, so now it's another transition. It took me a lot of time to hone my skills as a writer of stories, screenplays, aphorisms, Chuck Norris/etc. factoids, etc. etc. so it’s now much easier for me. It took me over a year to write my first story, but now I can whip up text fairly quickly, and find it enjoyable. Moreover, I now also have not one - but two ideas for new stories - both of which I have not started writing.

One implication is that I decided to transfer the maintenance of XML::LibXML to someone else, because while I believe I proved myself of utility in maintaing it, I find it hard to keep with its ongoing maintenance. One can easily fork its bitbucket repository, or given enough motivation, one can set up a similar one on GitHub or wherever (I recall receiving several patches with “--git” there) so if you have the skills, time, and motivation - just do it, and I’ll just upload the archives on your behalf (and eventually ask for giving you COMAINT). I have mentioned some ideas about what I have in mind for XML-LibXML elsewhere and you can always ask me on IM or IRC.

“Putting all the cards on the table - 2013”

I have started to write an essay on my “Unarmed but still Dangerous” blog titled “Putting all the Cards on the Table” - I start from the Technion, M.I.T., the film Silver Linings Playbook and its lead actress - Ms. Jennifer Lawrence (♥!) and goes on to discuss lots of other stuff including David vs. Goliath, computer networking, the second major battle that Chuck Norris lost, and to why we should initiate action (any action) instead of letting things go from bad to worse on their own, and there is much more to come. Hopefully, it will be amateur philosophy ( where amateur is someone who: 1) Loves what he does. 2) Is not professional. 3) Does not play by the same rules as professionals. - i.e: what we often call today as “hackers”) at the best I can do.

My main issue is that I felt the truly amateuristic intellectuals like me have been speaking too much in riddles, and that even I have been lying to myself and hiding many things from other people, and I want to offload everything I know as of March, 2013 (and it may be very different 10 years from now or even a year from now). And I want to do it in a truly honest, sincere, and putting all the cards I have now on the table fashion. There is a lot of humour in the essay, and a lot of personal analogies and references, some sex talk, (even sexism) and personal reflections (and my typical self-promotion), but it's still serious, honest, and sincere, and hopefully enjoyable.

Please comment on it on the blog, where you should be able to register using any OpenID provider, but anonymous comments, that are not spam, and where you give a link to identify yourself can also be done (just please preview the comment before sending it). I am planning on working on further publicity.

How to Achieve World Domination

A lot of people think that the proper way to achieve world domination is to create an architecture that will solve the whole world’s problems and then some. We’ve been seeing quite a few of them since Joel on Software wrote this article: Ruby, Google Go, Node.js, Mozilla’s Rust, Clojure, Scala, Perl 6, etc. Some of them have or will mature to something truly nice, or have inspired a lot of features in other languages, but it’s hard for plain-old-single-you to compete with them, and here is something interesting: not too many people want them.

What do people want? Chuck Norris/etc. factoids, lolcats and other captioned images, funny cat videos, parodies of My Little Pony: Friendship is Magic (♥), photos of attractive (or even not too attractive) men and women, screencasts of games or other programs (including many open source programs), photos of scenery, new and improved recipes for preparing food (and of course - tasty food itself), new, old or renovated jokes, and some interesting tales and anecdotes from your life. And naturally - programs that can will scratch an itch - however small.

Some people told me that my solver for Freecell and other solitaire games, simply called Freecell Solver is useless, but it's not - it's just a niche program. And I received hundreds of E-mails about it. Furthermore, given that Freecell is (or used to be) a big phenomenon in Israel, where many boys and girls starting from 18 found themselves playing it on the Israeli military computers out of boredom, then the fact that I have written a solver for it, has impressed many people I talked with or met, including some attractive (both physically and intellectually) young ladies (or what people may refer to as “hot chicks”), and they ended up asking me about how it was written, and which algorithms it employed.

So Freecell Solver was one of my most successful programs, not despite being a niche program, but because of it. Niche programs own. Not only that, but niche everything is great. Many people whom I referred to my stories helped themselves to the screenplay Star Trek: “We, the Living Dead” because it contained Star Trek in the name, and because there are quite a few fans of the Star Trek franchise and worlds.

The more of a niche artwork you write, the more a large subset of those who like it, are likely to pay attention to it, try it out, and enjoy it. For more information, see Eric Sink’s excellent and inspiring essay “How to get people talking about your product”. For example, DuckDuckGo was originally marketed as a search engine by Perl geeks, and for Perl geeks, and it was a good marketing decision because the Perl community is small, cohesive and is at a good strategical position to influence other communities. Now, many people who are not Perl programmers, are using it, as well as, or even in preference to Google, but choosing Perl was a good strategical decision. We can expect that with the future growth of DuckDuckGo, that it will use more performant technologies than Perl more and more, but it will still owe some of its initial success to be a Perl product.

Date: 13-04-2013
perl, philosophy, humor, hacktivity log, xml, films, fiction

Recent Hacktivity Log

This is another recent hacktivity log of what I have been up to recently, as far as software development and writing is concerned.

“Every Publicity is Good Publicity…”

True to my belief that “The Gods help them that help themselves”, I have been working much more on publicity recently, utilising my Twitter account, my Reddit account, my Facebook account and other online resources. I am not exclusively promoting only my own works, and also share/retweet/etc. the posts of my friends. I had great success with this /r/xkcd subreddit post which so far received 150 upvotes (and 36 down votes) about my new screenplay Summerschool at the NSA which has a strong xkcd (= the web comics) theme, and also had some lesser success with posts to other subreddits. As usual, I also upvote and comment on other people's posts and comments.

It seems that the main problem with my site up to now has not been that it lacked good content, but that most people were not aware of the site.

I’ve also been experimenting with buying Project Wonderful web advertisements, but so far they did not yield too many clicks.

The Olamot Sci-Fi/Fantasy Conference

As I reported on the Hamakor mailing list, I attended the Olamot Science-Fiction/Fantasy/etc. conference that took place during Passover in Tel Aviv, Israel, and had a great time. I didn't bring a camera to the first day, so people on IRC did not believe me that I saw many highly attractive geeks there, which I remedied by bringing a camera and taking many photos during the second day.

The conference was colourful, zany, and inspiring and most of the people I saw agreed to be photographed. I spent most of the time there helping with the booth of the open source community and we were better organised and more prepared than a similar conference several years ago, where we only had a very huge and heavy Sun CRT screen that did not yield to our attempts to get it to display something on the computer.

Work on Selina Mandrake - The Slayer (a Buffy Parody)

I was able to mostly complete my work on the screenplay Selina Mandrake - The Slayer, which is marketed as a parody of Buffy the Vampire Slayer, but which also crosses over many other elements, including from Star Trek: Deep Space Nine, Judaism, history of the Near East and Europe, and computer geekdom. It is in a usable condition now, but there are still some missing scenes, and the screenplay may also need some polishing.

Buffy and Clarissa Facts

In the name of girl power, and FOR GREAT JUSTICE, I have continued to collect factoids about females: Buffy Summers from the show Buffy the Vampire Slayer, and and Clarissa Darling from Clarissa Explains It All (which I fear no one is familiar with or remember now, but still makes for some awesome factoids). Additions are welcome.

Summerschool at the NSA

I got the idea for the screenplay Summerschool at the NSA during the Olamot conference mentioned above, and I am thankful for such great conference for providing a lot of inspiration. I was able to complete the screenplay in less than two weeks and it is in a usable condition now (but likely still has many rough spots). Quoting from the abstract:

The Hollywood actresses Sarah Michelle Gellar (of Buffy fame) and Summer Glau (of xkcd notability) conspire to kick the ass of the NSA (= the United States government’s National Security Agency), while using special warfare that is completely non-violent.

This screenplay crosses Judaism, the Mother Goose nursary rhymes, My Little Pony, substance/etc. addiction, xkcd, Buffy, the song “99 Problems” by Jay-Z, and some personal insights and memes, and despite all that is actually mostly realism for a change.

“All Truth is God’s Truth”

Some people, with whom I talked on the Freenode chat network, complained that I didn’t stay loyal to my Jewish roots, and instead crossed Judaism with other idea system, and some newer sources of influence. However I’d like to quote Larry Wall from his “Perl Culture” keynote:

I have a book on my bookshelf that I’ve never read, but that has a great title. It says, “All Truth is God’s Truth.” And I believe that. The most viable belief systems are those that can reach out and incorporate new ideas, new memes, new metaphors, new interfaces, new extensions, new ways of doing things. My goal this year is to try to get Perl to reach out and cooperate with Java. I know it may be difficult for some of you to swallow, but Java is not the enemy. Nor is Lisp, or Python, or Tcl. That is not to say that these languages don't have good and bad points. I am not a cultural relativist. Nor am I a linguistic relativist. In case you hadn't noticed. :-)

Furthermore, like Ayn Rand noted in her journal, a good work of fiction requires a solid philosophy, and so one can learn a lot from works of fiction. Furthermore, Peter Ustinov noted that “Comedy is simply a funny way of being serious.”, so even humorous works of art convey a good philosophy.

I think the main difference between contemporary or old works of fiction, such as the Greek mythology, Aesop’s fables, the works of Alexandre Dumas Pere, Star Trek, Buffy, etc. and “holy” works such as the Holy Bible or the Qur’an is that some people still take the latter too seriously, and consider them the final word on how to lead your life, rather than just another step in the road to enlightenment.

So I’m not going to let my personal philosophy stagnate by sticking only to traditional Judaism, which itself was never pure, and always incorporated many useful ideas from elsewhere, and still should.

XML-Grammar-Screenplay / XML-Grammar-Fiction

When working on the screenplays, I noticed that some of the error messages were quite unhelpful, so I implemented more informative error messages in XML-Grammar-Fiction / XML-Grammar-Screenplay. I noticed that the code was getting quite complicated, so I refactored it a little, but there is still a long way to go.

Freecell Solver

Someone reported problems understanding the solutions of the online (JS-based) port of Freecell Solver, and I decided to convert the card suit identifiers to their Unicode equivalents. So from:

Foundations: H-0 C-0 D-0 S-0
Freecells:
: 4C 2C 9C 8C QS 4S 2H
: 5H QH 3C AC 3H 4H QD
: QC 9S 6H 9H 3S KS 3D
: 5D 2S JC 5C JH 6D AS
: 2D KD TH TC TD 8D
: 7H JS KH TS KC 7C
: AH 5S 6S AD 8H JD
: 7S 6C 7D 4D 8S 9D

We get:

Foundations: ♥-0 ♣-0 ♦-0 ♠-0
Freecells:
: 4♣ 2♣ 9♣ 8♣ Q♠ 4♠ 2♥
: 5♥ Q♥ 3♣ A♣ 3♥ 4♥ Q♦
: Q♣ 9♠ 6♥ 9♥ 3♠ K♠ 3♦
: 5♦ 2♠ J♣ 5♣ J♥ 6♦ A♠
: 2♦ K♦ T♥ T♣ T♦ 8♦
: 7♥ J♠ K♥ T♠ K♣ 7♣
: A♥ 5♠ 6♠ A♦ 8♥ J♦
: 7♠ 6♣ 7♦ 4♦ 8♠ 9♦

Moreover, Shirl Hart informed me that he/she have uploaded a Java port of their Freecell Solver to GitHub, which runs much faster (70x reportedly) than the Perl version (but might still consume more RAM than an equivalent C port). All the power to Shirl!

DocBook EPUB generation

I ran into some problems with getting the EPUB (an Electronic book format) generation of the DocBook/5 XSLT stylesheet to work properly, but it was fixed in this commit thanks in part to help I got on the docbook-apps mailing list.

Wiki-ing

I have been desperately trying to find a usable photo (under a Creative Commons licence/etc.) of Christina Grimmie (= the singer and musician known for her YouTube videos) for her Wikipedia pages, without luck so far.

I also have been trying to protect the English Wikipedia page of Tiffany Alvord (another superb artist) from deletionism, and it’s ironic that the Spanish Wikipedia page about her is longer and more comprehensive, even though Alvord is American and almost always sings in English.

Furthermore, I have been using several pages in the Buffy Fan Fiction Wikia to organise my thoughts for the Selina Mandrake screenplay.

Thanks

Thanks to protist (Jonathan Avery) for reviewing this post and commenting on it.

Date: 13-04-2013
jobs, work, employment, hacktivity log

Copied from Slashdot.org: “Heroic people make any job they take awesome.”

First of all, I have written my recent hacktivity log over on my new dreamwidth.org blog, and I am not posting it here, because it involves a lot of non-code hacktivity, which I expect to do quite a lot more of from now.

That put aside, I am copying here something that I wrote in a Slashdot comment about why I am looking for a job not in IT. Especially of note there are my frustrations with employers being too domineering and control-freaks, and not letting the good developers do things the way they most prefer to do it. Here goes:

I'll put it on the table: I have a Bachelor of Science (B.Sc. - 4 year degree) in Electrical Engineering (more like a mixed CE/EE/CS degree) from The Technion in their Haifa, Israel Campus [wikipedia.org], and graduated cum laude, and I have a qualified engineer certificate which theoretically allows me to write software for guiding missiles (or other flaw-free software) and give my signature that it is flaw-free. Nevertheless, right now I'm looking for part-time jobs as a seller/vendor in icecream parlours, candy/snack stores, cafés/restaurants/bars/etc. or even as a street sweeper. Lots of places in Tel Aviv, Israel are now advertising for this, and this seems like a good way to earn some money, as well as interact with other people and get inspired which will really help me with my creative writing [shlomifish.org] and my essays [www.shlomifishorg]. And I can buy an Android smartphone (nothing really better now and some people have successfully installed GNU/Linux chroots there) so I can type stuff for later incoporation into my desktop and laptop devices.

So why not work as a software developer? I don't mind getting a job as a software developer or a hardware developer or whatever, but lately employers in Tel Aviv and vicinity have become extremely picky: you go to an interview, answer most technical questions nicely, and don't get hired. Furthermore, even if they like you they are often very domineering: don't work from home, work 10-12 hours a day, only full time, don't play computer games at all (I only played some card Patience/Solitaire and Sokoban and not for long and still got flack), don't go to Facebook/Twitter/Google-Plus, we don't want you accessing imgur.com (too muchu traffic to there so let's firewall it) etc. etc. Thing is - the junior developers are kings [avc.com] (see the link for the Joel article), and you should leave them alone to their elements to get shit done at their own pace, and using their own resources instead of being a control freak. If, as a boss, my developer watched porn for 6 hours a day, while still being available on the forums for questions, and spent 2 hours creating great code that is functional and beautiful, I would be happy, and give him a full salary. But finding such enlightened employers is a big problem.

Software was the first field where workers were in constant demand, but now it seems that other fields are headed the same way here in Tel Aviv and other major centres of commerce worldwide: the food outlets, the music industry, photography, and soon - writing, acting/drama/film and then hopefully also modelling, and then if we can get past the normal and silly legal barriers - also more brick-and-mortar industries. Right now I've decided to make a transition [perl.org] from a software developer to a writer/Internet-entertainer/amateur-philosopher - a field where I feel I produce better results and also something that people will find cooler and sexier (although like I note in the article, the fact that I wrote a Freecell solver has impressed some really cute and intelligent chicks), and will have a larger influence. I still see knowing programming and other software development as an absolutely necessary means for that, just like I can no longer survive without knowing how to read and write English. Everyone should know at least HTML/XHTML/etc.

What I'm trying to say is that one should avoid Fatalism. People can improve for the better. I spent six and a half year doing my Elec. Eng. degree in the Technion and it cost me a lot of frustrations, but I'm still alive and have constantly become a better person - more competent, more able, smarter, wiser, and with a greater capacity for love and friendship. As long as you're not dead and still have some health in you, you will do fine. My suggestion to someone who got a Ph.D. in literature is to realise that that may make them a really awesome programmer , or a bartender, or a candy store vendor, or a secretary, or a sys admin, or anything else that they will find a job at. Don't think "I'm too good for that" because like they say in Hollywood "There are no small roles - only small (= small-minded) actors." You can be an awesome superheroic person even if you're just a factory worker.

Date: 07-01-2013
cpan, perl, hacking, hacktivity, rsync, uploading

The “sky” command-line application and other Recent hacktivity

If you have a good web hosting, you may have run into a pattern, where you are uploading files to it for other people to download and need to find the URL where they were uploaded to. Thing is - recalling the exact Rsync (= a file uploader) command and then going to the web browser to access the URL is time-consuming, and repetitive. sky, written in Perl using Moo and available on CPAN, aims to fix all that.

Here is a sample invocation from the web-site:

shlomif@telaviv1:~$ sky up /home/music/Music/mp3s/Thierry\ de\ Massia/Elements\ essentiels/01\ -\ Le\ vent.ogg
X11 forwarding request failed on channel 0
sending incremental file list
01 - Le vent.ogg
     5271287 100%  147.24kB/s    0:00:34 (xfer#1, to-check=0/1)

sent 5272011 bytes  received 31 bytes  87141.19 bytes/sec
total size is 5271287  speedup is 1.00
Got URL:
http://www.shlomifish.org/Files/files/music/mp3-ogg/01%20-%20Le%20vent.ogg
shlomif@telaviv1:~$

As you can see, we just specified the file, and it divined the rsync command and gave us the resultant URL. Convenient.

sky requires a configuration file in ~/.config/Perl/App-Sky/app_sky_conf.yml such as this one:

---
default_site: homepage
sites:
    homepage:
        base_upload_cmd:
            - 'rsync'
            - '-a'
            - '-v'
            - '--progress'
            - '--inplace'
        dest_upload_prefix: 'hostgator:public_html/'
        dest_upload_url_prefix: 'http://www.shlomifish.org/'
        sections:
            code:
                basename_re: '\.(?:pl|pm|c|py)\z'
                target_dir: 'Files/files/code/'
            music:
                basename_re: '\.(?:mp3|ogg|wav|aac|m4a)\z'
                target_dir: 'Files/files/music/mp3-ogg/'
            video:
                basename_re: '\.(?:webm|flv|avi|mpeg|mpg|mp4|ogv)\z'
                target_dir: 'Files/files/video/'

And it uses the basename_re to figure out where to upload it later. The next features I would like to see added are an ability to specify the target directory or alternatively override the target section, and naturally - better documentation. But I'm happy with what I have so far.

CPAN Cleanups

I have been going over many of my CPAN distributions and doing various cleanups such as removing trailing whitespace (with tests based on Test-TrailingSpace), or converting the Changes file to be compliant with CPAN-Changes. It was kinda fun, though time consuming.

New Version of Freecell Solver

There’s a new stable version of Freecell Solver, 3.18.0 released with some improvements including a port to JavaScript.

Black Hole Solitaire Solver

I have done a lot of work on Black Hole Solitaire Solver, and it can now also solve All-in-a-Row-Solitaire, and has some other improvements.

Binary Puzzle Solver

The Binary Puzzle Solver (written in Ruby) is now at version 0.0.3, with some bug fixes, several new moves and a convenient command line application.

Date: 25-06-2013
perl, Module-Build-Tiny, valgrind, windows, open, source

Some Perl-Related Bugs and How They Were Fixed.

In this entry, I’d like to tell about several Perl-related bugs I have run into, and how they were fixed. I know I have not been blogging a lot lately, but, on the bright side, I was busy coding.

XML-Grammar-Fortune-Synd Test Failures on Some Windows-based Testers

For a long time, I've been getting test failures such as this one for my XML-Grammar-Fortune-Synd module, from some Windows-based systems, which I was unable to reproduce on my local Linux system. Per Michael G. Schwern’s advice, I tried to convert all the path handling to use File::Spec for paths portability, but it did not fix the problem. Then I tried it on a Windows XP VM, but the tests passed there fine. Eventually, I had to install a Windows 7 VM, and run the tests there, and they failed. I originally suspected the problem was with File::Temp’s tempdir() function, but it turned out to be an inconsistency in the behaviour of File::Copy across the systems. On some systems, it copied a read only file to the temporary directory, preserving its read-only status, which made open() throw an error when writing to it.

This was fixed by these two subroutines:

sub _my_copy
{
    my ($src, $dest) = @_;

    open my $out_fh, '>', $dest;
    print {$out_fh} _slurp($src);
    close($out_fh);

    return;
}

sub _slurp
{
    my $filename = shift;

    open my $in, "<", $filename
        or die "Cannot open '$filename' for slurping - $!";

    local $/;
    my $contents = <$in>;

    close($in);

    return $contents;
}

Where I used _my_copy() to copy from one file location to another.

Since this was fixed, I didn't get any test failures for the module from Microsoft Windows machines or otherwise. Silence is golden.

Module-Build-Tiny Test Failures on Mageia Linux

I noticed that some of the tests of Module-Build-Tiny (which some CPAN distributions started using) failed to run on Mageia Linux, while they ran fine in a perl installed from perlbrew. The problem was that the file was partly writable while Module-Build-Tiny wanted it to be completely read-only. At first, we suspected a combination of the perl build-time flags caused it, but a perl I built from source with all the Mageia flags, passed all the tests. So it was likely caused by a Mageia patch.

By using the perl debugger, I realised that a downstream patch changed the permissions in the Perl ExtUtils::Install to 0644 instead of 0444, and after testing the package without this patch, the Module-Build-Tiny tests passed.

We ended up removing the patch permanently from the Mageia perl package.

Second Problem with Module-Build-Tiny: Double-Dash

Another problem I had with Module-Build-Tiny, after the previous one was that it appeared to have ignored the “destdir” and “installdirs” command line arguments , but it turned out that we needed to spell them --destdir=$FOO instead of destdir=$FOO, and as --installdirs=vendor instead of installdirs=vendor (with double-dash prefixes). This was noted in the Mageia Perl Policy, and I also sent a pull request for fixing it to CPANPLUS-Dist-Mageia.

Parallelising Time-Consuming Automated Tests Using prove -j

As I did some work on Freecell Solver, I was annoyed by the fact that the valgrind.t test script, which ran several tests for checking the programs for valgrind sanity, was too time consuming, despite the fact that I ran it first and ran the other test scripts in parallel to it using prove’s “-j” flag.

Then it occurred to me that I can parallelise these tests inidividually. I decided to split them into an array of tests, each one with an ID, and then have a program write several tests scripts, with each one running an individual ID, and then run all the files generated by the generation program.

This seems to have improved performance, and I can now run the parallelised tests in 21 seconds.

I've been thinking that this could be a useful CPAN distribution, and am contemplating writing something like that for CPAN.

Thanks

Thanks to Altreus for reviewing this entry.

Date: 25-10-2013
cpan, perl, hacking, hacktivity, download manager, 100

I now have over a 100 Distributions on CPAN!

Some days ago I discovered that my CPAN distributions count had already gone above 100, only that my MetaCPAN page has misled me due to a bug ( which I reported since). I now have 103 distributions on CPAN and you can find a list of them on the Israeli Perl Mongers site, with whatever is missing from the MetaCPAN page.

So now I'm in the CPAN 100 club, and now will also better focus on improving the quality of my existing distributions. According to GumbyPAN, the top ten authors are SHARYANTO [265] RJBS [258] TOBYINK [239] ADAMK [236] ZOFFIX [222] MIYAGAWA [216] BINGOS [197] INGY [177] TOKUHIROM [170] SMUELLER [156], so no one has gone up to 300 distributions yet (also see the top 20 current in the leadercpan page.).

Maniac Downloader

One of the distributions on my road to the 100 distributions was Maniac Downloader, which is a download accelerator written in Perl using AnyEvent and other CPAN distributions. It was written as a way for me to scratch an itch where I noticed that I could get better download throughput from many sites by opening more than one connection. I tried several download managers, but most of them were GUI only and the only terminal one I found - prozilla, could not handle https:// URLs and, furthermore, didn’t implement the “secret sauce” of Maniac downloader of splitting slow segments into multiple parts to speed up the acceleration, and finally - was very noisy. Since prozilla is written in C, it was not easy to hack on it, so I decided to write something myself using Perl.

I wrote the first prototype of Maniac Downloader using POE, but didn’t get very far, and I also think performance left some things to be desired. Then, some weeks ago, I started working on the second version as a Dist-Zilla distribution and using AnyEvent, and made more progress. AnyEvent is easy to use, and works nicely and quickly, and I like it more than POE.

I released App-ManiacDownloader-v0.0.3 to the CPAN today, and it now resumes interrupted downloads, so it's getting more usable for me. There are still some tasks left to be done there, but you can try using it already.

Date: 13-01-2014
perl, perl 6, tech, tip, tech tip, loops, labels

Tech Tip: Loop Labels in Perl 6

The Tip

It is known that one can label loops (or arbitrary blocks) in Perl 5, using the syntax of MYLABEL: while (COND()) { BLOCK } or MYLABEL: for my $x (@array) { BLOCK } and then one can do last MYLABEL;, next MYLABEL;, or redo MYLABEL; (for more information see perldoc perlsyn). However, I was unable to find how to do something like that in Perl 6, despite some amount of searching. Luckily, the people on the Perl 6 helped me.

The answer is that in Perl 6, it’s essentially not different:

MYLABEL: for (1 .. 100) -> $x
{
.
.
    last MYLABEL;
.
.
}

WHILE_LABEL: while $x < 24
{
.
.
    next WHILE_LABEL;
.
.
}

In Perl 6, one can also write MYLABEL.last; instead, but last MYLABEL; will still work. Note however that “last/redo/next” + label are not currently implemented in Rakudo Perl 6 (though you can still safely add labels to the loops).

Cheers!

Meta

I haven’t blogged for a while in my blogs.perl.org blog, even though I’ve been meaning to. Anyway, I’m mostly fine, and have been working on some Project Euler challenges, some pull requests and patches to projects, and some activity on my own projects. Hopefully, I'll find the time to write something more substantial. Recently, I’ve contributed some extra examples to the Project Euler section of the perl6-examples repository. As a result, I was recently granted a perl6-GitHub-project-wide commit bit (by none other than TimToady), so now I can do all the MAYHEM and DESTRUCTION I want there (Muahahahahahahah!). Just kidding about that: all I’m planning to do for now is add more Perl 6 examples.

Date: 19-01-2014
perl, perl 5, tech, tip, tech tip, open, files, I/O

Tech Tip: Opening a file for read/write without clobbering it.

The Tip

perlopentut gives several options for opening a file for read and write, and I opted to use '+>' for Maniac Downloader, but as it turned out, it caused the existing file to be clobbered (= its length to be set to zero and all of its contents deleted).

After asking on Freenode’s #perl channel, we reached this solution for opening a filehandle so that: 1) it will be opened for read/write. 2) it can open both an existing file or create a new file that does not exist. 3) If the file exists, its contents will be retained, and it won't be clobbered. and 4) it will overwrite existing contents, and not append everything at the end of the file.

The code is as follows:

sub _open_fh_for_read_write_without_clobbering
{
    my ($path, $url_basename) = @_;

    # open with '+>:raw' will clobber the file.
    # On the other hand, open with '+<:raw' won't create a new file if it
    # does not exist.
    # So we have to restort to this.
    #
    # For more information, see: http://perldoc.perl.org/perlopentut.html
    {
        open my $fh_temp, '+>>:raw', $path
            or die "Cannot open '$path' for temp-creation. $!";
        close($fh_temp);
    }
    open my $fh, "+<:raw", $path
        or die "${url_basename}: $!";

    return $fh;
}

( You can freely reuse this code under your choice of the MIT/X11 License or the Public Domain/CC0. )

The $url_basename is a relic of the roots of Maniac Downloader. Using that file-handle I used sysseek and syswrite, and it worked nicely.

I should note that mauke suggested using this instead:

use File::Open qw(fsysopen);
my $fh = fsysopen($path, 'rw');
binmode $fh;

More about Maniac Downloader

I investigated why Maniac Downloader misdownloaded several “.iso” files after being interrupted and resumed, and it turned out to have been caused by the fact that it clobbered the temporary buffer files, due to the reason I mentioned above. This was fixed in version 0.0.5.

Next I tried to benchmark it against aria2 and GNU wget in trying to download a file from a local mirror. Using ten connections for both aria2 and Maniac Downloader, I saw that aria2 and wget took about 30 minutes to download the file, while Maniac Downloader downloaded it in less than 13 minutes. However, at one point the ManDown downloading completely stopped (displaying 0 KB/s), and I had to Ctrl+C it and run it again. I guess now I’ll need to investigate how to cancel the HTTP/HTTPS downloads and start them again if they stalled.

Date: 29-03-2014
perl, du, analyze, downloader, download, manager, disk usage, command line, khronos group, opengl

Recent Hacktivity Log

This is another “recent hacktivity log” of some of the open source work I’ve been up to lately.

New Command-Line App: App-Du-Analyze

App-Du-Analyze (with its command-line script of "analyze-du") is now available on CPAN. What it does is allow you to analyse the output of the UNIX “du” command, get results based on a prefix and a depth, and sort them. It is my preference for a disk usage analyser, with the benefit of being able to run several queries on the same data, by keeping the same du.txt file - a feature which I found is often lacking in GUI disk usage analysers.

Here's an example of using it:

$ export ANALYZE_DU_INPUT_FN="$(pwd)/t/data/fc-solve-git-du-output.txt"
$ analyze-du -p "fc-solve" -d 1
16      fc-solve/tests
120     fc-solve/docs
172     fc-solve/scripts
232     fc-solve/arch_doc
276     fc-solve/rejects
392     fc-solve/benchmarks
2920    fc-solve/site
4192    fc-solve/source
44208   fc-solve/presets

You can find a report about using an earlier incarnation of the same program to find the hotspots in a Windows XP disk.

New Versions of Maniac Downloader

I uploaded new versions of Maniac Downloader, which is a CPAN module that implements a download accelerator. What they do is convert the file open to sysopen (per Steven Haryanto’s tip (thanks Steven!), and attempt to refresh stale connections after a timeout, which is a problem that bit me several times.

Working on my CPANTS Kwalitee Score

I worked on my CPANTS (= a CPAN Testing Service) Kwalitee score. My CPANTS page currently says I have an Average Kwalitee of 134.88, a CPANTS Game Kwalitee of 99.79 and a Rank of 68 in the league of “5 or more”.

I was looking for something to do and decided to revamp my CPAN distributions’ Kwalitee as much as I could. This involved quite a lot of actions:

Converting distributions from “Makefile.PL” to “Build.PL” or to Dist-Zilla.

Adding various test scripts for POD coverage, POD validity, CPAN changes validity, and trailing whitespace (the latter are not required by CPANTS but they are something I like to have for good measure).

Resurrecting or tracing the version control history of various modules, either using App-cpangitify, using the old repositories over at bitbucket.org, or the even older ones on my Subversion repository on svn.berlios.de.

Adding "use strict;" and "use warnings;".

Having a $VERSION in all the modules (“.pm” files).

Anyway, it was a good excuse to do a lot of clean ups, and doing all this work made me appreciate the utility of Dist-Zilla even more, but it kinda sucks that sometimes existing dist.ini checkouts break after an upgrade (like this App-CPAN2pkg pull request indicates).

Anyway, CPANTS still complains about some stuff in my modules, but a lot of them are false positives.

Khronos Group Kickoff Meetup

I went to the kickoff meetup of the Tel Aviv chapter of the Khronos Group. In case you do not know, the Khronos group is an industry consortium for maintaining some standards for hardware-assisted computing like OpenGL and OpenCL (whose specifications are open, but do not always have open source implementations). I got some free food and drinks there, and it was easy to travel to, and I caught a ride back home. The talks - one about OpenVX and the other about OpenCL 2.0 were enjoyable, but I think I would have liked more code and focus on “hands-on” development.

The Khronos Group’s local chapters aim to reach out to the community of developers who use their APIs.

Anyway, I met there a few people from some companies like Intel and AMD. I talked with the AMD representative and he was a bit shocked that I was using the open source drivers for Linux on my ATI Mobility HD laptop, saying that the proprietary drivers were more performant and featureful, and that the open source drivers were primarily provided for servers. I remember trying the proprietary drivers, but recall having had some problems with them, and I also hesitate to use proprietary software, especially as kernel drivers.

On my way back, someone gave me a ride, and I talked with him about OpenCL and he gave me some ideas for a possible methods to still accelerate Freecell Solver using it. I'm not sure if they are practical, but they were still good food for thought.

Anyway, I’d like to attend more of their meetups.

perl-begin.org Update and Revamp

I dedicated some time to go over the contents of the Perl Beginners’ Site (perl-begin.org) and update it to reflect the new knowledge and best practices. Now the site is in much better shape than it was before. I still want to write an item for it in its news page.

Desal Text Representation

Dextr

1. Overview

1.1. Introduction
1.2. Design goals
1.3. Syntactic blocks

2. Tokenization

2.1. Token types
2.2. Tokenization modes

3. unsorted stuff

3.1. get interface
3.2. postfix incrementation operator
3.3. function-interface
3.4. cast

4. not marked-up

Chapter 1. Overview

1.1. Introduction

This document defines a means of representing Desal semantics, and a means for extracting the semantics by a computer agent.

1.2. Design goals

easy for current programmers to pick-up. This means a representation that uses text files which are meant to be worked with directly by programmers.
relatively easy to parse by humans and computers
able to encode most semantics offered by Desal Semantics, with a very direct 1-to-1 mapping
minimalism where not detrimental. This means if leaving a few characters out doesn't really hurt, leave them out

1.3. Syntactic blocks

if a > b
	doSomething1()
	doSomething2()
else
	doSomethingElse1()
	doSomethingElse2()

if a > b : doSomething1(), doSomething2()
else : doSomethingElse1(), doSomethingElse2()

if a > b { doSomething()
  doSomethingElse2() }
else
{
	doSomethingElse1()
doSomethingElse2()
}

In the first way, whitespace is significant. In the second and third way, newlines end the block, but otherwise whitespace is not significant.

Chapter 2. Tokenization

How to break up Dextr source code into tokens.

2.1. Token types

xxx
xxx

2.2. Tokenization modes

xxx

Chapter 3. unsorted stuff

Word ::=
	WordChar +
	
Identifier ::=
	Word
	
Keyword ::=
	"$" Word

$if else > return {
	$throw throw
}

Rationale: Users should be quickly and easily able to tell whether a word is an identifier or a keyword, without having to memorize the list of keywords. Because identifiers are usually more common than keywords, keywords are given the burden of having an extra character instead of identifiers.

Move to IDE guidelines:
Syntax highlighters are encouraged to hide the $ character in keywords (in display only, not to remove it from source) and differentiate between keywords and identifiers though some other means (e.g. color). Such syntax highlighters must provide a means of switching a word between keyword and identifier.

One possibility would be to display the $ in a particular keyword whenever the cursor has been next to or within the keyword for more than half a second. Such syntax highlighters should automatically and immediately recognize when a word has lost or gained a $ and update the way it is displayed immediately e.g. if the $ is removed from a keyword, the syntax highlighter should recognize the change immediately and not continue displaying the word like it is a keyword.

Another possibility would be to never show the $ after a keyword has been typed, and ignore $ added in front of identifiers, but have a button, menu item, and/or keyboard shortcut that when activated, flips the meaning of the keyword that the cursor is currently in or next to.

3.1. get interface

It's always possible to bind the interface of an object to an identifier.

func getInterface{I}(I o) { return I; } dynref o = getMysteryObj() interface i = getInterface(o) i o2 = o

3.2. postfix incrementation operator

"object++" doesn't create a temporary. The object has its increment method called after the object is accessed. The below two groups of code represent the same semantics.

int a = 3 int b = a++ int a = 3 int b = a ++a

3.3. function-interface

required_s ::= ( " " | comment ) +
s ::= required_s ?
required_ls ::= ( required_s | "\n" | "\t" ) +
ls ::= required_ls ?

function-interface ::=
	funcfaceshort | funcfacelong

funcfacebase ::=
	"func" s "(" s funcfaceparameters ? s ")"

funcfaceshort ::=
	funcfacebase s identifier

funcfacelong ::=
	funcfacebase s "(" ls expression ls ")"

funcfaceparameters ::= ...

3.4. cast

cast ::=
	expression s "as" s expression

example:
(foo as Bar)

Chapter 4. not marked-up

foo

*** operator precendence examples ***

interface alpha
	func beta(int)
alpha foo

foo.beta(3)
//is the same as
foo => alpha::beta (3)

(alpha o).beta(3)
//is the same as
cast{alpha}(o).beta(3)
//is the same as
o => cast{alpha} .beta(3)


*** statement block ***

indented statements
	statement 1
	statement 2
	statement 3

colon then statements: statement 1, statement 2, statement 3

enclosed in braces { statement 0
	statement 1
statement 2
		statement 3, statement 4  }


*** 2007-06-10: adjuncts removed ***

func int.times(func() f)
	for(int i = 0; i < this; i++)
		f()
 
3.times func()
	println "test"

func times(int num, func() f)
	for( int i = 0; i < num; i++ )
		f()

3 => times func()
	println "test"
	
3..times || println "test"

do 3 times: println "test"

//same as

times( 3, func()
	println "test"
)

//same as

times(3, ||println "test")


*** functions ***

a "function" is an object that implements the "callee" interface
(xxx would "callable" be a better name?)

function literals create objects with an interface that inherits from callee
function declaration - defines a function and binds it to an identifier
syntax
	"func"
	identifier
	"("
	* [ interface identifier ] (seperated by ,)
	")"
	? interface
	statement-block
func foo(float a) int
	return a * 2

syntax for interface of specific types of functions
func(float)int f = foo

function expressions aka inline functions

func{I}(I)int h = |x| x * 3
func(int)int h = |x| x * 3 //can auto convert
func(int)int j = { |int x|
	string str = cast string x
	int hash = hash(string)
	return str.toLowerCase()
}


*** additional semantics ***

Desal Text Representation (Dextr, or Desal Dextr) has additional semantics on top of Desal semantics. These semantics are used to obtain Desal semantics from Dextr source code. Most of these semantics involve tokens/objects "grabbing" other tokens/objects.


*** example of additional semantics in Dextr ***

func doStuff() int
	return 3

func foo1()
	function square(ratnum num) ratnum
		return num * num

	doStuff()
	
func foo2()
	function(ratnum num) ratnum
		return num * num
	
	doStuff()

In foo1, the function is bound to the identifier "square" and not called.
In foo2, the function is not bound to an indentifer. The value returned from doStuff() is fed into it as an argument.

So Dextr differentiates between "function expressions" and "function declarations", although in Desal Semantics there is not such differentiation.


*** operators ***

Operators are able to "grab" what comes before and/or after it. Which operator grabs what is determined by operator precedence. Operators can be thought of as macros.

[] grabs what is before it and passes it to the array function
	string[] is equal to array(string)

[int] grabs what is before it and passes it and the int to the array function
	float[5] is equal to array(float, 5)

+ grabs what is before and after it, and sends what's after it to the add method of what's before it
	3 + 5 is equal to 3.add(5)
	
= grabs what is before and after it, and sends what's after it the assign method of what's before it
	a = 8 is equal to a.assign(8)

+ has greater precedence than =
	a = 3 + 5 is equal to a.assign( 3.add(5) )

The actual functions follow the regular left-to-right behavior.
	a .assign 3 .add 5 //is equal to
	a.assign(3).add(5)

"not" grabs the boolean that's after it and inverses it
	not true //is the same as
	true.inverse()

"or" grabs the booleans before and after it
	foo or bar //is the same as
	foo.or(bar)
	
if f is a function:
f 1 + 2 + f 3
is equal to
f(1).add(2).add( f(3) )

function calls have precedence over +


*** parameters/arguments ***

Parameters are a part of a function, and have names. Arguments are the values passed to functions.

//alpha and beta are the parameters
function foo(int alpha, float beta) string 
	...

//3 and 7.8 are the arguments
foo(3, 7.8)


*** function signatures ***

a function signature consists of the parameters and the return type


*** function calling ***

If something follows a function, it will be passed to the function an argument.
Like operators, functions are able to "grab" what follows them.
If a function grabs a collection (described below), the items in the collection will be passed as arguments.

func foo(int arg = 3)
	...

foo //function not called
foo() //function called
foo ()
foo 3 //function called
foo(3) //function called
foo (3)
foo.params //function not called
foo .params


*** collections ***

Things grouped in parenthesis forms a collection. How this collection is touched determines how it is treated.

If a collection is grabbed by a function, the elements are passed as arguments to the function.

else
	if the collection has one element
		the element is evaluated
		the (...) evaluates to that
	else
		error

--- functions ---

a = (3)
The = is an operator. The line is equivalent to: a.assign (3)
Assign is a function, so it grabs what follows, "(3)"
3 is passed as an argument to the assignment function.

string[] names
names = ("Bob", "Sam", "Sally")
names.assign ("Bob, "Sam", "Sally")
assign here is a var-arg function
The strings are passed as arguments to names.assign

dynref foo = int[] (3, 5, 7)
dynref foo = array(int)(3, 5, 7)

dynref foo = int[] 9
dynref foo = arry(int)(9)

--- else ---

a = (3) + (5) + (8)
Operator precendence causes the + to grab arguments before = can get anything.
a.assign( (3) .add (5) .add (8) )
Because there's not a function before (3) trying to grab it, and (3) only has one element, (3) evaluates to 3.
a.assign( 3 .add (5) .add (8) )
int a = ((3.add(5)) + (8))
Because there's nothing before (3.add(5)) trying to grab something, it evaluates to 3.add(5)
int a = (3.add(5).add(8))
int a \n a.assign(3.add(5).add(8))

--- labels and enum shortcuts ---

enum bar
	VALUE_1,
	VALUE_2,
	VALUE_3

func foo( int a = 1, int b = 2, int c = 3, bar eBar)
	...

foo( c: 8 )

foo( 7, 8, 9, = VALUE_1 )

foo( eBar: = VALUE_1 )

foo( a: 1, b: 2, c: 3, eBar: bar.VALUE_1 )

foo( a: 1, b: 2, c: 3, eBar: = VALUE_1 )

foo( 1, 2, 3, bar.VALUE_1 )


**** ----- ****

All identifiers are in the same namespace. There are no reserved words. If a user defined idetifier conflicts with a system identifier, the system identifier must be prefixed with "$". The "$" is optional for other user defined identifiers.


UTF-8 is default encoding, if none is specified.
A BOM on a UTF-8 document shouldn't causes problems.
".desalt" file extension


Input consists of a series of Unicode characters.
Tokenization processes input character by character to produce a series of tokens.
Parsing processes the tokens to extract semantics.


*** character types ***

illegal
	control characters
	Unicode reserved code points
	Unicode tags
	surrogates
	illegal characters cannot appear anywhere in source code
		not even in comments
reserved
	space
	tab
	newline
	quote " ' `
	opening bracket
		parenthesis (
		box bracket [
		brace {
	closing bracket
		parenthesis )
		box bracket ]
		brace }
	special + - / * @ $ = \ , .
numeral
	0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9
free
	all Unicode characters not otherwise categorized
	includes: ! ? _

XXX uncategorized
	% ~ # ^ | ; & :


*** token types ***

indentation, line separation, string, opening bracket, closing bracket, special, number, word

examples:

number
	5
	700.0
	3.03f
	6i
	0xFF
	
word - a free character optionally followed by free characters and numerals
	x
	if
	else
	myItem2
	myItem3
	MyClass
	IDoStuff
	foo2bar3baz

string
	""
	"foo"
	"foo bar"
	'''test 333 
	    test'''
	"foo \" bar"
	
	
*** tokenization ***

Tokenization begins in ready mode with the first character.


--- modes that do not produce tokens ---
	
ready
	Based on the type of the current character, ready mode switches to the appropriate mode.
	
	character type		mode to go to
	------------------------------------
	illegal				illegal
	space				space
	tab					indentation
	newline				line seperation
	quote				string
	opening bracket		opening bracket
	closing bracket		closing bracket
	special				special
	numeral				number
	free				word
	
illegal
	end tokenization unseccessfully
	
line comment
	if there's a newline character following
		move to the next newline character and switch to line seperation mode
	else
		end tokenization successfully
	
multiline comment
	if there's an instance of */ following
		if there's a character after it
			move to that character
			switch to ready mode
		else
			end tokenization successfully
	else
		end tokenization unsuccessfully
	
space
	go to the next character
	switch to ready mode

	
--- modes that do produce tokens ---

indentation
	create an indentation token
	add the current character to it
	loop
		go to the next character
		if it's a tab
			add it to the token
		else
			close the token
			switch to ready mode
	
line separation
	create a line separation token
	go to the next character that isn't a newline
	switch to ready mode
	
string
	String processing rules determine when this mode is done.
	When it's done
		if an illegal token was encountered
			switch to illegal mode
		if some other error occured
			end tokenization unsuccessfully
		else
			string processing rules produced a string token
			switch to ready mode

opening bracket
	create an opening bracket token for the current character
	go to the next character
	switch to ready mode
	
closing bracket
	create a closing bracket token for the current character
	go to the next character
	switch to ready mode
	
special
	create a special token
	add the current character to it
	loop
		go to the next character
		if it's a special character
			add it to the token
			if token == '//'
				discard token
				go to line comment mode
			if token == '/*'
				discard token
				go to multiline comment mode
		else
			close the token
			switch to ready mode

number
	create a number token
	add the current character to it
	loop
		go to the next character
		if it's a numeral
			add it to the token
		if it's an "x"
			if the token currently consists of "0"
				add it to the token
			else
				end tokenization unsuccessfully
		if it's a "."
			if the token does not contain an "x"
				add it to the token
			else
				end tokenization unsuccessfully
		else
			close the token
			switch to ready mode
	
word
	create a word token
	add the current character to it
	loop
		go to the next character
		if it's a free character or a numeral
			add it to the free token
		else
			close the token
			switch to ready mode


*** tokens ***

In normal text, a token is a series of characters of the same type.
Strings and comments are considered to be string and comment tokens.
Each of the reserved types are considered seperately here. 

example 1:
  func doStuff(ref int arg) int
    return arg * 2
  }

  tokens:
    func
    SPACE
    doStuff
    (
    ref
    SPACE
    int
    SPACE
    arg
    )
    SPACE
    int
    LINEBREAK
    SPACE
    return
    SPACE
    arg
    SPACE
    *
    SPACE
    2
    LINEBREAK
    }
  
  
example 2:
  423oeuth03928nothunho394898+&*(^%$#&+++oetuhntoh
  
  tokens:
    423
    oeuh0328notho3998
      transition from numerals to free characters begins a new token
      transition from free characters to numerals continues the same token
    +&*(^%$#&+++
      transition from free characters to symbols
    oetuhntoh
      transition from symbols to free characters

	  

	  

*** identifiers ***

An identifier is a token with an assigned meaning. 
Identifiers must consist of either:
  all symbols
  all free characters
  free characters and numerals
Identifiers can never:
  begin with numerals
  begin with reserved characters
  begin with /*
  end with */ 


*** default identifiers ***

Identifiers that are already defined by default.
Some of these can be redefined or overloaded while others can't.
  
includes:
  if
  else
  {
  }
  [
  ]
  break
  class
  func
  #
  +
  -
  *
  /

  
*** reserved identifiers ***

An identifier that cannot be (re)defined.

includes:
  if
  else
  {
  }
  [
  ]
  break
  class
  func
  #
  

*** string tokens ***

When the first character of a quote token is found, string processing rules take over.
They determine:
	what characters are part of the string token
	where normal processing should continue from

examples:

a + "test" + b

a - free - a free token begins
  - space - the free token ends (the space itself is ignored since it served only to separate)
+ - symbol - a symbol token begins
  - space - the symbol token ends
" - quote - string processing rules take over and produce a string token
  - space - the string processing rules said to start here, and it was just a space, which should be discarded
+ - symbol - a symbol token begins
  - space - the symbol token ends
b - free - a free token begins
end of file - the free token ends

output tokens:
free	a
symbol	+
string	test
symbol	+
free	b


"this is a string"
'this is a string'
"""this is a string"""
'''this is a string'''
sized-string 16 this is a string


*** Enclosers ***

Some characters surround other characters to note that the inner characters are grouped together in some way.

(...)
[...]
<...>

Enclosers allow things to span multiple lines.


*** Blocks ***

A block is code that is grouped together.

Some identifiers can open blocks.
These are known as "block-opening identifiers".
These include: "if", "else", "while", colon, opening curly brace

Some identifiers can close blocks.
These are known as "block-closing identifiers".
These include: closing curly brace

Some identifiers can close a block and open a new one.
These are known as "block-reseting identifiers".
These include: "else", "while"

The full-stop opens a block and immediately closes it.
  (Meaning it signifies an empty block.)


int a
if test
  doStuff()
a = 3

"if" absorbs the following test and then opens a new block.
"  doStuff" set the indentation for this block to 2 spaces.
"a = 3" was not indented, so it closed the block.

To ensure the block doesn't include more than it should, include a closing brace.

int a
if test
  doStuff()
}
a = 3

To avoid the indentation requirements, start the block with an opening curly brace {.
Note that blocks beginning this way must also end with a closing curly brace }.

int a
if test {
doStuff()
}
a = 3
-or-
int a
if test
{
  doStuff()
}
a = 3

To place the block's code on the same line, begin the block with a colon.

int a
if test: doStuff()
a = 3
-or-
int a
if test : doStuff()
a = 3

The below code doesn't work.

int a
if test
  :doStuff()
a = 3
-or-
int a
if test:
  doStuff()
a = 3




*** Phrases ***

Phrases are similar to what is often called "statements".
Phrases consists of identifiers and/or reserved symbols and/or blocks that are grouped together.
Phrases can be ended by linebreaks or commas.

Example:
  In C++, semicolons end statements.
    doStuff1(); doStuff2(); doStuff3();

  In Desal, linebreaks or commas end statements.
    doStuff1()
    doStuff2()
    doStuff3()

    doStuff1(), doStuff2(), doStuff3()

    
*** Desal Syntax Description Language (DSDL) ***

Used to describe the syntax of features of Desal.

"text"
  specific text that must appear
newscopeid
  an identifier that is not defined anywhere else in that scope
join
  the thing before and after this cannot have any whitespace between them
paren()
  the arguments have parenthesis surrounding them
opt()
  the arugments are optional
optmult()
  the arguments may appear 0 or more times
type
  a type that is already defined in that scope
userid
  an identifier that is defined by the user
codeblock
  a block of code
block()
  a block with contents described in the arguments
obj
  identifier for an object that is in scope
  may be: doStuff(args) if doStuff returns something
objid
  identifier for an objcet that is already defined and in scope (no object literals)
either()
  any 1 of the multiple arguments may appear
    
    
    
    


*** XXX Unsorted Stuff ***

if the keyword phrase is ended by a linebreak, the block ends with a curly brace that resides on its own line or another keyword
  //keyword phrase: "if waitingCount > 0"
  //keyword: "if"
  //body: "waitingCount > 0"
  //ends with a linebreak
  if waitingCount > 0 
    doStuff()
  }
  
  "if" test block
  
  //the keywords that can end a block depend on what keyword opened the block
  
  switch obj
    case 1 //keyword phrase opened block that can be closed by "case", "fallcase", or "default"
      doStuff1()
    case 2 //"case" keyword ended previous block
      doStuff2()
    default //"default" keyword ended previous block
      doStuff0()
    }
  }
  
  if obj eql current //keyword phrase opened block that can be closed by "elif" or "else"
    doCurrent()
  elif obj eql past //"elif" keyword ended previous block
    doPast()
  else //"else" keyword ended previous block
    doFuture()
  }
  
if the keyword phrase is ended by a colon, the block ends with a line break or a comma
  if test: doStuff()
  
  if test: doStuff(), else: doOtherStuff() //"if" block ended with comma, "else" block ends with linebreak

if the keyword phrase is ended by a full-stop, the block must be empty
  while notReady? //test value of notReady until it evaluates to true

  if doNothing?
  else: doStuff()
  
if the keyword phrase is ended by an opening curly brace, the block ends with a closing curly brace
  if that eql "cool" { buy(that) }
  
  if that eql "cool" {
    buy(that)
  } //note that "else" can't close this block due to the opening curly brace
  else {
    burn(that)
  }
  
when a block is empty, a warning is raised
  if test: //empty block ended with linebreak
  if test //empty block ended with "else"
  else
  } //empty block ended with }
  

*** colon ***

if a colon is followed by whitespace, it begins a block
  example:
    if num1 < num2: doStuff()
else, it seperates a namespace identifier from an identifier in that namespace
  example:
    std:doStuff()  

This means the colon character has special meaning beyond that of other reserved characters.


*** namespaced operators ***

The "boost" library defines a binary "|<" operator.
It returns the amount of elements in the array on the left that are less than the number on the right.

array int numbers
int amount

amount = numbers boost:|< 3
amount = numbers boost:op(|<) 3
amount = numbers boost:(|<) 3
amount = numbers boost(|<) 3
with namespace boost: amount = numbers |< 3
with boost:operators: amount = numbers |< 3
with boost:(|<): amount = numbers |< 3


*** tabs and spaces ***

The semantics of spaces is to separate characters.
The semantics of newlines is to separate actions.
The semantics of tabs is to group related actions.

Desal partially attempts to require proper use of these characters.


*** tabs ***

Tabs are only allowed at the beginnig of lines.
After any non-tab character, further tabs are not allowed.
The first code on a line must be preceded only by 0 or more tabs.


*** comments ***

Comments are treated as spaces.

These lines are equivalent:
(end-of-line represented by |)

a /* big */ = b /* small */|
a           = b            |


*** blocks ***

1. Blocks are opened by some keywords.
2. The block ends when a line with code is encountered that has the same indention as the line that opened the block.

1:
if alpha < num //opens a block
	doStuff()

2:
if alpha < num
	doStuff()
else //this line has the same level of indention as the line that opened the above autoblock, so that block is closed
	...

Lines that are direct children must begin with 1 more tab than the line that opened the block.
Within a block, on a line with code:
	a tab or group of tabs must appear first
	code must appear second
	then spaces, comments, and more code may appear
	

example:
(tabs represented by 4 underscores)

if test
____doStuff1()
____
____doStuff2()

____doStuff3()

is equivalent to:

if test {
doStuff1()
doStuff2()
doStuff3()
}


example 2:

/* comment */ doStuff()
doStuff()____/* comment */

This is illegal because a tab appeared after code.



syntax:

()* means 0 or more

tab* (space/comment)*
tab* ( code (space/comment)* )*

A few years ago I started exploring a parallel computing design style based on Actors. That post referenced SolidBlue, the simplest project I've developed with that style. It's a tiny application which recursively scans a folder and computes the MD5 fingerprint of the contents, for the sake of verifying integrity. I'm routinely using it for checking that my photo files are ok, as in the past I've sadly experienced silent failure of the HFS+ filesystem of my MacBook Pro and, unfortunately, after so many years Apple didn't release a new filesystem with embedded integrity checking, Ă  la ZFS or BTRFS. Of course I do have several backups, but verifying that everything is fine on the laptop still has a meaning.

This is a sort of perfect example for studying real-world parallelism, as the specifications are simple, but it not only manipulates data structures in memory: it also performs disk I/O - massively, as the total size of the photo folder exceeds 500GB - and it has some interactions with a GUI. SolidBlue is currently made with the NetBeans Platform as the overall graphic infrastructure, and JavaFX for the details.

After a few years I feel the need to rewrite it from scratch because a number of reasons:

In the end, it has to stay a very simple tool, with a very simple GUI - nothing more than a set of progress bars during the scan. The NetBeans Platform - while it can be shrunk to some bare-bones - is definitely too much and a simple thing with JavaFX would suffice. For my recent UI-based projects I've ever abandoned the NetBeans Platform and moved to a Spring + JavaFX solution, even using some complex technique such as AspectJ. In this very case, Spring and other tools are unnecessary.
Even the Actor-based design itself looks like it's too complex for this simple application. Given also the fact that I've started giving classes on Java 8, and I think I'll soon be mentoring some customer on that technology, I've decided to self-assign to myself the exercise of re-designing SolidBlue parallelism over the bare Java 8 library, that is the one of Streams. Also for keeping the thing as simple as it can, I'm initially restraining myself from using Lombok - which is very powerful and stable in my experience - just not to have too many things on the table at the same moment.

The exercise will be incremental and iterative and in this post I'm just illustrating the very first version, which supports a very simple user story: run from the command line, get the folder path to scan as an argument, and perform the scan in a sequential fashion.

This post assumes that the basic concepts and syntax of Java 8 lambdas and Streams are known.

Let's start with the main():

public static void main (final String ... args)
  throws IOException
  {
    final Path targetPath = Paths.get(args[0]);
    log.info("Scanning {}...", targetPath);
    final Map<String, String> storage = Files.walk(targetPath, FOLLOW_LINKS)
                                             .filter(Main::matchesExtension)
                                             .peek(p -> log.info("Discovered {}", p.getFileName()))
                                             .collect(toMap(p -> p.getFileName().toString(),
                                                            p -> computeFingerprint(p, "MD5"),
                                                            (v1, v2) -> v2));
    store(targetPath, storage);
  }

It uses the Files.walk() method, introduced with Java 8, which recursively scans a directory and supports lambdas: the result, in fact, is a Stream<Path>. First it filters files with the required extensions, then produces a log message, and in the end collects everything to a Map<String, String> whose key is the file name and the associated value the MD5 fingerprint. Note that the toMap() method is the overloaded version with a third parameter, which is a BinaryOperator<String>, whose implementing lambda just returns the second operand: (v1, v2) -> v2. This version must be used when the incoming Stream has duplicated values. Indeed, my photos are organised so that they have unique file names (in the form 20150111-0354.ARW), so it shouldn't happen. But there is an old directory from my very first years in photography which uses a different approach and it has a few duplicates. It should really be fixed, but this is not my priority at the moment: so I'm just working around the problem in a way that it doesn't break the program. If I didn't use the third parameter, the code would have raised a runtime exception at the first duplicate key.

The filter to extract files with the required extension is straightforward:

private static boolean matchesExtension (final Path file)
  {
    final String extension = file.getFileName().toString().replaceAll("^.*\\.", "").toLowerCase();
    return Files.isRegularFile(file) && FILE_EXTENSIONS.contains(extension);
  }

The code to compute the fingerprint uses memory-mapped I/O to speed up the operation, even though many things should be said about this part, especially in the perspective of parallelisation. But it's not in the scope of the current post, so the only important thing is that it works.

It's worth mentioning that Streams don't accept checked exceptions in their lambdas, not because of a language limitation, but because the library was purportedly designed in this way. It's a thing that I don't like, but in this case it's not a problem: any error during the scan should be recorded, so it makes sense that the result is always a String, which in case of failure describes the error.

private static String computeFingerprint (final Path file, final String algorithm)
  {
    try
      {
        log.info("computeFingerprint({}, {})", file, algorithm);
        final MessageDigest digestComputer = MessageDigest.getInstance(algorithm);

        try (final RandomAccessFile raf = new RandomAccessFile(file.toFile(), "r"))
          {
            final MappedByteBuffer byteBuffer = raf.getChannel().map(READ_ONLY, 0, Files.size(file));
            digestComputer.update(byteBuffer);
          }

        return toString(digestComputer.digest());
      }
    catch (NoSuchAlgorithmException | IOException e)
      {
        return e.getMessage();
      }
  }

private static String toString (final byte[] bytes)
  {
    final StringBuilder builder = new StringBuilder();

    for (final byte b : bytes)
      {
        final int value = b & 0xff;
        builder.append(Integer.toHexString(value >>> 4)).append(Integer.toHexString(value & 0x0f));
      }

    return builder.toString();
  }

At last there's the code that writes the data to a text file:

private static void store (final Path targetPath, final Map<String, String> storage)
  throws IOException
  {
    final Path folder = targetPath.resolve(".it.tidalwave.solidblue2");
    final Path file = folder.resolve("fingerprints-j8.txt");
    Files.createDirectories(folder);
    log.info("Storing results into {} ...", file);

    try (final PrintWriter w = new PrintWriter(Files.newBufferedWriter(file, Charset.forName("UTF-8"))))
      {
        storage.entrySet().stream()
                          .sorted(comparing(Entry::getKey))
                          .forEach(e -> w.printf("MD5(%s)=%s\n", e.getKey(), e.getValue()));
      }
  }

The written file is something like that:

MD5(20150828-0006.NEF)=20cbd8dafe1d02dfc305b18177bdc873
MD5(20150829-0004.ARW)=e2f90c58489bd12d89da121b24aab2e5
MD5(20150830-0016.ARW)=563cb64b228862b6335905d990e4878c
MD5(20150830-0021.ARW)=6919c81409ec43c7c7ce6b0b5d8eb2b7
MD5(20150830-0026.ARW)=b2e9175509ffe2d50154e6127cc4ad73
MD5(20150830-0028.ARW)=d77469d294130d8cf362312a699dc35d
MD5(20150830-0031.ARW)=02937ba68642a1fbc8063dcf0c05ad5c
MD5(20150830-0034.ARW)=bd415547599ed168028c2cdb1234b65d
MD5(20150830-0046.ARW)=f17e34f24f1b28f6c94b53b98b34ea41
MD5(20150830-0052.ARW)=7cba4d7421ccf42605a5f196022e00b6
MD5(20150830-0056.ARW)=f056088310ce59b247948b08141d00b7

So, everything is very simple, it fits in a single class and you can read the whole source here; and it is written in functional style, that is, no extra classes, only static methods. It's a good starter.

What is it missing? Well:

Parallelism. While some could be tempted to say that I could just add a parallel() call in the Stream pipeline, it wouldn't work at all - I mean, the computation would stay absolutely sequential. This is because the parallelism in a Stream is an optional operation, that is not always available. In particular, the data source must be designed so it supports parallelism. In this case the problem is the Files.walk() method that works only in a sequential fashion.
Notifications. In the perspective of having a GUI I need to have notifications of the progress in real time. While the notification itself would be just a matter of inserting some stages in the pipeline, the major issue is that in order do compute a percentage of the progress I need to know how many files have been scanned. But since the Stream is sequential, I'll know that value only when the processing has been completed.
The last problem is a subtle requirement of the original SolidBlue. Since the elapsed time of the run is long, sometimes I have to early kill it. In this case I'd like to just have the partial results. First problem: now the result file is only written at the end, so if I kill the process I wouldn't get anything. It would be simple to have store() been called by a shutdown hook, but there is a secondary problem. I keep the fingerprints for every run and I compare them with the diff command to see whether something went wrong, because a file changed its MD5. Of course, from session to session, I could have added some files and deleted others. If I interrupt a run before it's complete, there will be many missing entries (files that have not been discovered yet) that would be misinterpreted as deleted files. So, the original SolidBlue prepares an entry such as MD5(20150111-0354.AWR)=unavailable as soon as a file is discovered, and the results are periodically written to the disk since the beginning. This means that after the file discovery has been completed - in less than a minute - I already have a result file which at least contains all the file names. From now on, it will be periodically updated changing unavailable with the MD5 value.

The whole project, made with Maven, is available at BitBucket; the source illustrated in this post is part of 1.0-ALPHA-1.

A few time ago I ran into a blog post by Ugo Cei, via Bob Atkins, with some interesting musings about landscape photography:

I was in Munich yesterday, [...] in a place where they had a huge TV monitor on the wall that was playing a slideshow of landscape photos. I couldn’t keep my eyes away from it, as the photos were really beautiful. You know that type of photo: amazing locations, wonderful light, colorful sunsets, starry skies, waterfalls, ocean waves, tropical beaches, brilliant colors. Most of them revealed a mastery of technique, accurate choice of location, delightful composition, masterful post-processing. Each one of those photos could have won a contest, get printed on a calendar or poster, graced the pages of a magazine or got a million likes on social networks. [...] And yet, after having seen the slideshow roll around three or four times, I was disgusted and wanted to throw my jug of beer to the screen. I even contemplated giving up landscape photography and picking up some other genre. That much beauty had left me numb and a feeling not unlike how you feel after a binge of eating chocolate or sweets.

20130709-0020

$XMP.dc.title$

Nikon D7000 $shootingData$, hand-held.

20130622-0223

$XMP.dc.title$

Nikon D7000 $shootingData$, hand-held.

Some underlying problems and consequences have been correctly described by Ugo just a few lines below:

Part of the problem, I think, was that at a time and age when everyone can have a decent camera for not much money, when photographic education is cheap or free, when it is much easier to travel to awesome locations than it used to be, almost everything has already been photographed in the best light. [...] Another problem is that I am seeing a growing trend of conformism in landscape photography. I could not recognize any one of those photos and tell who was their author, but at the same time they could have been attributed to any one of the many photographers who are very popular on social media. There is this prevalent style in landscape photography that aims to capture the viewer with dramatic light, strong composition and bright, saturated colors. I can definitely see why people like it, but I don’t like it anymore.

Apparently, it makes a lot of sense.

20100910-0177

$XMP.dc.title$

Nikon D5000 $shootingData$, hand-held.

That post by Ugo triggered me a number of thoughts and at a certain point I realised I had to write things down. Which is my relationship with photography? What are my expectations? Why am I shooting photos? So I thought it was appropriate to have a Weltanschauung moment: stopping and thinking over what I'm doing, going deeper into my awareness. Sometimes you start doing this, or thinking that, because of a very contingent reason (in my case, I started photography as a healthy excuse to stay in the open) and then, after some time, things have changed and completely turned upside down your initial rationale (sure, I've been enjoying photography for many years now, up to the point that my health suffered because of neck and back pain). “I shoot because I enjoy it” is a good answer, but a very partial one.

After some days, looking back at Ugo's post, I was still convinced he had raised a reasonable issue from his premises, but ... I didn't agree anymore on the premises. Is mannerism really a problem? Why?

Ugo - whom by the way I've met, years ago, when I was doing an IT consultancy for his company - is one of the many talented engineers / computer scientists with a passion for photography who, at a certain point in their life, steered the route of professional photography. The idea of making money out of photos is not bad, especially when I consider the amount of money I've spent in my gear. Having a return, even partial, would be good. But the problem is that when one starts thinking in terms of market, he's unavoidably engaged in a competition. Unfortunately competition means being subjected to rules, which in turn mean conformism (if you want to sell) - or being enslaved to a strategy for being not conformist (if you want to be original). In both cases a limitation of freedom. So, while I'm happy that even in the Flickr age there are professional photographers, I'm also happy to say that I'm not a pro and I can enjoy a full freedom in my photographer activity.

This is my short reaction to Ugo's stimulus. But probably it's not enough, as I'm not taking photos here and there at random, without a rationale or a process reference. So, I spent some further time thinking over my relationship with photography and elaborated a longer, deeper answer.

20140603-0100

$XMP.dc.title$

Sony NEX-6 $shootingData$, hand-held.

First, seeing the world in the Catholic perspective, for me everything is naturally being understood by means of a transcendental approach. St. Paul wrote “So whether you eat or drink, or whatever you do, do everything for the glory of God.” [1 Co 10, 31] and this holds true for photography too. Thus landscape and architecture photography, which are my main interests, are a way to contemplate Beauty in nature- and man-made things of diverse kinds, a direct and indirect product of the Grace of the Holy Ghost. Capturing them into a good quality still image is important - I feel it as a supplementary way of praying and thanking the Lord for the gifts He gave us.

20140316-0186

$XMP.dc.title$

Sony NEX-6 $shootingData$, hand-held.

But I also give a lot of importance to the process, which implies training and the capability of see things that a distracted observer would miss. By internalising the process I can naturally enjoy sparkles of beauty even when I don't have a camera at hand, or when it's impossible to take a photo. Sometimes I'm driving through a highway, or sitting in a running train, and I find myself looking out of the window “mentally framing” things, perhaps waiting that a few objects in different plans align into the optimal composition, or appreciating the quality of the light which is illuminating them. Those “missed photos” were, at the beginning, a sort of frustration, I mean I was sorely upset that I didn't have the trigger just under my finger; but as time passed by, I somehow turned it into a pleasing experience. Even if I'm not actually taking a photo, some photographic concepts I've learned, such as the focal length, teach me how to see things in different perspectives and scale - from the breadth of the wide-angle landscape up to the small details of a flower caught with a long tele.

20120519-0042

$XMP.dc.title$

Nikon D7000 $shootingData$, hand-held.

20090624-0113

$XMP.dc.title$

Nikon D200 $shootingData$, hand-held.

All of this is very subjective and personal, so I don't want to be constrained by any kind of fashion or external opinion. While it's true that, as my technique and aesthetic sense improves with time I constantly re-evaluate photos that I took in the past, on the other hand I will always like a photo just because it triggered something inside me, even though it might be completely off the current canons, or - at the other extreme - a so-called conformist shot. That's why I'm not obsessed by access statistics, nor I am interested in getting “likes” or stars; or getting more links to my website to increase the traffic (recently I've even removed all the Google Analytics stuff from this site). These things are the death of beauty, the starters of a wicked competitive attitude. Thus I'm no more interested in contests and competitions - and I only publish my photos here, with just a few notable exceptions. I don't want to be constrained to try fashionable techniques, such as “compulsory” blurs or long exposures; I'd try them only if I wish.

After all, in no way I consider myself an artist, but just a practitioner of the art. I even take pictures in days with an empty sky, or with harsh light, if it happens that I am in some place with that conditions and I felt as I liked to freeze that moment. After all, landscape photography is depicting the reality out there (even though by means of one's own interpretation) and reality is not only made of perfect scenarios with that golden light of the sunset. Otherwise, we'd be talking about the Hyperuranion.

20140603-0900

$XMP.dc.title$

Sony NEX-6 $shootingData$, hand-held.

Still, since this post is about art and conformism, I have to start a not-so-short digression. Photography is a very recent form of art, and all of its history lies in the modernity age. I think this fact introduces quite a strong bias in evaluating things - I think I have some points to argue about a strongly distorted perception of things in this age. Since photography is part of the family of Visual Arts, and here we have a millennial history, there's something more interesting to see in this broader perspective. To simplify things I'm going to focus on the history of Visual Arts in my home country (the richest on the earth in this field). There has always been a strong relationship between arts and power; and in the past power was a matter of restricted groups. For about a millennium and one half, one of the strongest centres of power was the Catholic Church. Still, we had a very long sequence of Masters, including many from the Middle Age, constantly evolving in a variety of styles. For centuries, religious themes had been the only subjects in Visual Arts - so one might call this a limited set - and still we enjoy a huge amount of different ways in which artists were able to represent the same things over time. An explosion of creativity and innovation, always bringing masterworks, century after century. Even after the Council of Trent, which had a special political agenda about visual arts, we had Caravaggio and Bernini: both artists brought revolutionary ways of conceiving painting and sculpture, at the point of raising wild discussions; but, at the end of the day, they were always free to innovate. There have been a few cases in which the subject was subjected to a form of control - after all, arts were perceived as a mean to deliver a specific message - but there have never been constraints on style. The proof is in the huge amount of masterworks still hanging in churches, palaces and museums. In the meantime, during Renaissance a new class of secular patrons emerged (think of Lorenzo de' Medici) and they brought profane subjects, which broadened the spectrum of subjects. Then, in the latest centuries, power centres apparently started to dilute - we had, progressively, the rise of Bourgeoisie up to the spread of democracy. In theory, modernity should see such a high degree of freedom, creativity and beauty in Visual Arts - including photography.

20101016-0171

$XMP.dc.title$

Nikon D5000 $shootingData$, hand-held.

20050925-0022

$XMP.dc.title$

Nikon D70 $shootingData$, hand-held.

But I don't see it happening. A few years ago, when I first questioned myself with the problem of mannerism in photography, I decided to learn something more and attend some exhibits to learn about the current trends. For instance I attended the famous Rencontres d'Arles photo festival. I could see the most fashionable solutions to the mannerism problem: do strange, bad, poor, wretched, wicked photos. I still remember an exhibit by a “genius” that placed a pizza pie right in the middle of her landscape photos; sure, with tons of sophisms to pretend there was a rationale for that nonsense. My first and last time at Rencontres d'Arles. “Creativity” today just sounds as a hypocrisy for “strangeness”, and by strangeness I mean that people just trying to occupy yet another absurd corner. Part of this is due to the fact that freedom in this field is just a fictitious thing: the self-referential castes of art critics and, for what concerns photography, publishers grabbed the power to decide what's fashionable or not. They are no more the equerries that assisted their masters, acting as disseminators helping the spread of culture into the segment of observers, that was quickly growing as our societies were becoming wealthier. They didn't stick with the original, sane role of driving the original relationship between an artist and his patron to the relationship between an artist and his wider public; today they create and destroy artists at their will. And while the Church is no more the most prominent mind maker, there are other subtler kinds of power that pursue their own agendas.

Were I an artist, why should I enslave my creativity to the wills of those castes? Neither art critics nor publishers are the possible appropriate source of inspiration to fight conformism. And given that I'm not an artist, but a mere practitioner of the photographic art (which brings the advantage of not having the problem of making a living out of my skills), I see even less reasons for that. While I welcome sane creativity, mannerism is not a problem for me. I will never feel numb about the beauty of the real world out there that is reproduced in a photo.

That's my well though rationale argument for which I disagree with Ugo's “I don’t like it anymore”.

20081213-0054

$XMP.dc.title$

Nikon D200 $shootingData$, hand-held.

20090621-0142

$XMP.dc.title$

Nikon D200 $shootingData$, hand-held.

Given these premises, I think it's clear that my primary attitude about my keeper photos is: I like them and if others like them, the better; otherwise I don't care much.

But the very fact that I'm publishing them to the web does mean something: actually, I like to share up to a certain degree. Now, the problem arises about the capability of my photos to convey to readers the same feelings I experienced. This is an objective issue and thus I need to take advantage of the state of the art, because it's true that the proper technique can improve the communication skills. That's why I constantly read a few blogs of masters of the art whom I like and sometimes I participate in a critic forum (but carefully picked: one which is attended by a limited number of persons, that you can trust, and where the competitive attitude is barely perceived). Sure I can be convinced that something I did can be improved. Other times, I would keep things as they are, but at least I'd be aware that I see things in a very different way than other people. Awareness is always a key thing.

20110910-0058

$XMP.dc.title$

Nikon D5000 $shootingData$, hand-held.

And then there are places themselves. Shooting landscapes, to me, is also a way to become intimate with a place: a marsh in Maremma, a village perché in Provence, a valley in the Alps or a small church in Val d'Orcia. It implies knowing its history, the relationship with the people who live and lived there, possibly forging it (which is always a fundamental thing in Europe, even for wilderness). It means returning to it multiple times, in different seasons and light conditions. It means flying there with my mind, when I'm constrained to stay elsewhere, trying to imagine whether it's snowing or not, or there's the sun and a rainbow, or whether that mimosa tree in front of the chapel has already blossomed; or whether the greylag geese are already preparing for their Spring migration. A way, sometimes, to escape from some boring circumstances, but always flying to a real thing or place.

And - no, I never have enough of this.

20120216-0035

$XMP.dc.title$

Nikon D7000 $shootingData$, hand-held.

20140222-0070

$XMP.dc.title$

Sony NEX-6 $shootingData$, hand-held.

20140517-0077

$XMP.dc.title$

Sony NEX-6 $shootingData$, polariser, hand-held.

Java 8 introduced lambdas and streams, two tools that seem to offer many ways for improve our code, in particular for what concerns conciseness and readability. There are a lot of samples around, focusing often on over-simplified contexts. In this post I'm describing a small refactoring that I applied to a portion of code in a project I'm developing. With its own limitations, I think it's an interesting real-world case to analyse. In this post, I'm assuming that the reader knows the basic concepts and syntax of some Java 8 features, such as lamdas, Streams and Optional<T>.

First, let's give the relevant context. I have a MediaItem interface, which represents e.g. an audio file, which exposes a Metadata interface:

public interface Metadata
  {
    @Nullable
    public <T> T get (@Nonnull Key<T> key);

    @Nonnull
    public Set<Map.Entry<Key<?>, ?>> getEntries();
    …
  }

It's basically a type-safe Map, that there is a set of pre-defined Key items which carry the type information of the value they're associated with. So there's no need to cast the values coming out from the get() method.

Now I have to extract metadata items and store them into a semantic repository. You don't need to know a lot about semantic repositories, but the fact that they contain statements, or triples, in the form subject-predicate-object. Subjects or objects, when they refer to an entity and not a literal value, are basically the identifiers of the related entities (which are URIs in the semantic world). That's all you really need to know.

Indeed, for the scope of this post, you could pretend that the semantic repository is just a plain relational database in which I have to insert some SQL statements. The relevant point is that I'm going to insert them by firing an asynchronous message in a publish-and-subscribe architecture; a subscriber somewhere will be notified of the request and perform the insertion. For the sake of performance, I'm not firing a message for each statement, but I'm grouping them together (this might also have to do with transaction control: perhaps I want to process them as atomic batches). On this purpose, there's an AddStatementRequest message with its fluent Builder. The fluent nature of this object was a small problem with streams that I needed to solve.

Here it is the version of the code at the beginning of the refactoring:

public void importMediaItemEmbeddedMetadata (final @Nonnull MediaItem mediaItem, final @Nonnull URI mediaItemUri)
  {
    log.info("importMediaItemEmbeddedMetadata({}, {})", mediaItem, mediaItemUri);
    
    final MediaItem.Metadata metadata = mediaItem.getMetadata();
    final Integer trackNumber = metadata.get(MediaItem.Metadata.TRACK);
    final Integer sampleRate = metadata.get(MediaItem.Metadata.SAMPLE_RATE);
    final Integer bitRate = metadata.get(MediaItem.Metadata.BIT_RATE);
    final Duration duration = metadata.get(MediaItem.Metadata.DURATION);

    AddStatementsRequest.Builder builder = AddStatementsRequest.build();
    
    if (sampleRate != null)
      {
        builder = builder.with(mediaItemUri, MO.SAMPLE_RATE, literalFor(sampleRate));
      }

    if (bitRate != null)
      {
        builder = builder.with(mediaItemUri, MO.BITS_PER_SAMPLE, literalFor(bitRate));
      }

    if (trackNumber != null)
      {
        builder = builder.with(mediaItemUri, MO.TRACK_NUMBER, literalFor(trackNumber));
      }

    if (duration != null)
      {
        builder = builder.with(mediaItemUri, MO.DURATION, literalFor((float)duration.toMillis()));
      }
    
    messageBus.publish(builder.create());
  }

I think it is quite readable. There are two immediate code smells: the sequence of if statements, and the fact that I'm dealing with nulls.

Let's start from the latter issue. Java 8 offers the Optional<T> class which represents a value that can be present or not. I can refactor Metadata as follows:

public interface Metadata
  {
    @Nunnull
    public <T> Optional<T> get (@Nonnull Key<T> key);

    @Nonnull
    public Set<Map.Entry<Key<?>, ?>> getEntries();
    …
  }

So get() now is guaranteed to return a non null value. The method can be rewritten as follows:

public void importMediaItemEmbeddedMetadata (final @Nonnull MediaItem mediaItem, final @Nonnull URI mediaItemUri)
  {
    log.info("importMediaItemEmbeddedMetadata({}, {})", mediaItem, mediaItemUri);
    
    final MediaItem.Metadata metadata = mediaItem.getMetadata();
    final Optional<Integer> trackNumber = metadata.get(MediaItem.Metadata.TRACK);
    final Optional<Integer> sampleRate = metadata.get(MediaItem.Metadata.SAMPLE_RATE);
    final Optional<Integer> bitRate = metadata.get(MediaItem.Metadata.BIT_RATE);
    final Optional<Duration> duration = metadata.get(MediaItem.Metadata.DURATION);

    AddStatementsRequest.Builder builder = AddStatementsRequest.build();
    
    if (sampleRate.isPresent())
      {
        builder = builder.with(mediaItemUri, MO.SAMPLE_RATE, literalFor(sampleRate.get()));
      }

    if (bitRate.isPresent())
      {
        builder = builder.with(mediaItemUri, MO.BITS_PER_SAMPLE, literalFor(bitRate.get()));
      }

    if (trackNumber.isPresent())
      {
        builder = builder.with(mediaItemUri, MO.TRACK_NUMBER, literalFor(trackNumber.get()));
      }

    if (duration.isPresent())
      {
        builder = builder.with(mediaItemUri, MO.DURATION, literalFor((float)duration.get().toMillis()));
      }
    
    messageBus.publish(builder.create());
  }

Honestly, this is an almost neglectable improvement. Sure, isPresent() is marginally better readable than != null, but there's no much beef. The if statements are still needed, and while there can't be NPEs any longer, I can still get it wrong: if a presence check is wrong, sampleRate.get() will throw NoSuchElementException. So,  I've just exchanged an exception with another. While there's plenty of code samples like this, and flame wars about whether it's good or not, to me it's quite evident that this usage of Optional is basically meaningless.

Optional offers a more functionally oriented method, such as map() to apply a Function. It would eliminate conditionals, but wouldn't solve an issue, described below, with the fact that builder is not final. That's why I did not consider this route.

Now, a fundamental point is that, if you want quality in your code then you need testing. But a compiler of a statically-typed language could help in avoiding some blatant errors and, in the end, save some time. By introducing Optional it has not been the case.

Basically, the null-related issue is secondary. The problem here is conditioned by the major code-smell, which is the sequence of conditional statements. It's also an approach that badly scales: what if I need to add mapping for another dozen of metadata items?

Let's think of a Java 8-oriented refactoring that will bring the code down to 4 lines. Well, I'm lying: the fundamental lines will be 4+4, plus some other stuff. But improving the quality of code doesn't (always) mean literally shrinking lines, rather having better lines.

First, we realize that, rather than having a sequence of special-cases, we need a collection of metadata mappings, and iterating over it. In Java 8 we have lambda expressions that allow code an iteration in a single line. For instance, something such as the following pseudo-code:

AddStatementsRequest.Builder builder = AddStatementsRequest.build();
mapping.stream().forEach(() -> builder = builder.with(… /* do something smart */));
messageBus.publish(builder.create());

Unfortunately, it can't work whatever smart the thing is conceived. The problem is that a lambda is a sort of masked inner class, and the usual rule applies: if it accesses local variables declared outside its scope, they must be final. But a fluent Builder can't be referenced by a final variable (it prevents from writing builder = builder.with(...)). While at first sight one might think: “ok, these are the classic devil's details that jeopardise a could-be elegant approach, and I give up”, the problem is that we're looking at a very limited number of features offered by Java 8. Functional often requires that you re-think some details. For instance, a fluent Builder is a sort of 'collector' of things that are incrementally added. But Java 8 streams offer their own version of a Collector: an object that 'terminates' a stream, collecting all the elements in it into a single object. Perhaps we can replace our collector with their collector, and find that their collector fits better?

I received some feedback about this passage. It was pointed out that the problem is not only related to the limitation about lambdas and final references pointing to immutable objects such as Builder. Indeed from the design point of view a good functional approach should avoid side-effects.

So our code becomes:

Collector<Statement, List<Statement>, AddStatementsRequest> collector = ...;
AddStatementRequest request = mapping.stream(). … .collect(collector);
messageBus.publish(request);

Even better, taking advantage of static methods, in a single line:

messageBus.publish(mapping.stream(). … .collect(toAddStatementsRequest()));

Now, what is the cost of writing a custom Collector? Something like that:

@Nonnull
public static Collector<Statement, List<Statement>, AddStatementsRequest> toAddStatementsRequest()
  {
    return new ArrayListCollectorSupport<Statement, AddStatementsRequest>()
      {
        @Override @Nonnull
        public Function<List<Statement>, AddStatementsRequest> finisher() 
          {
            return statements -> new AddStatementsRequest(statements);
          }
      };  
  }

public abstract class ArrayListCollectorSupport<COLLECTED_TYPE, COLLECTING_TYPE> 
        implements Collector<COLLECTED_TYPE, List<COLLECTED_TYPE>, COLLECTING_TYPE>
  {
    @Override @Nonnull 
    public Supplier<List<COLLECTED_TYPE>> supplier() 
      {
        return ArrayList::new;
      } 

    @Override @Nonnull 
    public BiConsumer<List<COLLECTED_TYPE>, COLLECTED_TYPE> accumulator() 
      {
        return List::add;
      }

    @Override @Nonnull 
    public BinaryOperator<List<COLLECTED_TYPE>> combiner() 
      {
        return (left, right) -> { left.addAll(right); return left; };
      }

    @Override @Nonnull 
    public Set<Characteristics> characteristics() 
      {
        // Not CONCURRENT since ArrayList is not thread-safe
        return Collections.emptySet();
      }
  }

Honestly, we're adding a lot of lines of code. But:

ArrayListCollectorSupport is a very reusable class for many kinds of programmer-defined Collectors. Actually, it was already in my kitchen-sink library of small useful things that I reuse everywhere.
toAddStatementsRequest() is very specific to AddStatementsRequest, but I can reuse it a few times.

I think most people working with Java 8 know Collectors up to a certain degree, since they offer some facility methods to easily re-pack a Stream into a List, or format it to a String with controllable formatting. But I see that only a few ones understand that they could write their own Collector for their classes, and this kind of usage of the Java 8 APIs can be useful for achieving a real benefit. Sometimes you have complex logics in the collection strategy that don't fit with a simply iterative approach. For instance, within a Stream you can filter() item by item, but you cannot take a decision based on the whole collection of items accumulated so far. In a earlier version of the code related to this post it was possible to override statements with the same subject and predicate, because a certain piece of medatada was first extracted by an audio file and later superseded by a better piece of information retrieved from the web. This was implemented in a custom Collector.

This requirement went away with other refactorings, so now the custom Collector was removed. I'm leaving it in this post just for didactic purposes - let's just recall that in some more complex cases it can help us. Ignoring that the Java 8 Streams API is made not only of Streams might make you give up a refactoring and preclude an interesting way to re-shape your code.

Now, let's focus on the stream. We can start with the whole set of metadata entries:

mediaItem.getMetadata().getEntries().stream()

and then apply a filter for picking only those that I want to store to my semantic repository:

filter(e -> MAPPER.containsKey(e.getKey())

Now the trickiest part. I have to 'translate' a Metadata Key in the corresponding Statement. A Statement, I repeat, is a triple subject-predicate-object. In my case the subject is the id (i.e. the URI) of the mediaItem. This is a variable part for each invocation, so can't be a responsiblity of the MAPPER. The predicate and object are fixed for each metadata key, so they can be a responsibility of the MAPPER. First, we need to introduce a Pair class which encapsulates predicate and object:

@Immutable @RequiredArgsConstructor @ToString
static class Pair
  {
    @Nonnull
    private final URI predicate;
    
    @Nonnull
    private final Value object;
  }

I'm taking advantage of Lombok for saving some plumbing code (constructor and getters). At this point I can define the MAPPER as a Map from Key to a Function transforming an Object (the metadata item value) to a Pair of predicate and object:

private static final Map<Key<?>, Function<Object, Pair>> MAPPER = new HashMap<>();

static
  {
    MAPPER.put(Metadata.TRACK,       v -> new Pair(MO.P_TRACK_NUMBER,    literalFor((int)v)));
    MAPPER.put(Metadata.SAMPLE_RATE, v -> new Pair(MO.P_SAMPLE_RATE,     literalFor((int)v)));
    MAPPER.put(Metadata.BIT_RATE,    v -> new Pair(MO.P_BITS_PER_SAMPLE, literalFor((int)v)));
    MAPPER.put(Metadata.DURATION,    v -> new Pair(MO.P_DURATION,
                                                literalFor((float)((Duration)v).toMillis())));
  }

Note that here we are already losing something. While in the original code, with the “unrolled” conditional statements, we were taking advantage of the type information brought by Key, here we have lost it. For this reason, we are forced to put explicit casts in the parameter of literalFor(). I don't see solutions, and the cause is the limited support of type information, not reified, in Java generics.

The final touch is to add to Pair a method to create a Statement with a given subject:

@Nonnull
public Statement createStatementWithSubject (final @Nonnull URI subject)
  {
    return ...createStatement(subject, predicate, object);
  }

How to use that stuff? By applying a mapping to the stream, in which we first get the relevant Function inside the MAPPER, then apply it to the metadata value, retrieve the Pair and create the Statement:

stream().map(e -> MAPPER.get(e.getKey()).apply(e.getValue()).createStatementWithSubject(mediaItemUri))

Putting all together:

public void importTrackMetadata (final @Nonnull MediaItem mediaItem, final @Nonnull URI mediaItemUri)
  {
    log.debug("importTrackMetadata({}, {})", mediaItem, mediaItemUri);
    messageBus.publish(mediaItem.getMetadata().getEntries().stream()
        .filter(e -> MAPPER.containsKey(e.getKey()))
        .map(e -> MAPPER.get(e.getKey()).apply(e.getValue()).createStatementWithSubject(mediaItemUri))
        .collect(toAddStatementsRequest()));
  }

So, let's recap. The original method had 15 lines (excluding logging, blanks and braces). The refactored method has got 4, but part of the information has been moved to the further 4 lines that populate MAPPER. In the end, we have 8 lines: we saved 7 lines. But we had to introduce Pair (4 lines, and a few one saved by Lombok): 4 further lines. Roughly, the number of lines didn't change. Was it worth the effort?

First, the refactored code scales much better: for each new metadata item to map, we need to add one more line (we can't do better than this!); in the original code we needed to add a whole new if statement. Not only it's made by 2 lines, but it's less readable. In the end, we split the original blob into an imperative part (the one in the method, with the stream iteration), which will stay the same forever. Then we have a purely declarative part, which is the code populating MAPPER. There's not much to test in it, but the correctness of the mapping. So we have split an original blob of two responsibilities into two separate sections, each one with a single responsibility. We can understand each section separately, focusing only on a few lines at a time.

On the other hand, I think that many would argue that they find the new solution more “complex” (whatever the word means...) than the original.

The most controversial line is clearly this:

.map(e -> MAPPER.get(e.getKey()).apply(e.getValue()).createStatementWithSubject(mediaItemUri))

Is there any further room for improvement? It can be refactored as:

.map(e -> MAPPER.forItem(e).createStatementWithSubject(mediaItemUri))

but with a non neglectable cost, as we need to create a subclass:

static class Mapper extends HashMap<Key<?>, Function<Object, Pair>>
  {
    @Nonnull
    public Pair forItem (final @Nonnull Map.Entry<Key<?>, ?> entry)
      {
        return get(entry.getKey()).apply(entry.getValue());
      }
  }

We're not saving any line here, instead we're introducing 4 more lines. And they are not reusable. In the end I applied this refactoring as well, but I'm not sure it's worth while.

What conclusion to draw? This is a specific problem, but a real case one. Undoubtedly, Java 8 was useful for refactoring my code in a way that has better responsibility separation, readability and maintainability. In terms of lines of code, there's not really a real gain, even considering some of the new lines I wrote are at least partially reusable.

So, if we limit ourselves to the mere LoC count, we could be easily displeased. When taking a broader horizon in consideration, the advantage is evident.

There are other advantages, in addition to readability. Streams are parallelizable, which means that if I had a large numbers of items to map, the refactored code would be faster, by taking advantage of multiple cores.

PS. While I was writing this post, my code evolved further. In particular, I found that the semantic schema I was applying was not correct: some metadata items have to be related to a certain entity, while others to a different one. The current code is:

static class Mapper extends HashMap<Key<?>, Function<Object, Pair>>
  {
    @Nonnull
    public Pair forItem (final @Nonnull Map.Entry<Key<?>, ?> entry)
      {
        return get(entry.getKey()).apply(entry.getValue());
      }
  }

private static final Mapper SIGNAL_MAPPER = new Mapper();
private static final Mapper TRACK_MAPPER = new Mapper();

static
  {
    TRACK_MAPPER. put(Metadata.TRACK,       v -> new Pair(MO.P_TRACK_NUMBER,    literalFor((int)v)));

    SIGNAL_MAPPER.put(Metadata.SAMPLE_RATE, v -> new Pair(MO.P_SAMPLE_RATE,     literalFor((int)v)));
    SIGNAL_MAPPER.put(Metadata.BIT_RATE,    v -> new Pair(MO.P_BITS_PER_SAMPLE, literalFor((int)v)));
    SIGNAL_MAPPER.put(Metadata.DURATION,    v -> new Pair(MO.P_DURATION,
                                                       literalFor((float)((Duration)v).toMillis())));
  }

public void importAudioFileMetadata (final @Nonnull MediaItem mediaItem, 
                                     final @Nonnull URI signalUri,
                                     final @Nonnull URI trackUri)
  {
    log.debug("importAudioFileMetadata({}, {}, {})", mediaItem, signalUri, trackUri);
    final Set<Map.Entry<Key<?>, ?> entries = mediaItem.getMetadata().getEntries();
    messageBus.publish(entries.stream()
                              .filter(e -> SIGNAL_MAPPER.containsKey(e.getKey()))
                              .map(e -> SIGNAL_MAPPER.forItem(e).createStatementWithSubject(signalUri))
                              .collect(toAddStatementsRequest()));
    messageBus.publish(entries.stream()
                              .filter(e -> TRACK_MAPPER.containsKey(e.getKey()))
                              .map(e -> TRACK_MAPPER.forItem(e).createStatementWithSubject(trackUri))
                              .collect(toAddStatementsRequest()));
  }

The readability improvement due do the introduction of MAPPER is now even more evident: the original sequence of conditional statements would easily induce errors in mis-matching the metadata items with the URIs of the two entities, while now we have two MAPPERs with their own configuration.

I have to further stress the point, anyway, that the final warranty of quality can't be given by syntax, but I need testing. Actually I have an integration test running over a few thousands audio files of my personal collection that makes sure data is properly translated; I couldn't have applied this radical refactoring without being supported by this test that assured me I was not introducing regressions at each step.

The better syntax, however, might help in making fewer errors and spending less time to run tests, detect problems and fix them.

People who make computer systems including a User Interface (UI) often refer to the Model View Controller (MVC) pattern to drive their design. MVC is actually a mainstream pattern of fundamental importance. But there are lots of misunderstandings about MVC and some improved patterns have been proposed to address some problems of the original MVC, which by the way is rather old.

The basic good idea behind MVC - and it was MVC to first introduce it - is Separated Presentation, as defined by Martin Fowler (emphasis is mine):

Ensure that any code that manipulates presentation only manipulates presentation, pushing all domain and data source logic into clearly separated areas of the program. ... The idea behind Separated Presentation is to make a clear division between domain objects that model our perception of the real world, and presentation objects that are the GUI elements we see on the screen. Domain objects should be completely self contained and work without reference to the presentation, they should also be able to support multiple presentations, possibly simultaneously.

This is basically a refinement of Separation of Concerns (SoC) for the UI context. The structure of MVC is the following:

20120808/MVC-class-diagram.png

Class diagram for MVC

There are three participants in the pattern:

The Model. This participant is usually part of the domain model and is made of one or more domain abstractions (e.g. a list of Person objects). It might be connected to a persistence facility (e.g. a relational database) and allow concurrent modification by means of transactions, but this is not relevant in the MVC perspective; actually the Model can be designed in many different ways. What's important is that it contains domain objects and exposes functions to manipulate them. This participant is completely ignorant of the UI - it even doesn't know what a UI is.
The View. This participant is the one that actually realizes the UI, so we can imagine it's made with a UI-specific technology, such as Swing, Android or Vaadin. It knows about the widget layout on the screen, the way widgets interact with the user, it can change their state as well as listen to user gestures made by means of the mouse, the keyboard, the touch screen or other input peripherals.
The Controller. This participant provides the “intelligence” of the UI, as it receives notifications by the View about user gestures and interprets them as requests to trigger business logics that manipulate the model or to change the View itself (e.g. by rendering a new screen, web page and so on). We can refer to this set of responsibilities as “presentation logic”.

From a dynamic point of view the interactions in a MVC design can be modelled as the union of two Observer patterns. Fowler calls it Observer Synchronization:

The View observes the Model and whenever the latter changes it pulls the new pieces of data to update the UI.
The Controller observes the View and whenever the user does something it reacts appropriately.

20120808/MVC-sequence-diagram.png

Sequence diagrams for MVC

Since design patterns in the real world are seldom found in a “pure“ way, there can be many legitimate variations on the basic theme. On the other hand MVC is probably one of the most misused terms in computer engineering: many people use the term just to mean Separated Presentation, that is a “good” design of a UI, but they aren't actually using MVC.

Before going on and criticize MVC, it's fundamental to understand a few points:

What's the Model? In many simple examples this participant is directly implemented by a Domain Abstraction class. This could be ok with some categories of applications, for instance monolithic desktop applications. If the application connects to a remote server, it's likely that the Model is an adapter to the real Domain Abstraction (for instance by means of a remoting proxy), or a local copy of it (for instance by means of a Data Transfer Object (DTO)).
Many popular UI frameworks that are considered by many to be MVC, aren't properly MVC. For instance, Swing architecture is

“loosely based on the traditional MVC design”

(quote from the original Sun paper), but it departs significantly from MVC for some details. It's true that many of them are related to some inner parts that aren't necessarily interesting for the developer: for instance, the relationship between components and “UI delegates” can safely be ignored if you aren't developing a look & feel. Ignoring these parts and looking at the technology only with the perspective of the integration with a back end, the MVC characterization can be still good.

A more relevant point is that most UI frameworks provide their specific “intermediate” models at least for the most complex components: think for instance of Swing javax.swing.table.TableModel, Android android.widget.Adapter and Vaadin com.vaadin.data.Container. These are adapters that “translate” data in a way that can be directly consumed by the UI components. This concept, which is pretty useful, is called “Presenter” by a variation of MVC called Model View Presenter (MVP).

How is the notification facility implemented? In the diagram we supposed to have a simple event notification mechanism without attributes, so the View later reads the Model; but it could be possible to avoid that further step by augmenting the notification with an object describing the changes. These are minor details, anyway.

Also, in this area a technique that has got some popularity is data binding (BeansBinding is an example in the Java ecosystem): by means of language feature or a specific library, it allows to logically bind properties in two different objects, so when one changes in the former object another is changed in the latter. Data Binding can be pretty useful with forms, as it reduces the complexity of implementing the data item exchange with the View. Think of a form with dozens of items: instead of exposing getter and setter methods for each one, you just need one getter and one setter for an object containing all the items as bindable properties.

For the scope of this discussion, we consider that the characterizing feature of MVC is the direct communication between the Model and the View, which is the source of many issues. Let's ask ourselves some questions:

Which is (or should be) the most valuable part of our design?

Which is (or should be) the least valuable part?

Where should we spend more resources for automated testing?

The most valuable parts of the design are the Model and the Controller. The former is part of the Domain Model, which is the core of our project, and it has got a strict relationship with data and business rules, which usually are the most stable and valuable portions of a software application. The latter implements the presentation logic and it's responsible for doing the right things on behalf of the user itself.

The least valuable part of the design should be the View. UI technologies are very volatile (I'd also say fashionable) and very depending on the context. If we don't have specific deployment issues (it happens for instance where deployment is supervised in some way) we can realize a full fledged desktop application by using Swing, JavaFX 2, the NetBeans or the Eclipse Platforms. If we have deployment issues it's better to go with a web application, for instance made with Vaadin. If we want to run on mobile appliances, we could pick Android.

Why am I mentioning Vaadin as a web technology example? For this blog post I'm keeping quite generic about UI technologies, just stressing the fact that I want a design that doesn't depend on them. But in practice I know that it works with the class of UI technologies that support “push updates”, that is UI changes that are performed in reaction to a stimulus originating from the server. Most of the technologies that are not web based support them, but the traditional web frameworks don't since they restrain updates within the “pull” approach typical of a HTTP request/response. Fortunately, modern frameworks for Rich Internet Applications support push updates by means of AJAX. Vaadin is one of them; it's not the only one, but one that I have a good experience of.

All these technologies have their own libraries for creating a UI, so an hypothetical application that must be deployed to multiple channels (e.g. Web and Android), or that during its life must be ported from an environment to the other, should be able to change its View implementation with the minimal effort and without touching the Model and the Controller.

Unfortunately, MVC doesn't separate enough for accomplishing to this requirement. These are some of the most common issues (in random order):

Formatting. The View directly accesses the Model, that we can call “raw data”. For instance, a date could be represented by a java.util.Date, but almost for sure we want it to be rendered in a human readable way, often localized. This behaviour wouldn't change whether we have a desktop, a web or a mobile application, so if it is implemented in the View we are going to lose it when that specific View implementation goes away - and re-implement it in the new View.

Some presentation logic in the View. The View very often has got some portions of presentation logic. For instance, our requirements could mandate that a measure readout in a gauge is rendered in different colours in function of the value (e.g. normal values are green, alert values are in flashing red). While different UI technologies require different code - changing colour in Swing, Vaadin or Android is made by calling different methods - a common mistake is to put the decision about which colour to use in the View rather than in the Controller, perhaps also because the UI technology offers some support for this operation. As for the previous point: change the View and the implementation goes away.

UI behaviour consistency. When MVC was defined most of UIs were just made of forms for data entry and a full application could be thought as a sequence of forms coordinated by a flow controller. Most of the View behaviour was filling form fields, picking menu items and pressing buttons. Today we have much richer ways of interaction, for instance contextual menus and reaction to click, swipe, pinch, etc... and furthermore we want consistency throughout the whole application: that is, a gauge representing a temperature in different parts of the application should always offer the same contextual menu and react in the same way to click, swipe, pinch, etc... (note that we're talking of a simple widget representing a single piece of data, not a whole View, thus decomposing Views doesn't help here). The typical way to cope with this requirement is to develop specific widgets for specific data types, for instance a TemperatureWidget, but since widgets are technology dependent this ends up in making a SwingTemperatureWidget, a VaadinTemperatureWidget and an AndroidTemperatureWidget. This ends up with further presentation logic in the View implementation that will be lost when that implementation goes away.

Lack of flexibility in data binding. If you like data binding, there are high chances that you experience some frustration when you move off simple cases. In MVC, binding can only occur between M and V. But this also means that the binding framework must provide support for formatting and formal validation (BeansBinding happened to do that, but this is not always the case). And what about derived or split properties? For instance, a single item in the Model could be represented by separate form items in the View (e.g. a phone number could be split into a prefix and the proper number). Usually these issues are addressed with further presentation logic in the View... and at this point you know the rest of the history (if instead you're thinking of binding the view with something else than the Model you're probably on the right track, but this is not MVC any longer... read below).

Testing. We didn't answer the previous question about where to spend more resources for automated testing. The answer is obvious: in every place where there's some valuable behaviour. Given the previous points, with MVC we have application-specific behaviour in the View, not only in the Controller, so we must test both (the Model of course is always tested on its own). Since the View depends on the technology, its testing depends too: so we have to use specific Swing, Vaadin and Android testing frameworks. Change UI technology... and you have to rewrite all the tests for your View.

For what concerns testing, there's an additional point. Even if you ignore the problem of switching the UI technology, automatic testing of a UI can be complex. There are many products that allow to do things such as recording user gestures, playing them back against a UI and asserting postconditions (Selenium being one of the popular ones in the web world), but after some initial enthusiasm I find that they are too much expensive to use and to maintain. I had a better experience with Swing automated testing, but now I think that a cheaper, alternate way of testing a UI must be found.

The underlying issues that we can infer from the previous points is that in MVC:

the View does too many things

we are forced to put too much value in the View
when we want / must change the UI technology all that value is lost
automated tests for the View are expensive

What we really need is a dumb View, really focused only on the graphic responsibilities. This is where Presentation Abstraction Control (PAC) can help.

Presentation Abstraction Control (PAC)

We can see PAC as an evolution of MVC: we still have three participants, but responsibilities are better distributed in two of them and there's some clean up in the interactions:

The Abstraction. It plays the same role of the Model in MVC, so there are no further comments.

The Presentation. It's the dumb View we were searching for.

The Control. It plays an enriched role of the Controller in MVC.

20120808/PAC-class-diagram.png

Class diagram for PAC

The different responsibilities of the pair PC with respect to VC are clear if you look at the interactions in the diagram:

20120808/PAC-sequence-diagram.png

Sequence diagrams for PAC

A good general guideline for evaluating a design is the presence or lack of symmetry. Generally speaking, symmetry is a plus. An asymmetry means that one task and its opposite, or its complementary, are performed in a different way. Unless there's a specific reason, this is just unjustified complexity, to be eliminated to comply with the Occam's razor. Compare the sequence diagrams for MVC and PAC: while PAC is symmetric (both interactions originating from the View and from the Abstraction linearly involve all the three participants), MVC is not (interactions originating from the Model don't involve the Controller).

There's no coupling between the Presentation and the Abstraction, as everything is mediated by the Control. In this way, the Control can take care of all the presentation logic and there are no residual parts in the Presentation. Referring to one of the examples above, when we need to render a Date, this means that it's possible to format it in the Control and then pass a String to the Presentation. In other words, this means that, when speaking of simple data items, the Presentation can only deal with Strings, to be rendered as they are. For instance, look at this code sketch:

public interface PersonAbstraction
  {
    public Date getBirthDate();
  }

public interface PersonPresentation
  {
    public void renderBirthDate (String birthDate);
  }

public class PersonControl
  {
    private PersonAbstraction person = ...;

    public void populateBirthDate()
     {
       SimpleDateFormat format = new SimpleDateFormat(...);
       presentation.renderBirthDate(format.format(person.getBirthDate()));
     }
  }

public class SwingPersonPresentation extends JPanel implements PersonPresentation
  {
    private JTextField tfBirthDate = new JTextField();

    public void renderBirthDate (String birthDate)
      {
        tfBirthDate.setText(birthDate);
      }
  }

As promised, no logics in the Presentation. Just get incoming data and render them in the proper place. All the other mentioned problems can be solved in a similar way: for instance, decide which colour to use in the Control and then call Presentation methods such as renderTemperature (int value, Color color). Imagine that an implementation for Vaadin or Android wouldn't be much different.

In the original description of PAC there's much more than this. For instance the pattern is defined in terms of agents and in general there's a better guidance to decomposing complex UIs. All interesting stuff that I'm ignoring in the scope of this post, but that I will pick in future.

On these premises, since the Presentation is dumb (no logics), there's less value in testing it. The whole set of user-UI interactions now stays in the Control, so it can be tested by mocking both the Presentation and the Abstraction with one of your regular Java tools such as JUnit, TestNG and Mockito. It also means that you can design in TDD (Test Driven Design) if you wish. More sophisticated testing can include integration tests where you have almost the whole application (I mean, the Abstraction is the real back end, not mocked), while the Presentation is still mocked.

There are some things to be clarified here. With this simplified kind of tests are you safe that Presentation is populated with the correct data and the application properly reacts to user gestures? Not completely. What you're sure of is that the object implementing the Presentation is called with the correct data and that when the callbacks in the Control are invoked the proper behaviour is triggered. What you miss is the very last step ("the last mile"): your specific Presentation implementation could miss to pass an inbound string to JTextField.setText() or could forget to bind a JButton to the Control callbacks. So, by restricting automated tests to mocked Presentations you're losing something. Is this a problem? How can be solved? Consider the following points:

I've never seen applications deployed to production after only automated tests were passed, without a final supervision by means of a human tester. There are some aspects, such as the visual quality of the rendering, that are very hard, if not impossible, to automatically test: for instance, how can you test whether a text is rendering on a background with insufficient contrast? Or whether a font is too small to be read, or too large to render the whole contents in a text box? These are things to be tested by the human eye. The important thing with human testing it's that it's expensive and must be reduced to the minimum.

The responsibility of the Presentation is so simple that it's less probable to make mistakes and they are restricted to very simple ones. I mean: with a MVC View, it could happen that you rendered the wrong data because of failing presentation logic. With a PAC Presentation, either you don't see data rendered (because you forgot to call that setText()), or they are correct (because they have been prepared by the Control). In a similar fashion, in a View pressing a button could trigger the wrong behaviour; with a Presentation either the button does nothing or it does the right thing (because it's fully implemented by the Control). Of course “less probable” doesn't mean ”impossible”: but given that you have to perform some human-based testing anyway, the human tester can also easily spot the trivial errors that we are talking about. The added cost of to perform this task is negligible.
If you still want some form of automated test for your Presentation, you can consider using a specific UI technology framework exercising not the whole application, but each single Presentation in isolation with a mocked Control.

The details about testing will be more clear when I'll introduce some real-world code in a further post.

Summing up, PAC solved some problems, with the exception of two: the UI behaviour consistency and the lack of flexibility of the data binding. That's what the Presentation Model is for.

The Presentation Model

Martin Fowler defines the Presentation Model as (emphasis is mine):

Represent the state and behavior of the presentation independently of the GUI controls used in the interface. ... Presentation Model pulls the state and behavior of the view out into a model class that is part of the presentation. The Presentation Model coordinates with the domain layer and provides an interface to the view that minimizes decision making in the view. The view either stores all its state in the Presentation Model or synchonizes its state with Presentation Model frequently. ... A view then simply projects the state of the presentation model onto the glass.

In other words, the Presentation Model is a sort of intermediate object between the Presentation and the Abstraction. It doesn't have any knowledge of specific UI widgets, but provides the models that can be bound to them. For instance, an Abstraction can represent a Person in a registry with the name, the job description and a photo. Its Presentation Model could provide a short description (e.g. name + job) to be rendered in a list row, transform the photo into a small icon to be rendered near the description, and provide callbacks for the click and double click gestures, as well as an enumeration of further callbacks that could be rendered in a contextual menu.

The Presentation Model is a very similar concept to the Presenter in the previously cited Model View Presenter pattern.

It's a responsibility of the Control to instantiate and properly prepare a Presentation Model for an Abstraction. The Control would never directly expose an Abstraction to the Presentation to ask for it to be rendered; in its place it would pass the Presentation Model for it. In other words, we can say that the Presentation would never see and access a “naked” Abstraction, but only operate on it by means of its Presentation Model. Thus, the Presentation Model works as an Adapter of the Abstraction for the Presentation. By creating the same Presentation Model for a given Abstraction and reusing it for all the PAC instances in our application we are making sure that the UI will always behave in a consistent way.

The Presentation Model can also provide a solution for flexible data binding: instead of binding the Presentation to the Abstraction, you can bind it to the Presentation Model. It can expose a mix of the original Abstraction properties and derived ones (such as the description defined as name + job in the previous example).

20120808/PAC-with-PM-class-diagram.png

Class diagram for PAC with a Presentation Model

Generically speaking, the Presentation Model shouldn't depend on any UI technology. For instance, a developer focusing on Swing could be tempted to model the callbacks for the click gesture as a javax.swing.Action: after all, a Swing Presentation could easily pull it out of the Presentation Model and register it to a Swing component. In a similar fashion, if the Abstraction contains a hierarchic data structure that can be rendered, one might be tempted to implement it with a javax.swing.tree.TreeModel in the Presentation Model. Unfortunately, this would make the Presentation Model unusable with Vaadin or Android. Thus, the PresentationModel should expose generic classes (e.g. generically designed things such as CallBack or Hierarchy). These generic classes would be then “adapted” to their Swing, or Vaadin, or Android counterparts. This sounds as an additional work, but it's very simple and reusable, as shown by the following diagram:

20120808/Real-world-PM-class-diagram.png

A real world example of how a Presentation Model interacts with a Presentation for a project made with Swing.

Entities outside the packages are not depending on any UI technology; entities in the “Swing & reusable ..." package are reusable for all applications based on the Swing technology. Similar diagrams for Vaadin or Android could be drawn by just replacing the specific classes.

Sometimes it's advisable the opposite approach because some UI technology could already provide existing classes that are already a good Presentation Model or a good basis for it. The NetBeans Platform, for instance, offers a org.openide.node.Node class which is an excellent support, performing a number of integration tasks with the rest of the Platform. It could be expensive to rewrite that features. With the NetBeans Platform my approach is to use a Presentation Model implementation that inherits from Node. Both approaches can be made to co-exist by referring to a Presentation Model by means of an interface (or abstract class) and using a Factory pattern which returns the most appropriate implementation.

There's a trade off to apply here and often you have to give up to something. Most UI frameworks, or add-on libraries for them, offer specific support for common tasks: for instance, think of a table model that is associated to a SQL query, capable of self-populating and perhaps even in lazy mode (by just querying the minimum set of data to fill the page). In other cases, such as in Vaadin, you have specific APIs for building an Abstraction upon them. By using those features the UI framework will let you create a working application in minutes - a faster approach, definitely. My take is that you should give up to that (unless you are just doing a quick prototype): what you gain in the short term will show an additional cost in the medium and long term. My experience is that with the proper design it's not hard to develop a small set of classes that offer the same features in a UI technology neutral fashion. Of course, only you can make the correct evaluation, case by case.

PAC and Presentation Model, when properly implemented, can solve all the MVC issues that we've mentioned. But we can further improve our design to add some flexibility. For instance, for what concerns UI consistency, we assumed that a given Abstraction must be rendered always in the very same way throughout the UI. But sometimes there are exceptions: for instance, in some cases we'd like to prevent a contextual menu from appearing, in other cases we'd like to add or remove some menu item. Or we could need slightly different behaviours of the same PAC reused in two different applications. The most immediate solution is to implement alternate Presentation Models. But there's a better approach that delivers this flexibility without a proliferation of Presentation Models - indeed, we could even have only one single Presentation Model for everything!

DCI adds dynamic behaviour and flexibility to the Presentation Model

Data Context and Interaction (DCI) is the pattern that can help us. First, let's recall its basic concepts. This pattern is made of three participants:

The Datum is a stateful class only representing plain data with a very simple behaviour (the one which does not involve interactions with other objects). For instance, in the classic BankAccount example, there would not be a transfer() method (this requires another BankAccount, or another source or target), but a withdraw() or a deposit() (that is, the “partial” operations that are seen by a single instance of Datum). Apart from this refinement, a Datum is very close to the Model in MVC and to the Abstraction in PAC.
A Role is a stateless class that cooperates with one or more Datum instances, providing the non elementary behaviour related to interactions. Referring to the previous example, a Transferable role can expose the transfer() method by making bankAccount1.withdraw() and bankAccount2.deposit() to properly cooperate. Roles are stateless since they always operate on the state provided by a Datum (by means of methods exposed by Datum, or perhaps by directly accessing its state - it's reasonable to think of a Role as a friend class to a Datum).
When properly designed, Roles are pretty generic: for instance a Transferable can be applied to a BankAccount, but also to a CashAmount, or a DebitCardAccount and such.

A Context is a class representing a specific algorithm, use case or user story, or even an entire application where it makes sense to associate Roles to Data. Its responsibility is to instantiate Roles, bind them to and unbind from the Datum when needed. In fact, according to DCI, Roles must not be statically associated with Data, but dynamically attached and detached in function of the need. In this way, Data are most likely to be stable and reusable in different projects, while specific Roles can be developed ad hoc. This means that we should never see code such as BankAccount implements Transferable, but rather a getTransferable() method in BankAccount (or something even better).

20120808/DCI-class-diagram.png

Class diagram for DCI - note how interactions only occur among Roles or between a Role and client code

Given these premises, we can infer the following facts:

A single Domain Abstraction is no more represented by a single class, but by a dynamic aggregate of a Datum and Roles.

Datum objects never directly interact among them or with other classes, such as controllers. In other words, nothing can see a “naked” Datum: Roles act as Adapters among Datum objects and other classes.
When we focus on a given context, it's quite easy to define some very meaningful and reusable set of Roles. For instance, in the UI context things such as Renderable, Clickable, ContextualMenuProvider.

The fact that there are classes that are never seen “naked”, but accessed by means of adapters, should remind you of something I've written in the previous paragraph about the Presentation Model. Actually, we can think that if we're able to provide a set of UI-related Roles, properly designed so they are not technology-dependent, we can integrate PAC, Presentation Model and DCI so the Presentation Model just becomes a container of DCI Roles. In this perspective, the PAC Control is also a DCI Context which, knowing both the DCI Datum and the PAC Presentation, creates a Presentation Model with the Roles required for the interaction with the UI. Being the new Presentation Model just a dynamic container of Roles, it's possible to think of a universal Presentation Model for any kind of Abstraction.

Note that the Abstraction itself can be designed according to DCI (i.e. it could be already an aggregate of a Datum and Roles) or not. In the latter case, the Control would always create the Roles from scratch; in the former case, it could reuse some existing Role already present in the Domain Abstraction. I think that there are advantages in using DCI also for the Abstractions an application, but this is not a requirement. In other words, if you already have a back-end design not made with DCI, you can safely introduce DCI only for the Presentation and Control.

The dynamic and flexible behaviour in the presentation logic we were advocating for can be now easily achieved with the proper design. Instead of having hardwired methods such  as:

public interface PresentationModel
  {
    public Clickable getClickable();
    public ContextualMenuProvider getContextualMenuProvider();
  }

we can think of something generic such as:

public interface PresentationModel
  {
    public <Role> Role as (Class<Role> roleType);
  }

So we can think of a Presentation containing the following code:

PresentationModel pm = ...;
pm.as(Clickable.class).click();
pm.as(ContextualMenuProvider.class).renderContextualMenu();

This Presentation Model would allow to dynamically add, remove or replace Roles according to the needs of the specific Context, furthermore without having to rely on a closed set of predefined Roles.

I've been using these patterns together with success for a few years now in various projects using Swing + NetBeans Platform, Vaadin and Android. In this post I've kept code samples at a minimum in order to focus more on concepts and UML diagrams. Full examples of working Java code will be the focus of further posts.

The sample photos and more are also available at larger sizes in the diary.

There's only one thing better than looking at a lavender field: being inside a lavender field. Lavender fields are a multi-sensory experience: floods of colours, a sweet smell and the gentle buzzing sound of bees. Since when I started taking photos of lavender fields, in 2006, I wished I was able to convey at least parts of these sensations in a photo.

The basic idea is simple: get a wide-angle lens and shoot low on the ground, very close to a plant, so it pops out in the foreground. The wider the lens, the more dramatic the effect, so ... why not trying with a fish-eye? I did it the past July, even though I only had a few hours for a quick visit to a lavender field in southern France. Being in a hurry, I couldn't try everything I wanted, but as a first attempt I got decent results.

20110711-0014

Lavender fields at Valensole.

Nikon D7000 $shootingData$, hand-held.

The first approach is the “sea of lavender” mode: shoot at the height of plants' top and in a direction perpendicular to the field rows. It's not hard to do, provided that you pay attention to two details:

Use the hyperfocal technique for maximizing the depth of field. Even in this mode, it's likely that some spikes are too close to the lens and thus they get slightly out of focus. Try to put them at the sides of the photo, keeping the centre part sharp.
If possible, prevent straight objects from being framed: they would be rendered curvy because of the fish-eye effect. Even if you manage in transforming them into straight lines with a “de-fishing” filter, they wouldn't like to appear perpendicular to the ground because of perspective distortion (which doesn't go away with de-fishing). Unfortunately, in my scene there were many phone poles; but their distracting effect is reduced since they appear very small because of the distance.

In the previous photo, the spike at the left edge wasn't so out of focus as it appears. Its fuzziness is due to a additional blurring caused by de-fishing (which stretches a lot the image near the corners).

20110711-0023

Lavender fields at Valensole.

Nikon D7000 $shootingData$, hand-held.

Try different heights for the camera, and eventually having the camera slightly looking towards the ground. In this way, you can manage in framing a whole plant, not only the upper spikes.

A totally different approach is to frame the sky putting the camera on the ground (I call it “the ant's point of view”).

20110711-0020

The ant's point of view.

Nikon D7000 $shootingData$

20110711-0021

The ant's point of view.

Nikon D7000 $shootingData$

The ant's point of view is more challenging as many things must be taken care of:

The camera must be as low as possible. My tripod, even in the lowest configuration, is too tall. Maybe the Skimmer Ground Pod could be used, but I didn't have it with me; so I directly laid the camera on the ground, facing up (pay attention not to scratch the LCD panel: put a cloth between the camera and the ground). In either way, it's clear that you can't look into the viewfinder to control the composition, so you have to go with trial and error (and take a lot of shoots). Perhaps a camera such as the Nikon D5000, with its tilting viewer, can be helpful, but it doesn't work with my Samyang 8mm. A more effective idea could be to connect a small monitor by means of the live HDMI output of the camera.
You must use the self-timer, otherwise you'll be part of the shoot. Ten seconds are enough to comfortably work without having to run away from the scene.
The exposure is going to be challenging, because you're framing a very large portion of the sky. Unless you're working early in the morning or late in the afternoon, the sun will be in the frame, because the camera is facing up: beware of flares (the Samyang 8mm is very resistant to flare, but it's not perfect) and burning highlights. I took care of exposure by trial and error, taking some test shots and looking at the histogram. Don't strictly expose for highlights, otherwise the lavender spikes, most of which will be in shadow, will render too dark - bye bye sweet violet colour. Generally speaking, some tweaking with curves will be needed during post-processing. Having some clouds is helpful (and will also make for a more dramatic sky); working with the sun near to the horizon could help a lot with the exposure too - unfortunately my tight time window didn't allow me to try.

At last, a slight variation on the theme is to move off the vertical, tilting the camera a bit.

20110711-0022

The ant's point of view.

Nikon D7000 $shootingData$.

This is a reviewed version of an original post published at Java.Net.

Recently there has been a renewed interest into the Actor programming model. The Actor Model actually comes from the '70s, but as far as I'm aware it has been used only in a very limited subset of industrial projects outside the area of telecoms. Erlang (not by chance developed at Ericsson, a telecom industry), which is a language whose concurrency model is actor oriented, is getting some attention but it's definitely a niche kind of a language. More interesting is the fact that the Scala language developed its own actor-based platform, Akka, which is also available to Java (and, generally speaking, to JVM-based languages). While there might (a-hum) be a lot of hype about Scala and I'm pretty oriented to apply a big low-pass filter on trendy and cool stuff, actors have definitely their place in the world when you're involved with complex concurrency. Once upon a time complex concurrency was a matter only for specific industrial segments (e.g. the previously cited telecom industry), but since things such as multi-cores and "the cloud" are invading our battlefields it's better to get prepared.

BTW, cloud and multi-core apart, I've already seen a lot of production code with scattered synchronized sections that "perhaps shouldn't be there, but the thing works and it's better to let them stay". Note that this argument is the typical smell of lack of testing, but concurrency is such a complex thing to test that even when the customer is a good guy and achieves a very high coverage, often he can't be sure. The risk is to have some unprotected section that sooner or later will lead to some inconsistency or raise an exception, up to the scary possibility that a deadlock occurs. The better way to deal with concurrency is to pick a programming model that avoids problems by costruction, and actors can be a good choice.

I've started doing some coding in the area and while I'm still far from a conclusion it's high time I posted some considerations.

Actors and Akka

So, what are actors about? These are the basic principles:

No shared (mutable) data. Each actor manages its own slice of data and there's nothing shared with others. Thus no need for synchronized.
Lightweight processes. Threads are still good, since they scale well; but, as per the previous point, they must be isolated.
Communicate through Asynchronous Messages. What is traditionally done by invoking a method from an object to another now is done by sending an asynchronous message. The sender is never blocked, and the receiver gets all inbound messages enqueued into a 'mailbox', from which they will be consumed one at a time per each actor instance.
Messages are immutable. This should be inferred by the previous points (otherwise bye bye "no shared mutable data"), but it's a good advice to stress the point.

With actors the contract of a computational entity is no more represented by an interface (that is an enumeration of methods) and behaviour, but by the set of messages that the actor can receive and send, and behaviour. Copying the first example in the Java API for Akka, a simple actor can be:

import akka.actor.UntypedActor;
import akka.event.EventHandler;

public class SampleUntypedActor extends UntypedActor
  {
    public void onReceive (Object message) throws Exception
      {
        if (message instanceof String)
          {
            getContext().replyUnsafe("Hello " + message);
          }
        else
          {
            throw new IllegalArgumentException("Unknown message: " + message);
          }
      }    
  }

Actors, being managed objects (and possibly distributed on a network), can't be directly accessed, but must be handled by references. For instance, to send a message to the previous actor:

import static akka.actor.Actors.*;

final ActorRef myActor = actorOf(SampleUntypedActor.class);
actor.start();
...
actor.tell("world");

Now Akka has a considerable value in being tested and optimized - performance is one of the reasons for which you might want to use actors and it's not easy to achieve and Akka is known to scale to impressive numbers. But while messages can be delivered in different fashions, unfortunately Akka seems not to be supporting publish & subscribe which is my preferred way to go (I've seen references to extensions and possibly this feature could be introduced in future). This is a first showstopper for me. Furthermore, basic concepts are simple but, as it unfortunately often occurs, things get more complicated as you start digging into details. Also, you note the total lack of syntactic sugar, as the incoming message is a vanilla Object and you need a cascade of if (message instanceof ...) to deal with multiple messages. At least, for the things Akka calls untyped actors: there are typed actors too, which can be even defined again by an interface to mimic method calling, that Akka will manipulate through AOP to transform method invocation in message passing. An approach that I don't like, because I think that in a message-passing software the approach must be evident in source code, not masked under something that pretend to be method invocation; furthermore, method invocation semantics are incompatible with publish & subscribe. So, I'd say that with Akka either you have no sugar or you're going to sink into honey.

Anyway, just before publishing this blog post, I've learned that Akka 2.0 is going to have publish & subscribe. Excellent news. In the meantime?

Understanding what I want

In the meantime, I've started sketching some code on my own, to understand how I'd like to use actors. The idea is to learn things and then try to converge to Akka, eventually with a thin layer of syntactic sugar. There's enough work so far that's worth while a blog post, both for my personal need of writing down things and to discuss with others.

Since things must be given a real context I've started thinking of desktop applications, in particular two simple tools that I need: SolidBlue computes the fingerprint of the files contained in a directory (I use it for periodically checking the sanity of my photos and related backups) and blueShades provides a GUI for Argyll, a tool for color management, suited to my needs. Both are being implemented with the NetBeans Platform.

So let's focus on SolidBlue and its main feature. The scenario is:

You select a directory.
The application scans the directory recursively.
For each discovered file, contents are loaded and the MD5 fingerprint is computed.
Each MD5 computed fingerprint is stored into a flat file.
A UI monitors the workflow displaying the current status on the screen.

The flow can be parallelised. For instance, directory recursive inspection can be performed by multiple threads, as well as the MD5 computation, which only involves the CPU. On the other hand, loading from the disk is something that it's better to serialize (that is, reading only one file at a time) in order to maximize the disk throughput (which it's the true bottleneck of the application). Indeed, things are a bit more complex than I've just said, but I'll be back on the issue later.

20120104/SolidBlue-Actors.png

Actors in SolidBlue

Note: in the following code samples, I'm making use of Lombok annotations for some plumbing. This is not only great for everyday's work, but it also makes code samples much easier to read. Also, I'm only listing significant import statements, as well as skipping some non relevant code chunks.

Everything starts by sending to the system a message asking for a scan:

FileScanRequestMessage.forFolder("/Volume/Media/Photos")
                      .withFilter(withExtensions("NEF", "JPG", "TIF"))
                      .send();

As you can see, there's no target actor, but according to the "publish and subscribe" approach the message just sends itself. The listing for FileScanRequestMessage is below:

package it.tidalwave.integritychecker;

import it.tidalwave.actor.MessageSupport;
import it.tidalwave.actor.annotation.Message;

@Message @Immutable @RequiredArgsConstructor(access=PRIVATE) @EqualsAndHashCode @ToString(callSuper=false)
public class FileScanRequestMessage extends MessageSupport
  {
    public static interface Filter
      {       
        public boolean accepts (@Nonnull FileObject fileObject); 
      }

    @Nonnull @Getter
    private final FileObject folder; 

    @Nonnull @Getter
    private final Filter filter; 

    @Nonnull
    public static FileScanRequestMessage forFolder (final @Nonnull FileObject fileObject)
      {
        return new FileScanRequestMessage(fileObject, Filter.ANY);
      }   

    @Nonnull
    public FileScanRequestMessage withFilter (final @Nonnull Filter filter)
      { 
        return new FileScanRequestMessage(folder, filter); 
      }
  }

Somewhere there's a FileObjectDiscoveryActor that listens to that message:

package it.tidalwave.integritychecker.impl;

import it.tidalwave.actor.annotation.Actor;
import it.tidalwave.actor.annotation.ListensTo;

@Actor @ThreadSafe
public class FileObjectDiscoveryActor
  {
    public void onScanRequested (final @ListensTo FileScanRequestMessage message)
      {
        for (final FileObject child : message.getFolder().getChildren())
          {
            if (message.getFilter().accepts(child))
              {
                (child.isFolder() ? FileScanRequestMessage.forFile(child).withFilter(message.getFilter())
                                  : FileDiscoveredMessage.forFile(child)).send();
              }
          }
      }
  }

You can see here my syntactic sugar: the actor is a POJO and methods designated to receive messages are annotated by @ListensTo. Multiple methods can listen to multiple messages. The annotation is similar to @Observes by CDI (JSR-299) - actually I'd love to reuse it, but it seems to have different semantics (e.g. by default it can activate managed objects that are the target of an inbound message; furthermore there are multiple delivery options related to transactionality that at the moment I'm not interested into).

Recursive directory navigation is implemented by sending another FileScanRequestMessage. When a regular file is detected, a FileDiscoveredMessage is fired (there's no need to see its listing, as it's straightforward).

Inbound messages are first enqueued and then dispatched in a FIFO fashion (with exceptions explained later). If the actor is not thread safe, there's the guarantee that it can be engaged by a single thread at any time (thus, messages are processed one per time). In this way there's no need to have synchronized sections. If the actor is thread safe (the default), as FileDiscoveredMessage that's even stateless, it can be engaged by multiple threads at the same time. The thread safety property is specified as an attribute of @Actor (unfortunately @ThreadSafe can't help since its retention is compile time).

The second actor is the one that reads data from files:

package it.tidalwave.integritychecker.impl;

import it.tidalwave.actor.annotation.Actor;
import it.tidalwave.actor.annotation.ListensTo;

@Actor(initialPriority=Thread.MAX_PRIORITY) @ThreadSafe
public class FileLoaderActor
  {
    public void onFileDiscovered (final @ListensTo FileDiscoveredMessage message)
      {
        final FileObject fileObject = message.getFileObject();

        try
          {
            final File file = FileUtil.toFile(fileObject);
            final @Cleanup RandomAccessFile randomAccessFile = new RandomAccessFile(file, "r");
            final MappedByteBuffer byteBuffer = randomAccessFile.getChannel().map(READ_ONLY, 0, file.length()); 
            byteBuffer.load();
            randomAccessFile.close();
            new FileContentsAvailableMessage(fileObject, byteBuffer).send();
          }
        catch (Exception e)
          {
            FileDamageDetectedMessage.forFile(fileObject).withCause(e).send();
          }
      }
  }	

It uses memory-mapped I/O for speed and fires a FileContentsAvailableMessage carrying the bytes, or a FileDamageDetectedMessage in case of error.

The next stage is the actor that computes the fingerprint:

package it.tidalwave.integritychecker.impl;

import it.tidalwave.actor.annotation.Actor;
import it.tidalwave.actor.annotation.ListensTo;

@Actor @ThreadSafe
public class FingerprintComputerActor
  {
    public void onFileContentsAvailable (final @ListensTo FileContentsAvailableMessage message)
      throws NoSuchAlgorithmException
      {
        final String algorithm = "MD5";
        final MessageDigest digestComputer = MessageDigest.getInstance(algorithm);
        digestComputer.update(message.getContents());
        final Fingerprint fingerprint = new Fingerprint(algorithm, toString(digestComputer.digest()));
        FingerprintComputedMessage.forFile(message.getFileObject()).withFingerprint(fingerprint).send();
      }
  }

Again, a FingerprintComputedMessage message carrying the result is fired. The last stage is the persistence actor:

package it.tidalwave.integritychecker.impl;

import it.tidalwave.actor.CollaborationStartedMessage;
import it.tidalwave.actor.MessageSupport;
import it.tidalwave.actor.annotation.Actor;
import it.tidalwave.actor.annotation.ListensTo;
import it.tidalwave.actor.annotation.Message;
import it.tidalwave.actor.annotation.OriginatedBy;

@Actor(threadSafe=false) @NotThreadSafe
public class PersistenceManagerActor
  {
    @Message(outOfBand=true) @ToString

    static class FlushRequestMessage extends MessageSupport
      {
      }

    private final Map<String, Object> map = new TreeMap<String, Object>();

    private File persistenceFile;

    private boolean flushPending;

    public void onScanStarted (final @ListensTo CollaborationStartedMessage cMessage,
                               final @OriginatedBy FileScanRequestMessage message)
      {
        final File folder = FileUtil.toFile(message.getFolder());               
        final String fileName = new SimpleDateFormat("'fingerprints-'yyyyMMdd_HHmm'.txt'").format(new Date());
        persistenceFile = new File(folder, fileName);
        map.clear();
      }

    public void onFileDiscovered (final @ListensTo FileDiscoveredMessage message)
      {
        final String name = message.getFileObject().getNameExt();

        if (!map.containsKey(name)) // message sequentiality is not guaranteed
          {
            map.put(name, "unavailable"); 
            requestFlush();
          }
      }

    public void onFingerprintComputed (final @ListensTo FingerprintComputedMessage message)
      {
        final String name = message.getFileObject().getNameExt();
        final Fingerprint fingerprint = message.getFingerprint();
        map.put(name, fingerprint);
        requestFlush();
      }

    private void onFlushRequested (final @ListensTo FlushRequestMessage message)
      throws InterruptedException, IOException
      {
        flushPending = false;
        // writes data to file
     }

    private void requestFlush()
      {
        if (!flushPending)
          {
            new FlushRequestMessage().sendLater(5, TimeUnit.SECONDS);
            flushPending = true;
          }
      }
  }

The basic idea is not to write to disk every piece of data as it's generated, since it might be expensive (well, perhaps writing to a relational database wouldn't be, but for a simple tool such as SolidBlue it makes more sense to write to a flat file). So, data are first put into an in-memory map (a record is generated as soon as a file has been discovered and later overwritten with the final result) that is periodically flushed to disk. So, the actor is stateful, hence it's not thread safe (there must be only one instance). Whenever the map is changed, it's marked 'dirty' and a request to flush it to the disk is generated. The flush will happen within 5 seconds, but it's not a good idea to use a Java Timer as I'd run into the threading problems that I want to avoid. Instead, a private FlushRequestMessage is sent back to itself with some delay, triggering the write to the disk. This message is annotated as 'out-of-band', it means that must delivered with high priority (in practice, it's placed at the head of the incoming message queue rather than the tail). Since the runtime guarantees that only a single message can be processed by any actor instance at any time, there's no need to protect the map, or the  flushPending flag, by synchronized sections.

The onScanStarted() method is interesting, because it introduces the concept of collaborations.

Collaborations

Actually, asynchronicity is excellent for massively concurrent system (as well as, not to say, to model things that are asynchronous in nature, and there are many). But it's nice to know, in some way, that a sequence of things that happened in response to a message of yours has been completed. In my code I've called this concept “Collaboration”:

Any message is always part of a Collaboration.
If the thread creating a certain message is not bound to a Collaboration, a new Collaboration is created and the message will be considered its originator.
The originator message will be delivered in threads bound to its Collaboration. This means that any further message, created as a consequence of the reception of the originator message, will share its Collaboration.
A Collaboration keeps tracks of all the related messages and threads by means of reference counting.
When there are no more pending messages or working threads for a Collaboration, it is considered completed.

Two special messages, CollaborationStartedMessage and CollaborationTerminatedMessage, are fired by the runtime to notify of the creation and completion of collaborations.

When a message is sent, you can get its Collaboration object:

final Collaboration collaboration = new MyMessage().send();

and any listening method can get the Collaboration as well:

public void onMyMessage (final @ListensTo MyMessage message)
  {
    final Collaboration collaboration = message.getCollaboration();
    ...
  }

By construction, thus, a Collaboration is attached to all the threads that are directly or indirectly triggered by the originating message. This could be used for managing regular transactions (for instance, attaching a javax.transaction.UserTransaction to the Collaboration). But actors seem to be better dealing with Software Transactional Memory, so I drop this argument for now.

It's even possible to synchronously waiting for a Collaboration to complete:

collaboration.waitForCompletion();

even though I think it's only useful for tests.  More interesting is the case in which a Collaboration includes bidirectional interactions with a user: for instance, making a dialog box to pop up and wait for a selection. In these circumstances, a Collaboration can be suspended (this means it is not considered to be terminated even though there are no pending messages or working threads) and later resumed. More details in a further post.

Collaborations is something that I don't expect to find in platforms such as Akka, since I'm not sure it's feasible to have them working in an efficient way in a distributed context (I mean: maybe yes, maybe not, I haven't studied the problem yet). But they are a nice feature to have if possible and perhaps it's possible to implement it on top of an existing actor platform.

Back to the method onScanStarted(), it is clear now that it listens to the CollaborationStartedMessage messages originated by a FileScanRequestMessage to initialize the storage of the fingerprints, which must be located in the top scanned directory.

In a similar way, the IntegrityCheckerPresentationControllerActor listens to the various messages being delivered, including those notifying the beginning and the end of the Collaboration, to update the user interface:

package it.tidalwave.integritychecker.ui.impl;

import it.tidalwave.actor.MessageSupport;
import it.tidalwave.actor.Collaboration;
import it.tidalwave.actor.CollaborationCompletedMessage;
import it.tidalwave.actor.CollaborationStartedMessage;
import it.tidalwave.actor.annotation.Actor;
import it.tidalwave.actor.annotation.ListensTo;
import it.tidalwave.actor.annotation.Message;
import it.tidalwave.actor.annotation.OriginatedBy;

@Actor(threadSafe=false) @NotThreadSafe
public class IntegrityCheckerPresentationControllerActor
  {
    private static final double K10 = 1000;

    private static final double M10 = 1000000;

    @Message(outOfBand=true, daemon=true) @ToString
    private static class RefreshPresentationMessage extends MessageSupport
      {
      }

    private final IntegrityCheckerPresentationBuilder presentationBuilder = Locator.find(IntegrityCheckerPresentationBuilder.class);

    private final IntegrityCheckerPresentation presentation = presentationBuilder.createPresentation();

    private final Statistics statistics = new Statistics();

    private boolean refreshing = false;

    private int totalFileCount;

    private long totalDataSize;

    private int processedFileCount;

    private long processedDataSize;

    public void onScanStarted (final @ListensTo CollaborationStartedMessage cMessage,
                               final @OriginatedBy FileScanRequestMessage message)
      {
        totalFileCount = 0;
        totalDataSize = 0;
        processedFileCount = 0;
        processedDataSize = 0;
        refreshing = true;
        new RefreshPresentationMessage().send();
      }

    public void onScanCompleted (final @ListensTo CollaborationCompletedMessage cMessage,
                                 final @OriginatedBy FileScanRequestMessage message)
      {
        refreshing = false;
        presentation.setProgressLabel("done");
        new RefreshPresentationMessage().send();
      }

    public void onFileDiscovered (final @ListensTo FileDiscoveredMessage message)
      {
        totalFileCount++;
        totalDataSize += message.getFileObject().getSize();
      }

    public void onFingerprintComputed (final @ListensTo FingerprintComputedMessage message)
      {
        processedFileCount++;
        processedDataSize += message.getFileObject().getSize();
        final Collaboration collaboration = message.getCollaboration();
        final long elapsedTime = collaboration.getDuration().getMillis();
        final double speed = (processedDataSize / M10) / (elapsedTime / K10);
        final int eta = (int)(((totalDataSize - processedDataSize) / M10) / speed);
        ... // and update the statistics object
      }

    private void updatePresentation (final @ListensTo RefreshPresentationMessage message)
      {
        presentation.updateStatistics(statistics);

        if (refreshing)
          {
            new RefreshPresentationMessage().sendLater(1, TimeUnit.SECONDS);
          }
      }
  }

Actually another advantage of message-based designs is that a user interface can be easily updated without having to know a large number of listeners.

Activation

Actors are managed objects and must be never directly accessed. To accomplish this, they are declared by means of activators, which typically are grouped together such as in:

package it.tidalwave.integritychecker.impl;

import org.openide.util.lookup.ServiceProvider;
import it.tidalwave.actor.spi.ActorGroupActivator;
import static it.tidalwave.actor.spi.ActorActivator.*;

@ServiceProvider(service=IntegrityCheckerActivator.class)
public class IntegrityCheckerActivator extends ActorGroupActivator
  {
    public IntegrityCheckerActivator()
      {
        add(activatorFor(FileObjectDiscoveryActor.class).withPoolSize(8));
        add(activatorFor(FileLoaderActor.class).withPoolSize(1));
        add(activatorFor(FingerprintComputerActor.class).withPoolSize(4));
        add(activatorFor(PersistenceManagerActor.class).withPoolSize(1));
      }
  }

Activators specify the pool size of each actor. Given that, it's possible to activate and deactivate the group:

Locator.find(IntegrityCheckerActivator.class).activate();
...
Locator.find(IntegrityCheckerActivator.class).deactivate();

For people not used to the NetBeans Platform, @ServiceProvider is a compile-time annotations that generates a service declaration into META-INF/services, while Locator is a facility that retrieves the reference at runtime.

Actors can have methods annotated with @PostConstruct and @PreDestroy, which will be called just before activation and just after deactivation, of course in a thread-safe way. There's the guarantee that messages can't be delivered before activation is completed and after deactivation.

Simpler than Akka... for how long?

This works, I enjoy the fact that I can avoid synchronized blocks and so far I don't miss the fact that that thing is clearly much less performant than Akka. Everything fits into less than 40k of jar file and it's much simpler than Akka (whose complexity is justified by the fact that it offers many more features). So what? Distributing to a network is something that we can't ignore in a cloud oriented world. So it's likely that going on I'll see the need for more features: often you discover that you need new features as you go on. Smell of reinventing the wheel ahead!

For instance, consider the FileLoadActor. I've previously said that experimental evidence demonstrates that it makes sense (at least with large files) to have it instantiated in a single instance, thus serializing data access to the disk. This makes sense given the physical nature of a magnetic disk. But this happens with a single disk: if you have more than one, it probably makes sense to have one instance per disk. Having a Solid State Drive (SSD) changes the rules. This means that you must have some more complex way to dispatch messages, a form of routing. Akka offers it, and it would be unwise to rewrite this feature from scratch.

So now I'm going to start phase two, that is to reimplement this stuff upon Akka (using the 2.0 milestone that's already available). In a few weeks I'll let you know how the story goes on.

The code that I described in this blog post are available at the Mercurial repository http://bitbucket.org/tidalwave/solidblue-src, tag 1.0-ALPHA-4.

In a further post I'll talk about how Collaborations are used by blueShades, which features more complex interactions with the user. See you later.

Niviok 1.0 Specification

Edition 1 Draft 2008-07-20

Copyright © 2008 James Justin Harrell

Permission is granted to use, copy, display, modify, sell, and distribute this document. This document is provided "as is" without warranty of any kind. In no event shall anyone be liable for any damages or other liability arising from use of this document.

1. Overview
2. Versioning

2.1. Niviok version
2.2. Specification version
2.3. Version notation

3. Glossary
4. Executing nodes
5. Overview part 2

5.1. Identifiers
5.2. Scidentres
5.3. Built-in numbers

6. Values
7. Functions

7.1. Function interfaces

8. Interfaces

8.1. Adding and subtracting interfaces

9. Scopes
10. Handling declare-first nodes
11. Nodes

11.1. Node terminology
11.2. Tree node layout
11.3. Node supertypes

12. Node types

12.1. Terminal nodes
12.2. Family node types

12.2.1. expression
12.2.2. statement-declaration
12.2.3. interface-member

12.3. Tree node layout key
12.4. Non-executable

12.4.1. argument
12.4.2. boolean
12.4.3. direction
12.4.4. import
12.4.5. import-attempt
12.4.6. member-implementation
12.4.7. member-type
12.4.8. parameter-impl
12.4.9. parameter-info
12.4.10. worker

12.5. Statements

12.5.1. declare-first
12.5.2. hidable
12.5.3. module
12.5.4. sieve

12.6. Non-producing expressions

12.6.1. declare-empty
12.6.2. raise

12.7. Sometimes producing expressions

12.7.1. assign
12.7.2. call
12.7.3. compound
12.7.4. conditional
12.7.5. curry
12.7.6. declare-assign
12.7.7. identifier
12.7.8. select

12.7.8.1. case

12.7.9. set-property
12.7.10. try-catch

12.7.10.1. catcher

12.7.11. type-select

12.7.11.1. type-case

12.8. Always producing expressions

12.8.1. Boolean logic

12.8.1.1. and
12.8.1.2. nand
12.8.1.3. or
12.8.1.4. nor
12.8.1.5. xor
12.8.1.6. xnor

12.8.2. breed
12.8.3. caller
12.8.4. object
12.8.5. dictionary

12.8.5.1. dictionary-entry

12.8.6. enum

12.8.6.1. enum-entry

12.8.7. extract-member
12.8.8. function
12.8.9. function-interface
12.8.10. generator
12.8.11. generic-function
12.8.12. generic-interface
12.8.13. instantiate-generic
12.8.14. integer
12.8.15. interface

12.8.15.1. statused-member
12.8.15.2. member-status
12.8.15.3. breeder
12.8.15.4. callee
12.8.15.5. method
12.8.15.6. property

12.8.16. rational
12.8.17. string

13. Reserved identikey names
14. Standard library

14.1. println
14.2. activeInterface
14.3. String
14.4. func{I}(dyn)I cast
14.5. ceil
14.6. floor
14.7. modulo
14.8. round
14.9. interface generator
14.10. func id
14.11. func sameObject?
14.12. func(obj, interface)bool implements?
14.13. interface Int
14.14. interface BigInt
14.15. interface BigRat
14.16. interface Interface
14.17. interface Object
14.18. interface rat
14.19. Generator
14.20. InterfaceBuilder
14.21. Iterator
14.22. CInterfaceBuilder
14.23. getFuncInterface

15. Warnings
16. Error handling during processing
17. Rationales

17.1. Dynamic static typing
17.2. Terms

17.2.1. get/set

17.3. Executing boolean logic nodes
17.4. Disallowing executing declaration-first

18. Unsorted/outdated stuff

18.1. Closures
18.2. Tree examples

18.2.1. Example 1
18.2.2. Example 2
18.2.3. Example 3

18.3. get interface
18.4. obj interface
18.5. Binding to identifiers
18.6. Return interfaces of print and println
18.7. Adjuncts
18.8. runtime interface implementation
18.9. Runtime interface creation
18.10. "self" return type
18.11. Bind
18.12. Classes
18.13. Noninstantiated interface templates
18.14. Dynamic library loading
18.15. Static typing

Chapter 1. Overview

This document is a draft for the first edition of the specification describing the 1.0 version of Niviok. It can be represented as "Niviok 1.0 Edition 1 Draft 2008-07-20".

This document is a draft of the first edition of the specification describing the 1.0 version of Niviok.

Niviok is an abstract programming language. This document defines several node types which are used to represent Niviok source code. How Niviok nodes are represented is outside the scope of this standard. While syntax and semantics are not completetly separate, Niviok does contain much less syntax-influenced semantics than most programming languages.

Nodes that can be executed are statements or expressions. Statements are greatly restricted in where they can appear, while expressions are more relaxed and can be interchanged for on another. An expression may produce a value when executed.

Niviok contains some dynamic aspects, but in several ways is very static. For example, the tree of scopes and scidentres can be entirely known before runtime; scidentres cannot be declared conditionally like in highly dynamic languages such as JavaScript.

Chapter 2. Versioning

Each version of Niviok is described by a specification with one or more editions.

2.1. Niviok version

Each version of Niviok is identified by a major version number and a minor version number, both integers. Each new version that is mostly backwards compatible with the previous version increments the minor version number by one. Each new version that is significantly backwards incompatible increments the major version number by one and resets the minor version number to 0.

2.2. Specification version

Each version of Niviok is described by a specification that can have multiple editions. Each edition of a specification describing a particular version of Niviok is identified by an integer which starts at one and is incremented by one for each new edition.

A document that is intended to become an edition is a draft. A finalized edition is no longer in the draft stage. Each draft is identified by the date on which it was published.

Newer editions should serve only to better describe a particular version of Niviok, not to modify that version of Niviok. Newer editions should not attempt to correct problems with Niviok, only errors in describing that version of Niviok.

2.3. Version notation

A version of Niviok may be represented as "Niviok X.Y" where X is the major version number and Y is the minor version number.

A finalized specification for Niviok may be represented as "Niviok X.Y Edition A" where A is the edition number.

A draft of a specification edition may be represented as "Niviok X.Y Edition A Draft YYYY-MM-DD" where YYYY-MM-DD is the date on which the draft was published.

Example: Niviok 2.3 Edition 4 Draft 2008-01-20

Chapter 3. Glossary

Niviok agent
agent
An implementation of the Niviok language. Could be a source interpreter, a bytecode intepreter, a bytecode compiler, a machine code compiler, etc. If it recognizes the semantics of what it's running, and follows the rules of this document, it could be called a Niviok agent. Each agent should define what representations it supports.
object
A collection of data that holds state. Created by a class. Only the class that created it can access an object's state. Values are associated with objects.
scidentre
bound to one or more values. An identifier in a certain scope is associated with an identikey. In other programming languages, the terms "variable" or "constant" may refer to a similar concept. (Previously called "identikey" by this draft. Transition has only barely begun.)
value
Associated with an object and an interface implementation, except for the null value, which is associated with nothing or associated with an interface
active interface implementation
the interface implementation a value is directly associated with
active interface
the interface that the active interface implementation is associated with
global scope
the scope of the bundle node. a bundle node has one and only one scope each time the bundle is executed
element
A value stored in a container.
member
A callee, property, method, or conversion of an interface.
method
A member function of an interface.
scope
"Environment" in some languages.

Chapter 4. Executing nodes

No node besides the bundle node can be executed directly. All other nodes must only be executed when required by the execution instructions of another node, or as required to call a callee/method (such as when calling a value created by a function node). ((XXX clarify execution through calling)) Because values can only be created, directly or indirectly, by executing the bundle node, and because all node execution instructions only every instruct to execute child nodes, all node execution occurs as a result of executing the root bundle node. All Niviok nodes that are executed in any way must be part of a complete Niviok node tree, which means having an bundle node as the root node.

Note: A bundle might not have a main function. It might just expose its members, such as for scripting or a library.

interpreted:

a bundle representation is parsed to extract a tree of Niviok nodes
libraries are loaded and linked
tree is processed
optimization
execution of the planes' declaration-first nodes
execution of the function bound to "main" attached to the bundle node's scope, which may return an exit status
returning exit status, or 0 if none specified

runtime compilation:

a bundle representation is parsed to extract a tree of Niviok nodes
libraries are loaded and linked
tree is processed
optimization
tree translated to bytecode and/or machine code
execution of bytecode and/or machine code, which produces an exit status

beforehand compilation:

a bundle representation is parsed to extract a tree of Niviok nodes
static libaries are loaded
information about shared libraries is obtained
tree is processed
optimization
tree translated to bytecode and/or machine code and stored
code is loaded
shared libraries are loaded and linked
processing
execution of bytecode and/or machine code, which produces an exit status

This spec should define how to:

process a bundle (a valid tree of Niviok nodes with a bundle node as the root node)
execute nodes of a processed tree
execute a bundle

Implementations that aren't interpreters should produce equivalent behavior when being executed.

Chapter 5. Overview part 2

Niviok is represented by a node tree. The way this node tree is represented is not covered in this specification. This specification explains what kind of node tree a representation can represent, the meaning of the nodes in a Niviok node tree, and how to execute the node tree.

This node tree has scopes attached at various places. These scopes contain identikeys that are bound to namespaces and values.

5.1. Identifiers

identifier
sequence of words, with an optional ending exclamation mark or question mark
word
sequence of Unicode characters, where each Unicode character is a letter or an Arabic numerical digit
letter
member of an alphabet, abjad, abugida, syllabary, or logogram

Because identifiers are defined in terms of Unicode characters, letters are case sensitive wherever Unicode defines an uppercase and lowercase character for the same letter. Control characters, surrogates, whitespace characters, punctuation marks, and combining characters are not letters. This specification does not specify all characters that do or do not qualify as letters, but it does list some characters that must be recognized a certain way.

Arabic numerical digits: (complete)

0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9

letters: (incomplete)

a b c d e f g h i j k l m n o p q r s t u v w x y z
A B C D E F G H I J K L M N O P Q R S T U V W X Y Z

not letters: (incomplete)

0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 ` ~ ! @ # $ % ^ & * ( ) { } [ ] / ? = + \ | - _ ' " , < > .

Examples of how identifiers might be represented:

do some stuff XML_HTTP_request we\are\finished? mutate`this`thing!

5.2. Scidentres

Need to replace "identikey" with "scidentre".

An identikey is associated with a scope and an identifier. It may be associated with a nullable-type, a worker, multiple workers, and/or a namespace. Some identikeys can be mutated.

Every scope is assocciated with zero or more identikeys. Identikeys associated with the same scope must each be associated with a different identifier.

When an identifier node is executed, every identikey in the scope the identifier node resides in is checked to see if the identikey is associated with an equivalent identifier. If it is, the value produce by executing the identifier node is obtained from the identikey. The identifier node execution process moves up through the scope tree (not to be confused with the scope formula tree) looking for an identikey associated with an equivalent identifier.

namespace
associated with a namespace when created. immutable. multiple declarations of the same scidentre can be made in the same scope.
constant
associated with a worker when created. immutable.
overload
associated with a worker when created. immutable. multiple declarations of the same scidentre can be made in the same scope.
variable
can be mutated to point to different workers. only workers that match the type can be assigned to the identikey (note that the type could be e.g. any or Nullable<any>)

A function identikey can be bound to multiple functions (objects that implement a function interface; xxx link) at the same time. A function identikey can never be bound to multiple functions with the same interface.

If a value has multiple callees, the active interface is not a function interface, and thus it cannot be bound to a function identikey. The value must be cast to each function interface, and each resulting value bound individually to the function identikey.

var foo 123 foo = "bar" foo = getSomething() var Int num num = 2 num = 89 var ?auto bar getSomething() bar = getSomethingWithSameTypeAsBefore() interface Foo func fooMeth() interface Bar func barMeth() var obj getFoo() obj.fooMeth() obj = getBar() obj.barMeth() var foo foo = getBar() foo.barProp foo = 3 foo.minus(5) foo = "test" foo.toUpperCase() foo = CMyClass() foo.myClassProp foo = cast<BazInterface>(alpha) foo.bazProp foo = (alpha as MazInterface) foo.mazProp foo = alpha as GazInterface foo.gazProp (BazInterface foo).bazProp (MazInterface foo).mazProp

5.3. Built-in numbers

The built-in implementations of the Int and Rat interfaces must be able to handle numbers of an arbitrary complexity. Built-in libraries should handle numbers of an arbitrary complexity. Niviok implementations must not ever introduce rounding errors or otherwise introduce numerical errors without being explicitly told that such errors may occur.

For example, pow(10, pow(10,100)), must correctly return an Int object reference that accurately represents a googolplex, and must be able to perform operations on this number with perfect accuracy.

Implementations may throw errors when they are unable to perfectly represent a number. Implementations must not silently introduce errors. This is the only alternative to perfectly representing the number.

For example, if the implementation was directed by user code to print a googolplex without using scientific notation (i.e. a "1" followed by a googol "0"), the implementation may throw an error specifying that it is unable to create such a representation.

Chapter 6. Values

Values are associated with an object and an interface implementation.

Objects hold which is used by the interface implementation. This state can only be accessed or modified by interface implementations that they object was intented to hold state for. Objects have an ID that never changes. Each interface implementation consists of the implementation of the members of that interface.

This specification may speak of values implementing interfaces. In these cases, what is actually refered to is whether the interface implementation the value is associtiated with is in a tree where one of the interface implementations is an implementation of that interface. The value itself does not actually implement any interfaces.

Interface implementations form a tree. Multiple interface implementations in the same tree can implement the same iterface. When a value has an active interface that has multiple implementations, the interface implementation that is used when the value is accessed is the interface implementation that the vaule is associated with.

Chapter 7. Functions

Functions are just values with an active interface that defines callees. Functions can be "called". Functions can have a return interface and parameters. Parameters have an interface and an optional default value.

7.1. Function interfaces

XXX this needs a lot of work

Function interfaces implement FunctionInterface instead of Interface and inherit from Function. FunctionInterface simply inherits from Interface and defines no new members. Function interfaces declare a callee and an "apply" method that hides the members of the Function interface.

interface Function
	callee(dyn[] params) dyn
	func apply(dyn[] arguments) dyn //actually takes an array
	func bind(dyn[] params) dyn
	func call(dyn[] params) dyn
	func curry(dyn[] params) dyn
	get List>Parameter> parameters
	get Bool return?
	get nullable Interface returnInterface

all function interfaces
	inherit Function
	callee(...) ...
	func apply(dyn[] params) ...
	func call(...) ...

For example, for func(Int a, Rat b, String c) Bool :

interface (func(Int a, Rat b, String c) Bool)
	inherit Function
	callee(Int a, Rat b, String C) Bool
	func apply(dyn[] params) Bool
	func call(Int a, Rat b, String C) Bool
	get parameters returns List {
		Parameter { "a", Int },
		Parameter { "b", Rat },
		Parameter { "c", String } }
	get return? returns true
	get returnInterface returns Bool

Chapter 8. Interfaces

Interfaces define a means of interacting with an object's state. Interfaces declare that implementations will be able to provide object references with specified interfaces when asked for the object reference bound to identifiers specified by the interface and/or that implementations will be able to bind object references with specified interfaces to specified identifiers. Methods are a type of property. Methods are callable and cannot be assigned, only retrieved.

Interfaces cannot inherit in a circle. (E.g., interface A cannot inherit interface B if interface B inherits interface A.) Interfaces cannot inherit from themselves. (However, interfaces created by instantiating values created from generic-interface nodes should not throw errors if the interface tries to inherit itself. Instead, the error should be silently ignored. This is to allow generic interfaces to inherit other forms of themselves.) Interfaces that do not explicitly inherit any interfaces, should implicitly inherit Object. Therefore, all interfaces inherit from Object, either directly or indirectly.

Interfaces can declare that properties are "get only", "set only", or "get and set".

Interface member functions can have default values. This differs from a class with abstract members because interfaces cannot have any private members, so these default functions can not store or extract state in the object. These functions are only intended to call other member functions or throw errors.

There are two kinds of interfaces: object interfaces (Interface) and function interfaces (FuncInterface). Object interfaces define properties and methods. Function interfaces define parameters and a return type. An interface cannot be a function interface and an object interface, though an object interface can have call methods that allow implementations to be used like functions. A function interface can be wrapped to an object interface with a single call method.

Interface callees and members may refer to the interface. This is useful when an interface wants to define a method that returns an object reference with itself as the active interface. For generic interfaces, it is also possible to refer to the generic template.

interface Int func power(Self) Self r Self timesTwo //some representations may be able to translate the below example as well iterface Int func power(Int) Int r Int timesTwo //note that the interface node will have no knowledge of the identifier it is being bound to //generics: interface<T> Print callee(T) Self Print<Int> print = getIntPrinter() print(3)(5)(8) //the print callee returns a Print<Int> object reference //refering to Generic interface interface<T> Print callee(T) GenericSelf Print print = getGenericPrinter() print <Int>(3) <String>("foo") <Rat>(1.23) //some representations may also allow: print 3 "foo" 1.23

8.1. Adding and subtracting interfaces

Interfaces can be added together to produce other interfaces. How this addition occurs depends on whether the operands were produce through addition, and the inherited interfaces of the operands.

If an interface is "fromAddition", it was produced through addition and/or subtract. The Interface interface exposes this information as a property.

Interfaces produced from addition don't define any members themeselves; they only inherit from other interfaces.

No interface can inherit from an interface that is fromAddition. When a fromAddition interface is an operand of interface addition, the inheritees of the fromAddition interface are copied into the produced interface, but the produced interface does not inherit from the fromAddition operands.

No interface that is fromAddition can inherit from a single interface. When subtracting from a fromAddition interface, and the produced interface would have otherwise only inherited from a single interface, the produced interface is actually that single interface that it would have inherited from.

interface A
	fromAddition = false

interface B
	fromAddition = false

interface C
	fromAddition = true

interface D
	fromAddition = true

interface A+B
	inherit A
	inherit B

interface A+C
	inherit A
	C's inheritees (doesn't inherit from C)

interface A+D
	inherit A
	D's inheritees (doesn't inherit from D)

interface B+C
	inherit B
	C's inheritees (doesn't inherit from C)

interface B+D
	inherit B
	D's inheritees (doesn't inherit from D)

interface C+D
	C's inheritees (doesn't inherit from C)
	D's inheritees (doesn't inherit from D)

(A+B)-B must be A, not a fromAddition interface that inherits only from A.

consider this expression:
	(A+B+C)-(B+C)
if:
	* C is fromAddition
	* A and B are not fromAddition
	* C inherits from C1, C2, and C3
then the expresison is equal to:
	(A+B+C1+C2+C3)-(B+C1+C2+C3)
	(A+B+C1+C2+C3)-B-C1-C2-C3
	A

xxx ENSURE ORDER DOESN'T MATTER

Addition with operands A and B:

Create an interface, PRODUCT, where fromAddition is true.
If A is fromAddition, copy the inheritees of A to PRODUCT. If A is not fromAddition, add A as an inheritee to PRODUCT.
If B is fromAddition, copy the inheritees of B to PRODUCT. If B is not fromAddition, add B as an inheritee to PRODUCT.
If PRODUCT has only one inheritee, produce that inheritee. Otherwise, produce PRODUCT.

Note: An example of when PRODUCT would only have one inheritee from addition is when an interface that is not fromAddition is added to itself. i.e. A + A = A

Subtraction with operands A and B:

If A is not fromAddition, throw an error.
Copy A as PRODUCT. (i.e. Copy A. We'll refer to this copy as PRODUCT.)
If B is fromAddition, remove every inheritee of B from the inheritees of PRODUCT. If any of the inheritees of B is not an inheritee of PRODUCT, throw an error.
If B is not fromAddition, remove B from the inheritees of PRODUCT. If B is an inheritee of PRODUCT, throw an error.
If PRODUCT has only one inheritee, produce that inheritee. If PRODUCT does not have any inheritees, throw an error. Otherwise, produce PRODUCT.

Chapter 9. Scopes

Scopes consist of a collection of identikeys, and unless it is the scope of the bundle node, an association with a parent scope. Scopes form a hierarchy. When identifier nodes are executed, the current scope is searched for an identikey that is associated with that identifier. If one is not found, that scope's parent scope is searched, and so on, until a matching identikey is found. If such an identikey cannot be found, an error results.

When execution enters a node that "has scope", before executing that node, all contained declare-first descendant nodes that do not have a closer "with scope" ancestor node, are handled according to this section.

Chapter 10. Handling declare-first nodes

Rename this section to something like "entering node that has scope" or "creating new scope"?

This section specifies the actions that must take place when execution first reaches a node that "has scope".

Let scopeNode be the node that "has scope" that execution just reached, i.e., the node that lead to this process being performed.
Let nodeList be an ordered list of all declare-first nodes that:

are descendants of scopeNode, and
do not have an ancestor node that:

"has scope" or "has closure", and
is a descendant of scopeNode

Let listCount be the number of elements in nodeList.
Let thisScope be a new scope.
Add the identikeys specified by the nodes in nodeList to thisScope.
Let currentNode be the first node in nodeList. If nodeList is empty, end this process and begin execution of scopeNode with thisScope as the associated scope.
Begin executing the [value] member of currentNode.

If execution needs to evaluate an identikey created by this process, and the [value] member of the declare-first node associated with that identikey has not yet been evaluated and the product assigned to that identikey, pause the execution of this [value] member.
If execution completes successfully, assign the product to the associated identikey, and remove currentNode from nodeList.

Set currentNode to the next node in nodeList and go to step 6. (If currentNode was removed, the next node would be the node that followed currentNode when currentNode was in the list.) If there is no next node, continue to the next step.
If the number of elements in nodeList is equal to listCount, a cyclical dependency likely exists, where two or more expressions rely on the result of each other to execute. In this case, throw an error. If the number of elements in nodeList is not equal to listCount, set listCount to the number of elements in nodeList and go to step 5.

Example 1 of a cyclical dependency:

declfirst a = b + 2
declfirst b = a + 3

Example 2 of a cyclical dependency:

declfirst a = b + 2
declfirst b = c + 3
declfirst c = d + 4
declfirst d = e + 5
declfirst e = a + 6

Example 1 of a non-cyclical dependency:

declfirst a = b + 2
declfirst b = c + 3
declfirst c = d + 4
declfirst d = e + 5
declfirst e = 6

Example 2 of a non-cyclical dependency:

declfirst func foo = func() {
	bar()
}

declfirst func bar = func() {
	foo()
}

Concerning the last example: When one of these functions is called, infinite recursion occurs (negating intervention by the agent), but no such cycle is involved in just executing the function nodes. This is because the calls to foo and bar are not executed when the function nodes are executed.

Chapter 11. Nodes

Niviok defines 63 nodes.

Niviok code is represented by a tree of nodes. How this tree and its nodes are represented is outside the scope of this specification. Many means may exist of representing a Niviok tree.

Nodes are either base nodes or tree nodes. Tree nodes only contain other nodes, and their entire meaning is derived from their child nodes. Base nodes do not contain any other child nodes, and must is some way encode their meaning themselves.

When a node has multiple child nodes with equivalent meaning, the order of those child nodes is significant, so their order must be specified by some means. The order of nodes of different meaning in relation to each other is not significant, and must not have any observable side effects.

The child nodes of tree nodes are sometimes executed in order, such as expressions in blocks and arguments in function calls. This means the order of the child nodes is sometimes significant and thus should always be preserved.

How ordering is represented has no effect on the semantics (left-to-right, numbered, linked list, etc) as long as there is a specified order. Each representation should specify how nodes are ordered.

Node type names are nouns or noun phrases. XXX find correct English terminology

11.1. Node terminology

If a node can contain other nodes, it is a tree node. If a node is contained directly inside another node, the inner node is the child of the outer node, and the outer node is the parent of the inner node. If a node is contained inside another node, but not directly, the inner node is the descendant of the outer node, and the outer node is the ancestor of the inner node.

Expressions can be executed. When executed, they may perform some kind of action; e.g. they can have side effects. Expressions may produce a value when executed.

11.2. Tree node layout

The number, type, and order of a tree nodes children is determined by the tree node's layout.

11.3. Node supertypes

Where the layout for a tree node specifies that a child node is an expression, that child node can be any expression.

Chapter 12. Node types

This chapter describes the various types of nodes. A node type is either a family, tree, or terminal node type. A family node type is a collection of node types. A tree node is a node that is composed of other nodes. Tree nodes do not directly encode any data themselves. The nodes a tree node type contains is specified by the tree node's layout. When the a layout specifies the type of a child node is that of a family node type, the type of the child that takes that place must be in the collection of that family node type. A terminal node encodes data directly and does not contain other nodes.

12.1. Terminal nodes

These node types do not contain child nodes, and are thus the only nodes that must encode information themselves (as opposed to containing child nodes which together provide information).

boolean
direction
identifier
integer
member-status
member-type
rational
string

12.2. Family node types

12.2.1. expression

Any node type specified directly in one the following listed sections is an expression node. (Excludes node types specified in the sections of other node types.) Expression nodes can be executed, and may produce values.

Non-producing Expressions
Sometimes producing expressions
Always producing expressions

12.2.2. statement-declaration

Declares new local identikeys and assigns new stuff to them.

This family node type includes these types:

declare-first
sieve

12.2.3. interface-member

This family node type includes these types:

breeder
callee
property
method

12.3. Tree node layout key

This section describes how the layout of a node type is represented in this specification.

The layout for a node type is represented in this specification as a list of items. Each item represents a child node, or multiple child nodes with the same meaning.

Each item in these lists first specifies how many child nodes with that meaning may appear, or it says nothing about the number, which means there must be one (and no more). The ways of representing these amounts is described below.

?
0 or 1
*
0 or more
+
1 or more

Next comes the name of a node type. The child node represented by that list item must be of that type.

Lastly comes a optional label for refering to the child nodes represented by that item, when the type alone isn't enough to disambiguate which item is being referred to. These labels carry no semantic information, and are merely used by this specification to refer to specific child nodes. (Note this label is always singular, even for collections.)

Example layout:

alpha
? beta gamma
? beta delta
* epsilon
+ expression zeta

The first item represents a single required child node of type "alpha". The second item represents an optional child node of type "beta", which can be referred to using the label "gamma". The third item represents an optional child node of type "beta", which can be referred to using the label "delta". The fourth item refers to a collection of child nodes of type "epsilon"; the collection can be empty. The fifth item refers to a collection of expression child nodes; the collection must contain at least one node; nodes in this collection can be refered to using the label "zeta".

12.4. Non-executable

Nodes that cannot be executed. Most serve only to group other nodes together.

12.4.1. argument

? identifier parameter name
? expression value

func doSomething(Int a = 1, Int b = 2, Int c = 3, Int d) {...} doSomething(7, default, default, 8) doSomething(7, c = default, 8)

12.4.2. boolean

Terminal node. Specifies one of:

true
false

Cannot be evaluated because that would conflict with the "true" and "false" members of the Bool enum. Boolean values in the node tree use a boolean node, and boolean values in code use the "true" and "false" identikeys.

12.4.3. direction

Specifies the direction of a function parameter.

Terminal node. Specifies one of:

in
out
inout

At one time also included "in-mutable" and "in-mutable-out". The nun-mutable version would create copies. It is not clear whether these should be kept. Parameter direction is currently ignored.

A value passed to a function as an "in" parameter will not be mutated by the function. This means if the function uses the value in ways that may mutate the value, the value will be copied. If an action in the function may mutate the value, and the value does not declare a copy converter, an error results.

Instances where the value may be mutated include when the interface of the value does not provide opacity information and the function calls a method, or if the interface does provide opacity information but the function calls a mutator method, or if the value is passed to another function as an in-mutable or in-mutable-out parameter.

func alpha(in Int num) { println num } func beta(in-mutable Int num) { num += 567 } func gamma(out Int num) { //num not currently assigned to anything num = 987 } func delta(in-out Int num) { println num num = 1001 } func epsilon(in-mutable-out Int num) { num += 55555 num = 19591 } Int num = 123 alpha(num) beta(num) //value mutated gamma(num) //num assigned to different value delta(num) //num assigned to different value epsilon(num) //value mutated and num assigned to different value

12.4.4. import

Binds a library to a namespace identikey.

identifier alias
+ import-attempt

Each import-attempt node attempts to refer to a library. The agent should try each import-attempt node in order until it is able to find one with a scheme that it recognizes and leads to a library the agent is able to load. If the agent is not able to load a library after trying all import-attempt nodes, it must output an error message and end execution immediately.

import Xml "name" : "XmlLib" "UUID" : "9d0d5fdc-5a23-4375-892a-8cbfd80f0927" "local absolute path" : "/usr/bin/xmllib/niviok/xmllib.niviok.so" "local absolute path" : "C:\Program Files\XmlLib\bin\Niviok\xmllib.niviok.so" "local relative path" : "bin/xmllib.niviok.so" "URL" : "https://www.xmllib.org/repository/xmllib.niviok.so" def doc = Xml:Document() doc.appendChild(doc.createElement("foo")) def Xml:Element root = doc.documentElement

Note that this specification does not define any schemes. Which schemes are supported by an agent is agent-specific.

Need versioning information. Could just include versioning information in the body of each import-attempt, but then the version information would have to be repeated for every import-attempt. Even if going with that, example should be updated to inclue versioning information. But what if different schemes wanted to denote versioning information in different ways? For example, shared libraries on Unix have their own versioning system, with version numbers different from the public version number associated with a piece of software.

12.4.5. import-attempt

string scheme
string body

Used by the import node.

12.4.6. member-implementation

member-type
? identifier name
? expression interface
expression function

12.4.7. member-type

Terminal node. Specifies one of:

breeder
callee
getter
setter
method

12.4.8. parameter-impl

direction
expression type
identifier name
? expression default value

When a [default value] is given, [default value] is executed for every call to the function. It is not executed when the function node is executed.

12.4.9. parameter-info

direction
expression type
identifier name
boolean has default value

12.4.10. worker

expression face
* worker child worker
* member-implementation

Note: May actually correspond to multiple workers, since some of the member-implementation nodes may implement members of inherited interfaces.

12.5. Statements

Statements can be executed. Statements do not produce when executed. Statements differ from non-producing expressions in that statements have special execution rules that greatly restrict where they can appear.

12.5.1. declare-first

identifier name
boolean overload
expression type
boolean breed
expression value

Should [breed] be required to be false if [wo-scidentre-category] is "function"?

Creates an scidentre in the parent scope ash assigns the specified value to it. If [overload] is true, creates on overload scidentre; otherwise creates a constant scidentre.

The value expressions of declare-first nodes may depend on the values of other declare-first nodes that appear before or after it. Some types of expressions are allowed to reference the scidentres of each other. For example, two interfaces could reference each other.

For more (xxx outdated) information, see this section.

func b {3} !declfirst !functionworef b = !function(->Int) { 3 } declfirst Foo = interface { get Bar bar get Int number } declfirst Bar = interface { get Foo foo } const Foo foo = getFoo() println( foo.bar.foo.bar.foo.bar.foo.number )

12.5.2. hidable

boolean hidden
statement-declaration declaration

12.5.3. module

A grouping of identikey declarations, for use as a library or a standalone program.

integer niviok major version number
integer niviok minor version number
* import
sieve

No node can contain a module node. Module nodes are the only nodes which can ever be parentless. All nodes that are ever executed in any way must be part of a complete tree, with a module node as the rootmost node.

Following stuff needs to be moved. Also, see "executing module.txt".

Implementations must not pass any arguments to the main function when executing a bundle as a standalone executable. Implementations should instead provide program arguments through a library which can be imported with the import node. Note that the program arguments are not required by this specification to be a sequence of strings.

The result produced by executing a bundle node as a standalone executable may be converted as necesary to suit the containing environment. How this conversion is performed depends on the containing environment and the Desal implementation, and is not covered by this specification.

When treating a bundle as a standalone executable:

Let globalScope be a new scope.
Create the identikeys required by Reserved identikey names.
For each import and expose child node, add the identikeys to globalScope specified by that node.
Execute all declaration-first children of each plane together as required by Handling declare-first nodes.
Let mainKey be the identikey in globalScope that is associated with identifier "main". If such an identikey does not exist, throw an error.
Let mainVal be the result of evaluating mainKey. If mainVal is null, throw an error.
Call mainVal with no arguments and let rv be the result. If mainVal is not callable, throw an error. If mainVal does not have a callee that takes no arguments, throw an error.
If rv is null, produce a value, with Int as the active interface, that encodes the number zero. Else if rv has an active interface that inherits from Int, downcast rv to Int and produce the result. Else if rv, with it's current active interface, can breed an Int, have rv breed an Int, and produce the result. Else throw an error.

When treating a bundle as a library:

Let globalScope be a new scope.
Create the identikeys required by Reserved identikey names.
For each import and expose child node, add the identikeys to globalScope specified by that node.
Execute all declaration-first children of each plane together as required by Handling declare-first nodes.
Expose globalScope, in an immutable form, to the containing environment. How this is done depends on the containing enviornment and the Desal implementation, and is not covered by this specification.

When acting as a standalone executable, need to specify what happens to exceptions that bubble all the way up to the bundle node. They are caught, an error message is output, and the bundle node returns some value, like 1. The bundle may expose to the containing environment additional information, depending on the enclosing environment and Desal implementation.

When acting as a standalone executable, what kind of errors should bundle by throwing? This is a problem that applies to many other nodes as well.

For when acting as a library, need a means of hiding/showing certain child namespaces/identikeys of the global namespace. For example, a bundle may have declarations in the global namespace and in a "private" namespace. The bundle should expose the declarations in the global namespace but hide the declarations in the private namespace. There has also been consideration of an "export" attribute/node that would expose specified identikeys, and all other identikeys would not be exposed.

The identikeys added to globalScope by import, using, and expose nodes should not be exposed to the containing environment when the bundle is acting as a library.

12.5.4. sieve

Limits reach of expose and using nodes. Can hide child scidentres.

Like some other special expressions, screen nodes add identikeys to their parent scope, as well as creating their own scope and adding identikeys to it.

* expression expose
* hidable

Example of sieve nodes used to contain the effects of "using" nodes:

--- file A module import as Foo [...] sieve include B include C --- file B using Foo as Bar --- file C func main { println(Bar:something) } --- all together module import as Foo sieve sieve using Foo as Bar sieve func main { Bar:do_something() #error - Bar namespace not defined }

12.6. Non-producing expressions

Expression nodes that never produce.

12.6.1. declare-empty

identifier name
expression type

Creates a variable scidentre in the parent scope. After this node executes, the produced scidentre does not yet point to a value.

var foo var any foo var ? foo var ?any foo var Int foo var ?Int foo var bar bar = 123 println bar bar = 456 println bar

12.6.2. raise

This node alters the control flow when executed. For example, if present in a sequence of statements that are executed in order, executing a node of this type alters control flow in such a way that the following statements in the sequence are not executed.

expression value

If the worker produced by the expression doesn't implement an interface that is or inherits from Signal, throw a NonSignalRaiseAttempt signal with the value from [value] as the wrapped value.

12.7. Sometimes producing expressions

Nodes that can be executed, and sometimes produce.

12.7.1. assign

Assigns a value to an identikey.

identifier name
boolean breed
expression value

The identikey's type must be dynamic, automatic, or strict. If the identikey's type is automatic or strict, the identifier must be variable (not constant).

If bree is false:

Let key by the identikey that [name] refers to.
Execute [value] and let value be the product.
Associate key with value so that key now refers (only) to value.

If breed is true:

Let key be the identikey that [name] refers to.
Execute [value] and let parentValue be the product.
Let faceValue be the required interface for key. If key does not require a particular interface, let faceValue be the active interface of parentValue.
Find parentValue's breeder that produces values with an active interface of faceValue. If such a breeder is not found, throw an error.
Activate the found breeder and let value be the product.
Associate key with value so that key now refers (only) to value.

Example of difference between breeding and not breeding:

decl Person person1 decl Person person2 person1 = Person() person1.name = "John" person2 = person1 //not breeding - person1 and person2 refer to same object person2.name = "Suzy" println( person1.name ) //Suzy person1 = Person() person1.name = "Michael" person2 := person1 //breeding - person1 and person2 refer to different objects person2.name = "Kim" println( person1.name ) //Michael

12.7.2. call

expression receiver
* argument

Execute [receiver], and let receiver be the result.
If result is not callable, throw an error.
Execute the argument values in order.
Send argument values to receiver for execution.
Produce the result on the previous step.

12.7.3. compound

* expression expose
* statement-declaration declaration
+ expression member

Has scope.

Execute each expression in order. Produce the result of the last expression. (Produce nothing if the instance contained no expressions or the last expression didn't produce.)

compound { using System:Console using System:Collections as Boxes const numbers = Boxes:List<MyFace>() Console.WriteLine(numbers.Count.ToString()) }

12.7.4. conditional

expression test
expression result
? expression else

Execute [test] and let test1 be the result.
Downcast test2 to Bool and let test2 be the result.
If test2 is true, execute [result] and produce it's result, ending execution.
If [else] is not present, produce null, ending execution.
Execute [else] and produce it's result.

decl Int a = (x ? 0 : 1) if foo == 1 doStuff1() elif foo == 2 doStuff2() else doDefault() decl bar = (foo == 1) ? getOne() : (foo == 2) ? getTwo() : getDefault() decl bar = if foo == 1 : getOne() elif foo == 2 : getTwo() else : getDefault() if not foo.isSetup? foo.setup() unless prefs.dont_do_it do_it()

12.7.5. curry

Provides a built-in means of partial application. (Note that Desal provides no built-in support for the original type of currying, where a multi-argument function is converted into a chain of single-argument functions.)

expression function
* argument
boolean call

If [call] is true, and this node results in the function receiving enough arguments to be called, the function will be called.

func foo(Int a, Rat b, String c, Bool d) Int { ... } //partial application func(String,Bool)Int foo2 = foo(1, 2.34) print foo2("text", true) //other type of currying func(Int)( func(Rat)( func(String)( func(Bool)Int ))) foo3 = curry(foo) print foo3(1)(2.34)("text")(true) //The above two are equivalent to: print foo(1, 2.34, "text", true)

Assuming the function is not called: If the arguments match only one of the callees/methods of [value], this node produces a value with a function interface as the active interface. If the arguments match more than one of the callees/methods on [value], this node produces a value with an active interface that is made by adding the function interfaces of the callees/methods together.

After execution, the specified parameters have values, so they do not appear on the resultant function.

Once the function has all its arguments supplied, it is called if [call] is true, and the result of that call is produced.

func doStuff1(Int a, String b, Bool alpha) {...} func doStuff1(Int a, Rat b, Bool alpha) {...} func doStuff2 = doStuff1~(3, alpha=false) doStuff2("test") doStuff2(123.456)

The middle line perhaps might also be represented this way:

(declare-first (identifier.name "doStuff2") (curry (identifier.value "doStuff1") (argument (integer.value 3)) (argument (identifier.name "alpha") (identifier.value "false")))) interface Alpha func bar(Int a, Rat b, String c) Alpha alpha = AlphaClass() alpha.bar(0, 0.0, "0") func()void bar1 = alpha.bar~() bar(1, 2.3, "4") func()void bar2 = alpha.bar~(c="text") bar2(7, 9.8) func()void bar3 = alpha.bar~(-9, 0.001, "stuff") bar3()

12.7.6. declare-assign

identifier name
boolean constant
expression type
boolean breed
expression value

Creates a scidentre in the parent scope and assigns the specified value to it. If [constant] is false, creates a constant scidentre; otherwise, creates a variable scidentre.

var any foo = 123 var Nullable<any> foo = 123 var ?any foo = 123 var Int foo = 123 var Nullable<Int> foo = 123 var ?Int foo = 123

12.7.7. identifier

Base/terminal node.

Let ident be the identifier specified by this node.
Let scope be the current scope.
If scope has an identikey that is associated with ident, let scope be the parent scope of scope. If scope has no parent scope, throw an error. Continue moving through parent scopes until an identikey associated with ident is found. Let key be this identikey.
If key is a function identikey, find parent function identikeys with that name, but with different types, and merge all the functions together. (XXX elaborate)
If key is bound to a value, produce the value that key is bound to. If key has been declared that it can be bound to values, but it is currently not bound to anything, return null.
If key is bound to a namespace, throw an error.

println( foo ) (println foo)

12.7.8. select

expression input value
* case
? expression else

Execute [value]. Execute each [values] child of each [case] and compare them to the [value] value (with the .equals? method of the [value] value) until finding a match. Then, execute the [result] of that case and produce the result. If no match is found, and [else] is given, execute [else] and produce its result.

12.7.8.1. case

+ expression test value
expression result

select event.type case Events.QUIT { return } case Events.FOO, Events.BAR, Events.MAZ { //no action } else { throw ErrorClass("unknown event type") } select foo case 1 doStuff1() case 2 doStuff2() else doDefault() decl bar = select foo case 1 : getOne() case 2 : getTwo() else getDefault()

12.7.9. set-property

expression source
identifier property name
expression value

Sets the value of a property. If the active interface of the value does not have a property with the specified name, or the property cannot be set, an error results. Evaluates to the value given by [value].

alpha.beta = "gamma" (= alpha.beta "gamma")

12.7.10. try-catch

expression try
* catcher
? expression on success
? expression finally

Must contain more than just [try].

12.7.10.1. catcher

expression type
? identifier name
? expression test
expression result

The [result] node adds a REMIT allowance.

function execute ( Node_TryCatch node, IScope parentScope ) -> IWorker {
	IScope tryCatchScope = new Scope(parentScope)
	IWorker result
	try {
		result = execute(node.try, tryCatchScope)
	}
	catch( ClientException exception ) {
		for(Node_Catch c in node.catchs) {
			try {
				Type type = Type.wrap(execute(c.type, tryCatchScope))
				if (can_downcast(exception.worker, type)) {
					IScope catchScope = new Scope(parentScope)
					if (c.name != null) {
						G.declareAssign(
							c.name.value
							WoScidentreCategory.CONSTANT,
							type,
							exception.worker,
							catchScope)
					}
					if (c.test != null) {
						if (unwrapBoolean(execute(c.test, catchScope)) == false) {
							continue
						}
					}
					try {
						result = execute(c.result, catchScope)
					}
					catch( ClientRemit remit ) {
						continue
					}
				}
			}
			catch( ClientException exception2 ) {
				if (node.finally != null) {
					execute(node.finally, tryCatchScope)
					throw exception2
				}
			}
		}
		if (node.finally != null) {
			execute(node.finally, tryCatchScope)
			throw exception
		}
	}
	if (node.onSuccess != null) {
		try {
			result = execute(node.onSuccess, tryCatchScope)
		}
		catch( ClientException exception ) {
			if (node.finally != null) {
				execute(node.finally, tryCatchScope)
				throw exception
			}
		}
	}
	if (node.finally != null) {
		execute(node.finally, tryCatchScope)
	}
	return result
}

Execute [try] and let result be the result.
If an exeception raised up through [try] as it was being executed:
	Let exception be the exception.
	For each [catch] child:
		Execute the type expression and let type be the result.
		If the [type] of catch does not match exception, continue to the next catch.
		If the catch specifies a name, bind the exception to that name as a constant.
		If tha catch specifies a test, execute the test, and continue to the next catch if the result is false.
		Execute the [result] of catch and set result to be the product, then stop looking for a catch.
		If a remit signal raises out of the catch while executing it, continue the search for a catch.
		If an exception raises out of the type, test, or result expressions, execute [finally] if present, and then allow the exception to rise out.
	If no matching catch nodes were found, execute [finally] if present, and then allow the exception to rise out.
Otherwise, execute [on success] if present and set [result] to be the result. If an exception raises out of [on success] while executing it, execute [finally] and allow the exception to rise out.
Execute [finally] if present.
Produce result.

try decl foo = getSomething() observe( OutOfMemoryError ) println "I'm not catching that!" //exception is noticed by this try-catch node, but not caught //the exception continues to rise out catch( NullError ) println "null error" catch( FooError e ) println "FooError: (e.message)" catch( Error ) println "unknown error" catch( Exception ) println "unknown exception" observe println "how execution reach here? am not good with computer" else println "no errors!" doSomeStuff() //don't catch errors from this in this node finally cleanup(foo) decl Status stat = try doSomething() Statuses.SUCCESS catch( NotSoBadError ) { Statuses.ERROR observe println "something horrible not caught when trying to doSomething()"

This node is too complicated. Try to simplify it. In particular, see about removing remit node and reintroducing catch/observe distinction.

12.7.11. type-select

expression input value
? identifier casted name
? boolean require match
* type-case
? expression else

[require match] must be present if and only if an [else] is not given.

If [require match] is true (which means an [else] was not given) and no match was found, an exception is thrown.

12.7.11.1. type-case

+ expression test type
expression result

if e is declare-assign
	e2 = e as declare-assign
	sb.reserveWoScidentre( e2.name, e2.category )
elif e is declare-empty
	e2 = e as declare-empty
	sb.reserveWoScidentre( e2.name, e2.category )

typeselect e as e2
case declare-assign
	sb.reserveWoScidentre( e2.name, e2.category )
case declare-empty
	sb.reserveWoScidentre( e2.name, e2.category )

typeselect e as e2
case declare-assign, declare-empty
	sb.reserveWoScidentre( e2.name, e2.category )

12.8. Always producing expressions

Expressions that, aside from e.g. exceptions, always produce when executed. These nodes, other than the and, nand, or, and nor nodes, are not intended to have side effects.

12.8.1. Boolean logic

12.8.1.1. and

Evaluates to false if either child expression evaluates to false.

expression first
expression second

Evaluate the first [expression] node.
Downcast [1] to Bool.
If [2] is false, evaluate this node to false.
Evaluate the second [expression] node.
Downcast [4] to Bool.
Evaluate this node to [5].

12.8.1.2. nand

Evaluates to true if either child expression evaluates to false.

expression first
expression second

Evaluate the first [expression] node.
Downcast [1] to Bool.
If [2] is false, evaluate this node to true.
Evaluate the second [expression] node.
Downcast [4] to Bool.
Evaluate this node to the inverse of [5].

12.8.1.3. or

Evaluates to true if either child expression evaluates to true.

expression first
expression second

Evaluate the first [expression] node.
Downcast [1] to Bool.
If [2] is true, evaluate this node to true.
Evaluate the second [expression] node.
Downcast [4] to Bool.
Evaluate this node to [5].

12.8.1.4. nor

Evaluates to false if either child expression evaluates to true.

expression first
expression second

Evaluate the first [expression] node.
Downcast [1] to Bool.
If [2] is true, evaluate this node to false.
Evaluate the second [expression] node.
Downcast [4] to Bool.
Evaluate this node to the inverse of [5].

12.8.1.5. xor

Evaluates to true if the child expressions evaluate to different values.

expression first
expression second

Evaluate the first [expression] node.
Downcast [1] to Bool.
Evaluate the second [expression] node.
Downcast [3] to Bool.
If [2] and [4] are different, evaluate to true. Otherwise, evaluate to false.

12.8.1.6. xnor

Evaluates to true if the child expressions evaluate to the same value.

expression first
expression second

Evaluate the first [expression] node.
Downcast [1] to Bool.
Evaluate the second [expression] node.
Downcast [3] to Bool.
If [2] and [4] are the same, evaluate to true. Otherwise, evaluate to false.

true and false true xnor false (and true false) (xnor true false)

12.8.2. breed

Creates a new object ("offspring") that encodes some or all of the information from the parent, and exposes that information through the specified interface. If an interface is not specified, the new object has same type as the parent, and should encode most or all of the information from the parent. If an interface is specified, the new object may be an exact copy of the parent object, or it may be of a completetly different form that encodes very little information from the parent object.

This node can be used to copy a value, or to convert a value into a different type.

expression parent
? expression interface

Execute [parent] and let parentValue be the product.
Execute [interface] and let faceValue be the product. If [interface] is not given, let faceValue be the active interface of parentValue.
Find parentValue's breeder that produces values with faceValue as the active interface. If such a breeder is not found, throw an error.
Activate the found breeder.
Produce the new value produced by the breeder.

decl Int num1 = 987 decl Int num2 = copy(num) decl Rat num3 = (num to Rat) (decl Int num1 987) (decl Int num2 (copy num)) (decl Rat num3 (breed num Rat))

12.8.3. caller

? expression interface
identifier method name

Creates a function that, when passed the type specified by [interface], calls the method named [method name] on the first argument with the rest of the arguments sent to it. It's purpose is to help with functional programming.

interface Foo { func doStuff(Int, Int) Rat } decl Foo foo = getFoo() decl func(Foo,Int,Int)Rat doStuffer = Foo::doStuff println doStuffer(foo,3,7) decl doStuffer2 = dyn::doStuff println doStuffer2(foo,3,7) //below all equilavent: println Foo::doStuff(foo,3,7) println dyn::doStuff(foo,3,7) println foo.doStuff(3,7) (decl Foo foo (getFoo)) (decl auto doStuffer (caller Foo doStuff)) (println (doStuffer foo 3 7)) (decl const doStuffer2 (caller dyn doStuff)) (println (doStuffer2 foo 3 7))

12.8.4. object

+ worker

12.8.5. dictionary

expression key type
expression value type
* dictionary-entry

12.8.5.1. dictionary-entry

expression key
expression value

decl ages = dict (String, Int) { "Saray" : 12, "John" : 70, "Mike" : 23 } for pair name, age in ages println name " " age (decl const ages (dict String Int (("Saray" 12) ("John" 70) ("Mike" 23)))) (forpair name age ages (println name " " age))

12.8.6. enum

An enum is similar to an immutable dict.

expression type
+ enum-entry

If [type] is not given, no enum entries can have a value. If [type] is given, all enum entries must have a value. Note that every enum entry has have a unique value. (XXX include restriction in execution instructions)

12.8.6.1. enum-entry

identifier name
? expression value

If [type] is given:

Let EntryFace be a new interface that inherits from EnumDictEntry<T> where T is specified by [type].
For every [enum-entry], create a value with EntryFace as the active interface, where the "value" and "name" properties are those specified by the [enum-entry].
Let ListFace be a new interface. For every [enum-entry], add a readonly property to ListFace with the type of EntryFace and a name specified by the [enum-entry].
Let EnumFace be a new interface that inherits from Interface, EnumDict<T, U>, and ListFace, where T is EntryFace and U is specified by [type].
Let EnumInstance be a value with EnumFace as the active interface such that:

the value given from getting a property of ListFace is the value created in step 2 that is associated with the same [enum-entry] as the property
the Interface implementation is EntryFace, i.e. EnumInstance cast to Interface is EnumFace

Produce EnumInstance.

If [type] is not given:

Let EntryFace be a new interface that inherits from EnumEntry.
For every [enum-entry], create a value with EntryFace as the active interface, where the "name" property is that specified by the [enum-entry].
Let ListFace be a new interface. For every [enum-entry], add a readonly property to ListFace with the type of EntryFace and a name specified by the [enum-entry].
Let EnumFace be a new interface that inherits from Interface, Enum<T>, and ListFace, where T is EntryFace.
Let EnumInstance be a value with EnumFace as the active interface such that:

the value given from getting a property of ListFace is the value created in step 2 that is associated with the same [enum-entry] as the property
the Interface implementation is EntryFace, i.e. EnumInstance cast to Interface is EnumFace

Produce EnumInstance.

Note that the sections specifying Enum, EnumDict, EnumEntry, and EnumDictEntry have additional requirements on the behavior of instances of these interfaces.

enum Animal {
	dog, cat, fish, parrot, ferret, gerbil, hamster
}

interface EntryFace
	inherit EnumEntry

interface ListFace
	get EntryFace dog
	get EntryFace cat
	get EntryFace fish
	get EntryFace parrot
	get EntryFace ferret
	get EntryFace gerbil
	get EntryFace hamster

interface EnumFace
	inherit Interface
	inherit Enum<EntryFace>
	inherit EnumList

Animal a = Animal.dog
Animal b = Animal.fromName("cat")
println Animal.size //assuming size is specified by Collection<T>

for animal in Animal
	println animal.name

activeInterface(Animal) == Interface + Enum<EntryFace> + EnumList
(Animal as Interface) == EntryFace

(enum Animal (dog cat fish parrot ferret gerbil hamster) (for animal Animal (println animal.name))

12.8.7. extract-member

expression source
identifier member name

Retrieves the a method or the value of a property from the value specified by [source]. If the active interface of the value specified by [source] does not have a property or method with the specified name, throw an exception.

println( alpha.beta ) alpha.doStuff() (println alpha.beta) (alpha.doStuff)

12.8.8. function

* parameter-impl
expression return type
expression body

The [body] node adds a RETURN allowance and removes REMIT and YIELD allowances.

If [return info] is not present, the function does not return anything, meaning it does not produce a value when called.

When this node is executed, it produces a value with a function interface as the active interface. Only the [parameter] node and [return info]'s [interface] nodes are executed at this time. When the resultant value is called, the [body] node is executed in the scope of this function node.

func square = { n | n * n } println( square(3) ) => 9 (decl const square (function (a) void (* a a))) (println (square 2)) decl square = {a|a*a} println( square(2) ) println( {a|a*a} 2 )

12.8.9. function-interface

? expression template-argument-count
* parameter-info
expression return type

println( func(Int,Int)Rat ) (println (funcface (Int Int) Rat))

12.8.10. generator

Produces a value that implements an instantiation of the Generator generic interface.

expression type
expression body

The [body] adds a YIELD allowance and removes REMIT and RETURN allowances.

If [type] is not given, the generator does not produce. (The generator could still be useful for producing side effects.)

decl foo = generator { decl Int i = 2 while i lt 5 { yield i i++ } } for i in foo { print i " " } prints: '2 3 4 ' interface of foo == Generator<Int> (decl const foo (generator (decl Int i 2) (while (lt i 5) (compound (yield i) (++ i))))) (forin i foo (print i " ")) decl foo = func(Int a, Int b) Generator<Int> { return generator { decl Int i = a while i lt b { yield i i++ } } } for i in foo(2, 5) { print i " " } prints: '2 3 4 ' decl foo = genfunc(Int a, Int b) Int { decl Int i = a while i < b { yield i i++ } } for i in foo(2, 5) { print i " " } prints: '2 3 4 ' decl foo = [2*x for x in L if x^2 > 3] decl foo = [x in L if x^2 > 3] decl foo = [x in L] for o in [2*x for x in L if x^2 > 3] { println o } //convert to Array Array<Int>([2*x for x in L if x^2 > 3]) //insert into existing collection collection.insert([2*x for x in L if x^2 > 3])

12.8.11. generic-function

+ parameter-info parameter
function

The direction of the [parameter-info] must be "in".

Evaluates to a value with an active interface that inherits from GenericClass and one or more function interfaces. When called, the value returns the value returned from evaluating the function node.

func larger<T>(T a, T b) T { if a lt b return b return a } println larger(2, 7) //prints "7" (declfirst auto larger (genericfunction (T) ((T a) (T b)) T (if (lt a b) (return b)) (return a))) (println (larger 2 7))

12.8.12. generic-interface

+ parameter-info parameter
interface

The direction of the [parameter-info] must be "in".

Evaluates to a value with an active interface that inherits from GenericClass and one or more function interfaces. When called, the value returns the value returned from evaluating the interface node.

interface List<T> { func addFront(T) func addBack(T) func removeFront() T func removeBack() T } decl List<Int> list = getNumbers() list.addFront(2) list.addBack(3) list.addFront(1) println list.removeFront() //prints "1" println list.removeBack() //prints "3" (declfirst auto List (genericinterface (T) (func addFront (T) void) (func addBack (T) void) (func removeFront () T) (func removeBack () T))) (decl List<Int> list (getNumbers)) (list.addFront 2) (list.addBack 3) (list.addFront 1) (println (list.removeFront)) (println (list.removeBack))

12.8.13. instantiate-generic

Need to decide how to include type information. Type value, or type node? Write down and compare pros and cons. (Some related info in "type occurrence.txt")

expression generic
+ argument

decl List<Int> numbers (decl List<Int> numbers)

12.8.14. integer

Base node. Evaluates to an object reference with BigInt as the active interface. The object may implement other interfaces if they do not conflict with the BigInt interface. Must not implement the LimInt interface.

println( 789 ) (println 789)

12.8.15. interface

* expression inheritee
* statused-member member

12.8.15.1. statused-member

member-status
interface-member member

12.8.15.2. member-status

Terminal node. Specifies one of:

new
normal
deprecated

12.8.15.3. breeder

? expression type

Specifies that implementations of that interface can be converted into the specified type. Or, if [interface] isn't given, that the value can be copied.

What is rationale for not just having an "* expression breedable interface" layout entry of interface nodes?

12.8.15.4. callee

* parameter-info
expression return type

12.8.15.5. method

identifier name
expression interface

12.8.15.6. property

identifier name
boolean writable
expression type

12.8.16. rational

Base node. Evaluates to an object with BigRat as the active interface. The object may implement other interfaces if they do not conflict with the BigRat interface. Must not implement the LimRat interface.

println( 123.456 ) (println 123.456)

12.8.17. string

string nodes consist of text

strings are expressions

Base node. Evaluates to an object with interface string as the active interface. The object may implement other interfaces if they do not conflict with the string interface.

println( "this is a string" ) (println "this is a string")

Chapter 13. Reserved identikey names

No user-defined identikeys can be associated with these identifiers.

global - Namespace identikey that refers to the scope associated with the bundle node. Defined in the global scope.
std - Namespace identikey for the standard library. Defined in the global scope.
true - Constant strict identikey bound to the Bool enum true member. Defined in the global scope.
false - Constant strict identikey bound to the Bool enum false member. Defined in the global scope.
outer - Namespace identikey that refers to the outer scope. Defined in all scopes except the global scope. Note that outer::outer may be valid, depending on which scope it appers in.
inst - Namespace identikey that exposes private fields of objects created by the class node. Defined in child scopes of class nodes.
std - The Niviok standard library. Defined in the global scope.

Other possibilites for the standard library: standard, system, language, and various capitalizations (Standard, System, Language) and abbreviations (std, stand, sys, lang).

Need to clarify somewhere (probably multiple places) that namespaces are not scopes, and that scidentres like global and std are not defined in those scopes. But note that this causes problems with e.g. outer:outer:outer. This hasn't been thought out enough yet.

Chapter 14. Standard library

Some new ideas the standard library might not reflect yet: Every object has 1 or more workers. Every worker implements an interface. An interface is a set of interface members. A type places restrictions on what kind of values can appear at a certain location. A cast is an explicit operation that takes a worker and a type, and returns a worker, or throws an exception. How the cast works depends on the type. A downcast is similar to a cast, but it is (or can be) an implicit operation.

interface Signal (formerly "Exception")
	get stack Sequence<String>
	func push (String ->)

interface Error
	inherit Signal

interface Break
	inherit Signal

interface Continue
	inherit Signal

interface Return
	inherit Signal




def ManualType any = ...
def Nullable nany = Nullable<any>
(same_object? nany Nullable<any>) => true


func if { test_val, true_callback |
	if test_val true_callback {}
}

func if { test_val, true_callback, false_callback |
	let dict = dictionary
		true : true_callback
		false : false_callback
	(dict test_val)()
}



interface Object
	#empty
	#Interfaces that don't inherit from anything else inherit from Object.

func Object() Object
	Returns a new wo-ref implementing the Object interface.
	Here, "new" means same_object?(Object(), any_expression_here) must always be false.

union Type
	Interface
	Nullable
	Union
	Subset
	ManualType

declfirst ManualType any = ...
	#worker is any non-null value (but note the existence of Nullable<any>)

declfirst ManualType void = ...
	#worker is unfaced null (can downcast from faced null)
	#Only untyped null values are allowed.
	#downcast: Returns unfaced null if worker is null. Throws if worker is not null.
	#cast: Returns unfaced null.

declfirst ManualType callable = ...
	#worker is callable (i.e. a function)

interface Interface
	get Set<Interface> inheritees
	get ?FunctionInfo callee
	get Dict<Identifier,PropertyInfo> properties
	get Dict<Identifier,Set<MethodInfo>> methods
	get Set<BreederInfo> breeders

interface Nullable
	get Type type
/*
	check: The worker must either: 1) be an unfaced null, or 2) be a faced null with an interface that the , or 3) match the rules of the specified type.
	can downcast: Yes if unfaced null, otherwise dependent on wrapped type.
	can cast: Yes if null, otherwise dependent on wrapped type.
	downcast/cast: If unfaced null and type is interface, returns faced null with interface as face. If unfaced null and type is not interface, returns unfaced null. If faced null, return a faced null with an interface returned by the downcast/cast specified by the type. If not null, follow rules of type.
*/

#The interface must be one of the interfaces in the members set.
interface Union
	get Set<Interface> members





func is?(?any worker, Type type) Bool
func can_downcast<Type type>(?any worker) Bool
func downcast<Type type>(?any worker) type
func can_cast<Type type>(?any worker) Bool
func cast<Type type>(?any worker) type
	''foo as Bar'' could be syntactic sugar for ''cast&lt;Bar>(foo)''
	
	#value
	123 as Int
	123 as ?Int
	123 as void #error
	
	#null
	null as Int #error
	null as ?Int
	null as void
	
	const Int o = getIntAndString()
	print( (o as String).length )

#note that these also work for Types besides ManualType
func interface_is?(Interface, Type) Bool
func determine_downcast(Interface, Type) ?Interface
func null_allowed?(Type) Bool

interface ManualType
	func interface_is?(Interface) Bool
	func determine_downcast(Interface) ?Interface
	get Bool null_allowed?

--- descriptions

-- is?
Tells whether the null or worker complies with the type.

pseudocode:
	if isNull?(worker)
		null_allowed?(type)
	else
		interface_is?(getInterface(worker), type)

-- can_downcast?

pseudocode:
	if isNull?(worker)
		null_allowed?(type)
	else
		determine_downcast(getInterface(worker), type) != null

-- downcast
If @worker is null and the type allows null, returns null. If @worker is null and the type does not allow null, throws an exception. If @worker is not null, returns @worker or a worker inherited by @worker that complies with the type. If there is no such worker, throws an exception.

pseudocode:
	if isNull?(worker)
		if not null_allowed?(type)
			throw NullException()
		null
	else
		const ?Interface face = determine_downcast(getInterface(worker), type)
		if isNull?(face)
			throw CastException()
		interface_downcast<face>(worker)

-- can_cast?

pseudocode:
	if isNull?(worker)
		null_allowed?(type)
	else
		determine_downcast(getRootInterface(worker), type) != null

-- cast
If @worker is null and the type allows null, returns null. If @worker is null and the type does not allow null, throws an exception. If @worker is not null, returns @worker or a worker implemented by the object associated with @worker that complies with the type. If there is no such worker, throws an exception.

pseudocode:
	if isNull?(worker)
		if not null_allowed?(type)
			throw NullException()
		null
	else
		const ?Interface face1 = determine_downcast(getInterface(worker), type)
		if not isNull?(face)
			interface_downcast<face1>(worker)
		else
			const ?Interface face2 = determine_downcast(getRootInterface(worker), type)
			if isNull?(face)
				throw CastException()
			interface_downcast<face2>(rootCast(worker))

-- interface_is?
Tells whether a worker implementing the specified interface would meet the requirements of this type.

-- determine_downcast
Of the specified interface and the interfaces inherited by it, determines which interface would meet the requirments of the type. If no such interface exists, returns null.

-- null_allowed?
Whether null is allowed by the type.





func all_false? = <T>{ Iterable<T> collection, (T -> Bool) callback |
	for T t in collection
		if callback(t)
			return false
	return true
}

func all_true? = <T>{ Iterable<T> collection, (T -> Bool) callback |
	for T t in collection
		if ! callback(t)
			return false
	return true
}

func any_false? = <T>{ Iterable<T> collection, (T -> Bool) callback |
	! all_true?(collection, callback)
}

func any_true? = <T>{ Iterable<T> collection, (T -> Bool) callback |
	! all_false?(collection, callback)
}




union FunctionInfo
	NamedFunctionInfo
	UnnamedFunctionInfo

interface NamedFunctionInfo
	get Sequence<NamedParameterInfo> parameters
	get Type return_type

interface UnnamedFunctionInfo
	get Sequence<UnnamedParameterInfo> parameters
	get Type return_type

func<T> each { Iterable<T> iter, (T -> void) callback |
	for T v in iter
		callback(v)
}

func<TI, TO> map { Iterable<TI> iter, (TI -> TO) callback -> Sequence<TO> |
	const Sequence<TO> s()
	for TI v in iter
		s << callback(v)
	s
}

func<T> filter { Iterable<T> iter, (T -> Bool) callback -> Sequence<T> |
	const Sequence<T> s()
	for T v in iter
		if callback(v)
			s << v
	s
}

def null = compound[
	var foo #declare-empty
	foo #evaluating wo-scidentre not associated with any worker
]

Below is old.

interface Object
interface Interface
... Bool
interface String
interface Int
interface Rat
interface BigInt
interface BigRat
interface<I> Generator
interface Octet
interface Blob
interface<I> Ref
interface<I> WeakRef
interface<I> Array
... Deque
func toDeque<I>(Collection<I>) Deque<I>
... Chain
func<I>(val)I cast
func(val, Interface face)Bool implements?
Bool true
Bool false

decl Deque numbers = Deque(3, 4, 5, 9)
numbers.pushFront(2)
numbers.pushFront(1)
numbers.popBack()
println(join(numbers, " ")) //prints "1 2 3 4 5"

decl Array<Int> numbers2 = Array<Int>(10, 11, 12, 13)
decl Deque<Int> numbers3 = toDeque<Int>(numbers2)

possible additions:

interface<I> Collection
interface<I> List
	indexed
	elements can be added to beginning and end
	dynamic array
interface<I> FwdChain
	forward chain, a singly-linked list
interface<I> Deck
	a deque with an easier name
interface Complex
	a complex number where both parts are limited to rational numbers
interface<I> Grid
	a 2-dimensional array
interface<I> Vector
	a resizable list
interface<I> Queue
interface<I> Stack
interface<I> Dict, SortedDict, MultDict, SortedMultDict, BiDict, SortedBiDict, MiltBiDict, SortedMultiBiDict
interface<I> Set, OrderdSet, MultiSet, OrderdMultiSect

func getProperty(dyn value, String propertyName) dyn
func setProperty(dyn value, String propertyName, dyn propertyValue) dyn

fixed-width/fixed-precision numbers
fixed-point integers
"limited" namespace
interface LimInt
interface LimRat

How to differentiate between mutable and immmutable versions?

//T is the type of an entry in this enum
interface<T : EnumEntry> Enum
	inherit Collection<T>
	func fromName(String str) T

//an Enum where every entry has an associated value
//T is the type of an entry in this enum
//U is the type of a value of an enum entry
interface<T : EnumDictEntry, U> EnumDict
	inherit Enum<T>
	func fromValue(U val) T

interface EnumEntry
	get String name
	func equals?( EnumEntry ) Bool

//U is the type of value each entry is associated with
interface<U> EnumDictEntry
	inherit EnumEntry
	get U value

14.1. println

interface PrintLnFace {
	call( param Stringable objs[] ) PrintLnFace
}
declfirst PrintLnFace println = ...

Need some way for client code to obtain function interfaces that return themselves. For example, "func(...)Self" and "getRecursiveFuncFace(...)". Then, the interface of println could be defined as something like "func(param Stringable objs[]) Self".

Need to define varargs (variadic functions).

Takes in multiple Stringable values, prints each to standard output, and returns itself.

println( 1, " ", 2, " ", 3 ) /* call once with multiple arguments */ println(1)(" ")(2)(" ")(3) /* call several times with one argument each time */ println 1 " " 2 " " 3 /* call several times with one argument each time */ (println 1 " " 2 " " 3) /* call once with multiple arguments */ (((((println 1) " ") 2) " ") 3) /* call several times with one argument each time */

14.2. activeInterface

func activeInterface(dyn) Interface

println( activeInterface(false) == Bool ) //true

Returns the interface that is the active interafce of the specified value.

14.3. String

Besides downcasting to an Interface, String can also be called to produce a String.

func String( Collection<Int> unicodeCodePoints ) String

14.4. func{I}(dyn)I cast

The cast function returns an object cast to the specified interface, or throws a cast error. The returned object must be the same object that was passed in.

if (foo is Bar) cast<Bar>(foo).propOfBar()

14.5. ceil

func ceil(Rat) Int

Finds the ceiling of the specified rational number.

14.6. floor

func floor(Rat) Int

14.7. modulo

Finds the remainder of dividing two integers.

func modulo( Int dividend, Int divisor, ModuloMethod method = ModuloMethod.divisor ) Int

enum ModuloMethod {
	dividend,
	divisor,
	positive,
	negative
}

When one or both of dividend and divisor are negative, there could be two possible remainders, one positive and one negative. In such a case, the ModuloMethod determines which of these to return. When there is only one possible remainder, the ModuloMethod is ignored.

The "dividend" option returns the remainder with the same sign as the dividend. The "divisor" option returns the remainder with the same sign as the divisor. The "positive" option returns the positive remainder. The "negative" option returns the negative remainder.

This function should throw an error if divisor is 0.

modulo(15, 4, dividend) -> 3
modulo(15, 4, divisor) -> 3
modulo(15, 4, positive) -> 3
modulo(15, 4, negative) -> 3

modulo(15, -4, dividend) -> 3
modulo(15, -4, divisor) -> -1
modulo(15, -4, positive) -> 3
modulo(15, -4, negative) -> -1

modulo(-15, 4, dividend) -> -3
modulo(-15, 4, divisor) -> 1
modulo(-15, 4, positive) -> 1
modulo(-15, 4, negative) -> -3

modulo(-15, -4, dividend) -> -3
modulo(-15, -4, divisor) -> -3
modulo(-15, -4, positive) -> 1
modulo(-15, -4, negative) -> -3

14.8. round

func round(Rat, RoundMethod = nearest_away) Int

enum RoundMethod {
	up, //ceiling
	down, //floor
	awayFromZero,
	towardsZero, //truncation
	nearest_up,
	nearest_down,
	nearest_away, //common rounding
	nearest_towards,
	nearest_unbiased //unbiased rounding, bankers rounding
}

Rounds a rational number to an integer using the specified method. The nearest_* method comes in various forms to determine what to do when the rational number is exactly halfway between two integers. For all rational numbers that are not exactly halfway between two rational numbers, the nearest_* methods behave the same. The nearest_unbiased method rounds to the nearest even integer when the number is exactly halfway between two integers. (This is most commonly called bankers rounding.)

round(3.1) -> 3
round(3.1, up) -> 4

round(3.5) -> 4
round(3.5, nearest_towards) -> 3

round(3.9) -> 4
round(3.9, nearest_towards) -> 4

round(-3.1) -> -3
round(-3.1, up) -> -3

round(-3.5) -> -4
round(-3.5, nearest_towards) -> -3

round(-3.9) -> -4
round(-3.9, nearest_towards) -> -4

round(3.4, nearest_unbiased) -> 3
round(3.5, nearest_unbiased) -> 4
round(3.6, nearest_unbiased) -> 4

round(8.4, nearest_unbiased) -> 8
round(8.5, nearest_unbiased) -> 8
round(8.500000001, nearest_unbiased) -> 9
round(8.6, nearest_unbiased) -> 9

14.9. interface generator

interface{I} generator
	func next() I

The next() method will return objects when called until it throws a GeneratorDone exception.

Some looping constructs will automatically obtain a generator by calling the object's getValueIterator, getKeyIterator, or getPairIterator method, and call the next() method of the generator until the exception is thrown

MyClass[] objs for each o in objs o.doStuff()

14.10. func id

func id(obj) Int

println( id(true) )

Every object is associated with a constant non-negative integer. No two objects that are still accessible can have the same object number. This function returns a value, with Int as the active interface, that encodes the object number for the object associated with the given value. Two objects with non-overlapping lifetimes may have the same object id.

Returns a different number for every object. Always returns the same number for the same object, even if that object is a part of different values (the same object cast to different interfaces).

14.11. func sameObject?

Determines whether the two values have the same object.

func sameObject?(obj, obj) Bool

println( sameObject?(foo, bar) )
//same as
println( (foo as obj) == (bar as obj) )
//same as
println( id(foo) == id(bar) )

Tells whether the values are associated with the same object.

14.12. func(obj, interface)bool implements?

Tells whether the object implements the interface, like the implements node.

if implements(foo, Bar) (foo as Bar).propOfBar()

14.13. interface Int

func lessThan?(Int) Bool
func lessThanOrEqual?(Int) Bool
func equal?(Int) Bool
func greaterThanOrEqual?(Int) Bool
func greaterThan?(Int) Bool
func unequal?(Int) Bool
Bool positive?
Bool negative?
func add(Int) Int
func subtract(Int) Int
func multiply(Int) Int
func multiply(Rat) Rat
func divide(Int) Rat
func divide(Rat) Rat
func floorDivide(Int) Int
func floorDivide(Rat) Int
func remainder(Int) Int
Int absolute
func add!(Int)
func subtract!(Int)
func multiply!(Int)
func increment!()
func decrement!()
func floorDivide!(Int)
func floorDivide!(Rat)
func toBuiltin() Int
convert Int
convert Rat
convert String

The non-mutating methods of Int should never throw for precsion reasons, i.e. they should always return an Int that fully represents the result without loss of precision. However, the mutator methods may throw a PrecisionError if the value is not capable of representing the resultant integer.

When Niviok implementations need to determine the value of Int objects that were implemented by user code, they should call the toBuiltin method to get an Int object that was implemented by the implementation. If toBuiltin throws an error, it should raise into user code. If the returned Int is not a built-in, an error results that should extend into user code.

The String produced by the String convertee must represent the stored integer absolutely, with no loss of precision. It may throw an error if it is incapable of producing such a representation. There are no restrictions on how the integer should be represented, although Int implementations generally should try to produce a representation that is simple and short. Implementations of Int should prefer exotic and strange representations over throwing an error. For example, implementations should prefer representing a googolplex with e.g. "10E(10E100)" ofer throwing an error.

14.14. interface BigInt

Inherits from Int.

14.15. interface BigRat

Inherits from Rat.

14.16. interface Interface

get Bool fromAddition?
get Set{Interface} inheritees
get List{Parameters} parameters
get Type returnType
get List{Property} properties
get List{Method} methods
func add(Interface) Interface
func subtract(Interface) Interface

Implements itself.

14.17. interface Object

Bool builtin?
Bool mutable?
Int number
func{I} cast() I
func implements? (Interface) Bool
func sameObject? (Object) Bool

These methods expose the same functionality of some of the nodes.

The builtin? property tells whether the object is implemented by the Niviok implementation, such as for integers and strings. The implements? method tells whether the object implements a specified interface.

14.18. interface rat

func toInt() int
func round() int
func round!()

toInt will throw if the represented value is not already an integer. round should not throw. round! modifies the represented value.

Para between sections:

Constant identikeys in the std namespace. The values these identikeys are bound to are immutable.

interface InterfaceBuilder
func()InterfaceBuilder CInterfaceBuilder
func(int, interface[], interface)interface getFuncInterface
interface{I} Iterator
func{I}(:vararg)array{I} CArray
func(bool[] bits, bool positive = true)int CInt
func{I}(:vararg)list{I} CList
func{I}(I)SelfGen print
func{I}(I)SelfGen println

14.19. Generator

generic<T> interface Generator { func yield() T //throws a GeneratorExhausted exception (which inherits from SpecialCase) when all values have been yielded }

14.20. InterfaceBuilder

map{string, interface} properties
bool alwaysImmutable?
func()interface generate

interface interface is always immutable, so InterfaceBuilder exists to allow creating interface objects procedurally.

14.21. Iterator

interface{I} Iterator
	//values may change
	bool first?
	bool last?
	bool hasNext?
	bool hasPrevious?
	bool between? //iterator points between 2 items (such as after the item was removed)
	bool valid?

	//capabilities of the iterator - values should not change
	bool canMoveForward? //whether the iterator can move forward
	bool canMoveBackward? //whether the iterator can move backwards
	bool canRemove?
	bool canReplace? //whether the objects can be replaced with different objects
	bool canRead?
	bool canInsertAfter?
	bool canInsertBefore?
	bool canCompareCollection?
	bool canCompareIterator? //corresponds to equal?
	bool canComparePosition? //corresponds to before? and after?

	func moveForward()
	func moveBackward()
	func remove()
	func replace(I)
	func insertAfter(I)
	func insertBefore(I)
	func sameCollection?( Iterator{I} ) bool
	func before?( Iterator{I} ) bool
	func after?( Iterator{I} ) bool
	func equal?( Iterator{I} ) bool
	
	I value

An iterator is used to access the elements in a container. If the elements are not ordered 2-dimensionally, an 2-dimensional order must be decided for the iterator that does not change for that iterator instance. If the elements in the container are ordered 2-dimensionally, the iterator must refer the elements in that order.

The equals? method returns true if both iterators are pointing to same item of the same collection. If the collection is unordered, the order the iterator moves over items must also be the same.

A valid iterator either refers to an element or a position between two elements. An iterator should only refer to a position between two elements when the element the iterator currently pointed to was removed. If the iterator is not valid, or read? is false, the value property refers to null.

An iterator only becomes invalid if:

the container contains no objects
the iterator is moved beyond all objects
a non-supported method is called (example: moveBackward() is called on an iterator that can only move forward)

If an iterator is not valid, it may be possible to revalidate it by calling next() or previous(). For example, if the iterator refers to the last object and next is called, the iterator becomes invalid, but calling previous may make the iterator valid again. Whether an iterator can be revalidated and under what circumstances the iterator is revalidated is dependant on the implementation of the iterator.

Containers should always give iterators with the same functionality. For example, if a container, when it has three elements, gives an iterator with forward? set to true, it should also give an iterator with the property forward? set to true when it has 1, even though calling moveForward() would invalidate the iterator.

Container{int} numbers; Iterator iter = numbers.iterate(); int num = iter.value while( iter.valid? ) int num = iter.value iter.moveForward()

14.22. CInterfaceBuilder

CInterfaceBuilder, when called, returns an object that can be used to procedurally and/or dynamically create interface objects.

14.23. getFuncInterface

func getFuncInterface (
	int templateParamCount,
	interface[] params,
	interface returnInterface,
) interface

Returns an interface specifying a call method with the specified number of template parameters, the specified parameters, and the specified return interface. If returnInterface is null, the interface specifies a void call method. Every time it is called with the same arguments, it must return the same object.

Chapter 15. Warnings

This is a list of warnings predefined by this specification. Agents should create other warnings whenever needed.

name | meaning
always null | A node that will never produce a value when executed is being used as if it will sometimes produce a value. This warning is produced by the node that attempts to make use of the output, such as an assignment node, and not the node that doesn't produce. A node that will never produce a value when executed is being used as if it will produce a value. Example: The result is being assigned to an identikey or passed as an argument. This applies to node types like call which can sometimes produce a value, if a particular instance can be determined to never produce a value. (XXX should this warning apply to using nodes like throw, break, or return as expressions?
no effect | The output of a node that does not have side effects is not being used. For example, a member of a compound that is an integer node and does not appear last. The integer node would have no effect.
unreachable | Code is unreachable. Execution will never reach a particular piece of code.

Chapter 16. Error handling during processing

If an error is found during processing, and none of the already generated nodes have been executed, all generated nodes in the entire Niviok tree must not be used for purposes beyond explaining the source of errors. Construction of the Niviok node tree may continue after errors are found. The main() function must not be called, and the members should not be exposed as a library.

If errors occur while generating the Niviok node tree, and execution has already begun, a warning should immediately be emitted describing the error. How this warning is emitted is undefined. Generation of the Niviok node tree may continue. When execution reaches the damaged section of the tree, an error should be thrown describing the error. If execution never reaches the damaged section of the tree, the error should have no effect.

Chapter 17. Rationales

This chapter explains the decisions behind various choices made for Niviok.

17.1. Dynamic static typing

Dynamic static typing refers to explicitly using and enforcing type information that isn't available until runtime. The type information isn't known until runtime, but after it's known, it's enforced and can't be changed.

An example of this is loading an interface from a library and then using obtaining values with that interface through the library. The loaded interface can be used as the type for function parameters, free identifiers, etc. So although the interface wasn't known until runtime, one the information was known, it was enforced, and the values of that interface are only accessed by ensuring they are of that interface.

Dynamic static typing can do nothing beforehand to ensure property/method access is correct, but it can ensure that various values are of the same type. For example, consider the case where an interface is loaded from a library and bound to an identifer. Then a free identifier is declared to be of that type, and a function is declared to accept a value of that type. An implementation will known that the free identifer and the function's parameter are of the same type, so the value bound to the free identifier can safely be passed to the function. This safety could not be ensured with fully dynamic typing.

Dynamic static typing is not as safe as fully static typing, but interfaces cannot always be known before runtime, which is a requirement for fully static typing. Therefore, Niviok should provide something to give more type safety for the cases when interfaces cannot be known until runtime. Dynamic static typing is safer than fully dynamic typing.

Interface Foo = lib['Foo'] Interface Bar = lib['Bar'] func()Foo getFoo = lib['getFoo'] func(Bar)Int doStuff = lib['doStuff'] Foo foo = getFoo() //static typing: known beforehand that types match foo.somthing() //dynamic typing: don't know beforehand whether Foo declares a 'somthing' method doStuff(foo) //static typing: known beforehand that types don't match --- Dyn getFoo = lib['getFoo'] Dyn doStuff = lib['doStuff'] Dyn foo = getFoo() //dynamic typing: don't know beforehand whether types match foo.somthing() //dynamic typing: don't know beforehand whether value of foo has a "somthing" method doStuff(foo) //dynamic typing: don't know beforehand whether types match

Arguments against: Interfaces should almost always be known beforehand. Dynamic static typing may be very rarely used, and could encourage bad programming.

17.2. Terms

17.2.1. get/set

term as verb | term as noun | good points | bad points
get | getter | short, easy to say, easy to spell, common amoung programming languages | implies the property has been taken away
set | setter | short, easy to say, easy to spell, common amoung programming languages | sounds more like adding a new property than changing the value of a pre-existing property
access | accessor
retrieve | retriever
read | reader
write | writer
mutate | mutator

Additional notes:

The one letter difference between "get" and "set" (and "getter" and "setter") could cause errors more easily than if the difference were greater. Also, the noun form is slightly irregular; some people may expect "geter" and "seter" to be the noun form.

17.3. Executing boolean logic nodes

In other languages, functions/methods that return boolean values are often chained together with short-circuiting boolean logic nodes. XOR and XNOR nodes cannot short-circuit, and thus this does not apply to them.

list.empty? $or list.clear() //similar to: $if $not list.empty? : list.clear() list.empty? $and list = getValues() //similar to: $if list.empty? : list = getValues()

17.4. Disallowing executing declaration-first

Children of declaration-first nodes are executed when the scope is first created, which may involve executing an identifier associated with a variable identikey. When execution reaches a declaration-first node, the identifiers used to create the initial value assigned to the identikey may be assigned to different values. Thus, executing a declaration-first node could produce unexpected results.

$decl Int alpha = 12345 $block { alpha = 9000 println ( $decl-first Int beta = alpha ) //prints "12345" }

In the above example, alpha is executed and assigned to beta when the scope for the block node is created. Then, 9000 is assigned to alpha. Then, the declaration-first node is executed, producing the value assigned to beta, which is 12345. A programmer may have expected beta to be bound to the current value of alpha, which is 9000.

Chapter 18. Unsorted/outdated stuff

18.1. Closures

Functions and classes (amoung others) have references to their containing scope. Identifier references in these scopes can be accessed and modified by the functions/classes.

Copy closures create copies of specific values when a function node is executed. Modifying this copy does not modify the captured scope.

//regular closures func makePrinters(Int max) func()void[] { func()void[] printers = new func()void[] Int i = 1 while i <= max { printers << func()void { print i + ' ' } i++ } return printers } //array of functions that have no parameters and return nothing func()void[] printers = makePrinters(10) for printer in printers { printer() } //output 10 10 10 10 10 10 10 10 10 10 Each of the anonymous functions held a reference to the same scope where i was defined. Because i held 10 when the functions were called, each output 10. //copy closures func makePrinters(Int max) func()void[] { func()void[] printers = new func()void[] Int i = 1 while i <= max { printers << func()void { copyclosure i print i + ' ' } i++ } return printers } //array of functions that have no parameters and return nothing func()void[] printers = makePrinters(10) for printer in printers { printer() } //output 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 Each of the anynonymous functions held a copy of the value of i at the time the function was created.

18.2. Tree examples

18.2.1. Example 1

global declare-const identifier "main" expression [value] (function-definition) function-parameter identifier "args" expression [interface] (interface-template-instantiation) expression [interface-template] (identifier) "array" expression [template-argument] (identifier) "string" expression [return-interface] (identifier) "int" expression (return) expression (integer) 0 func main(string[] args) int return 0

18.2.2. Example 2

global (global) declaration (declaration > function-declaration) name (string) "main" return (expression > object-reference) name (string) "int" item (item > return) value (expression > integer) 0 func main() int return 0 <global type="global"> <declaration type="function-declaration"> <name type="string">main</name> <return type="object-reference"> <name type="string">int</name> </return> <item type="return"> <value type="integer">0</value> </item> </declaration> </global>

18.2.3. Example 3

global (global) name-bind (name-bind) identifier (identifier) "main" expression (function-definition) parameter (parameter) interface (interface > function-call) function (function > identifier) "array" argument (expression > identifier) "string" identifier (identifier) "args" return-interface (interface > identifier) "int" expression (expression > return) expression (expression > literal-integer) 0 func main(string[] args) int return 0 <global type="global"> <name-bind type="name-bind"> <identifier type="identifier">main</identifier> <expression type="function-definition"> <parameter-list type="parameter-list"> <parameter type="parameter"> <identifier type="identifier">args</identifier> <expression type="function-call"> <identifier type="identifier">array</identifier> <argument-list type="argument-list"> <identifier type="identifier">string</identifier> </argument-list> </expression> </parameter> </parameter-list> <return-interface type="identifier">int</return-interface> <expression-list type="expression-list"> <expression type="return"> <expression type="literal-integer">0</expression> </expression> </expression-list> </function> </name-bind> </global>

18.3. get interface

It's always possible to bind the interface of an object to an identifier.

func getInterface{I}(I o) { return I; } dynref o = getMysteryObj() interface i = getInterface(o) i o2 = o

18.4. obj interface

All objects automatically implement the "obj" interface.

obj foo = getAnObject() (myinterface foo) .doStuff 3

18.5. Binding to identifiers

int alpha

Declares that "alpha" can refer to objects that implement the "int" interface. alpha currently doesn't refer to anything; i.e. it refers to null.

alpha = 3

Creates an object that implements the int interface and makes alpha refer to it

int beta = 5

Declares that "beta" can refer to objects that implement the "beta" interface. Creates an object that implements the int interface. Binds the object to "beta".

Multiple identifiers can refer to the same object.

obj o = getObj() int a = o rat b = o

18.6. Return interfaces of print and println

Below, [unbound] means the interface is not bound to an identifier. However, these interfaces can be bound to identifiers and used like any user-created interface, and they have no special properties.

func{I}(I)[unbound] print
func{I}(I)[unbound] println

interface{I} Print
	func call(I) Print

interface{I} PrintLine
	func call(I) PrintLine

When print is called, it returns an object that implements an interface like Print. When println is called, it returns an object that implements an interface like PrintLine. Neither interface is bound to an identifier when execution begins. They are not the same interface, meaning print(1).interface == println(1).interface executes to false.

println 1 2 3 "a" "b" "c" 4.5 6.7 8.9

18.7. Adjuncts

interface IMyInterface public func doStuffA() public func doStuffB() class MyClass :implements(IMyInterface) ... func IMyInterface.doAB() this.doStuffA() this.doStuffB() func testThing(ref IMyInterface arg) arg.doAB() MyClass inst testThing(inst)

18.8. runtime interface implementation

With Niviok, you should be able to write a function that takes an interface (foo) and returns a function that takes an object of that interface (foo) and returns an object that implements that same interface (foo), but with an implementation that writes to a log anytime a method is called.

log l = Log()
foo o = Foo()
foo wrapped = wrap(o, l)
doStuffWithAFoo(wrapped)

Now anytime a method is called on the object, a log entry could be written.

func{I} wrap(I o, log l) I
objbuilder wrapper = newObjbuilder()
wrapper.implement(I)
for prop in I.props
wrapper.interfaces[I].setProp( prop.name,
func(:vararg)obj

interface i = newInterface()
i.inherit(I)
for prop in 

wrap(...) takes an interface and returns a function
wrap(foo)(...) takes a foo and returns a foo

18.9. Runtime interface creation

func createInterface( map{string,dyn} methods ) interface
	interface rv = newInterface()
	for (name, meth) in methods
		rv.methods.add( pair(name, meth.functionSignature) )
	return rv

func foo(int b) string
...

func bar(float c, float d) myClass
...

func baz(widget1 e, widget4 f)
...

map(string, func) table = {
"methA": foo,
"methB": bar,
"methC": baz
}
interface myinterface = createInterface(table)

func alpha(int g) string
...

func beta(float h, float i) myClass
...

func gamma(widget1 j, widget4 k)
...

myinterface myobj = {
methA: alpha,
methB: beta,
methC: gamma
}
string str = obj.methA(3)
myClass val = obj.methB(5.5, 7.7)
obj.gamma( createWidget1(), Widget4Factory.makeOne() )

18.10. "self" return type

func(int,float)self

is the same as

interface __foo__
	func call(int,float) __foo__

func example(int num) self
	...
	
example 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 //calls the example function 10 times

18.11. Bind

interface foo
	...

func bar(foo o, int num)
	...

foo fooInst = getAFoo()
bar(fooInst, 3)
(fooInst => bar) 3
func() funcy = (fooInst => bar)
funcy(3)

obj => func

The "=>" operator binds the obj to the first argument of the function. It executes to a function. Semantically this creates a function-definition with a closure of the obj and func.

18.12. Classes

Classes produce functors that, when called, create objects. If a class implements more than 1 interface, it can declare which of the implemented interfaces is the active interface of the returned object by marking an interface as default. If no interface is marked, the active interface is obj.

18.13. Noninstantiated interface templates

interface list{I}
	readonly int count
	func pushFront(I o)
	func popFront() I

struct node{C}
	node{C} next = null
	node{C} value = null

class makeList{T}
	node{T} first
	
	interface list{T} #default //so makeList returns a list instead of an obj that has to be cast
		...

list{int} nums = makeList{int}()
nums.pushFront(3)
nums.pushFront(5)
print nums.size //2

list{string} names = makeList{string}()
names.pushFront("John")
names.pushFront("Sarah")
names.pushFront("Billy")
print names.size //3

list someList = nums
print someList.size //2
someList.pushFront(5) //error

someList may refer to any kind of list, such as list{foo}, list{bar}, etc, so only methods that have the same paramater and return interfaces for all list{}s can be called.

18.14. Dynamic library loading

The selectLibrary function enables gaining references to objects without knowing the nodes that created the objects.

interface Library
	readonly String path
	readonly String name
	readonly String version
	readonly Bool loaded?
	func key(String name) Dyn
	func get{I}(String name) I
	func load()
	func unload()

//prototype
func selectLibrary(string identifier, string version, bool load? = true) Library

---

string identifier
string version
if platform == platforms.MacOSX or platform == platforms.Windows
	identifier = "libxml"
	version = "2.1"
elif platform == platforms.Linux
	identifier = "/usr/lib/libxml.so"
	version = "56"
else
	throw Error("unsupported platform")

Library XmlLib = selectLibrary(identifier, version)

Interface XmlElement = XmlLib.get{Interface}("XmlElement")
Dyn XmlReader = XmlLib["XmlReader"]

XmlElement element = XmlRead.read("foo.xml").documentElement

18.15. Static typing

XXX spec out static typing and demand that implementations check all typing as much as possible before running anything. Note the section on dynamic static typing.

In the third part of this exercise I'm going to focus on an issue related to just a few lines of code, that is quite interesting: partly because it involves a minor quirk in Java 8, partly because the understanding of it and its work-around is a good way to deepen the comprehension of lambdas.

Before moving to the main topic, there are a few things to say. First, I have to mention that the source code underwent a slight refactoring, in which:

I encapsulated everything related to progress tracking into a separate ProgressTracker class.
I turned some methods in the Main class from static to regular instance method - this means that now Main is instantiated before being executed.
I also renamed the package, but this is just a cosmetic thing.

There could be many things to say about this transformation, which converts the original, functional “look” into something traditionally object-oriented. But the scope of SolidBlue2, so far, is so simple that there is not enough context to make serious considerations about this topic.

Second, the scanning of the filesystem has been improved with a try-with-resources:

try (final Stream<Path> s = Files.walk(targetPath, FOLLOW_LINKS))
  {
    final Map<String, String> storage = s.filter(Main::matchesExtension)
                                         .peek(progressTracker::notifyDiscoveredFile)
                                         .collect(toList())
                                         .stream()
                                         .collect(toMap(p -> p.getFileName().toString(),
                                                        p -> computeFingerprint(p, "MD5"),
                                                        (v1, v2) -> v2));
    store(targetPath, storage);
  }

Stream, actually, has got a close() method. When the Stream source is in memory there's no need to close it, as the memory resources are handled by the Garbage Collector as usual. But when the source opens some system resources (such as sockets or files), the Stream should be explicitly closed. SolidBlue2 is currently a tiny command line application that terminates after the scan, so this aspect is not relevant now; but since it is going to become a full-fledged application with its own user interface, it's better to properly handled the thing before I forget. The best way to do that is to use try-with-resources, since Stream implements AutoCloseable.

Ok. Now we can focus on the main theme of this post. Let's look at the method that stores data into a file:

private void store (final Path targetPath, final Map<String, String> storage)
  throws IOException
  {
    final Path folder = targetPath.resolve(".it.tidalwave.solidblue2");
    final Path file = folder.resolve("fingerprints-j8.txt");
    Files.createDirectories(folder);
    log.info("Storing results into {} ...", file);

    try (final PrintWriter w = new PrintWriter(Files.newBufferedWriter(file, Charset.forName("UTF-8"))))
      {
        storage.entrySet().stream()
                          .sorted(comparing(Entry::getKey))
                          .forEach(e -> w.printf("MD5(%s)=%s\n", e.getKey(), e.getValue()));
      }
  }

While the code is fine and it's also robust, as it uses try-with-resources, one might ask whether Java 8 offers a less verbose way to do a simple operation such as writing some strings into a file. The verbosity related to BufferedWriter and PrintWriter is the thing I'm aiming at. In Java 8, actually, the Files class has been augmented with a couple of methods (I'm omitting some non relevant stuff):

public final class Files 
  {
    public static Stream<String> lines (Path path)
      throws IOException;

    public static Path write (Path path, Iterable<? extends CharSequence> iterable) 
      throws IOException;

    ...
  }

They are pretty useful as they encapsulate all the technicalities about opening and closing a file and provide a good abstraction that only focuses on the data to be read and written. Thus one might be induced to write something such as:

Files.write(file, 
            storage.entrySet().stream()
                              .sorted(comparing(Entry::getKey))
                              .map(e -> String.format("MD5(%s)=%s", e.getKey(), e.getValue())), 
            Charset.forName("UTF-8"));
    

Unfortunately this fails in compilation, because Stream<T> doesn't extend Iterable<T>. This is pretty curious, since Stream<T> does provide indeed a public Iterator<T> iterator() method (as well as another couple of methods defined in Iterable). The thing has been already debated at StackOverflow, where one of the answers was more or less “the thing is deliberate, because programmers are used to the fact that they can call iterator() on a collection multiple times, while Stream can be used only once“. Actually, one should recall that Stream is not a collection, rather a manipulator of collections of data. And Streams have been designed with the internal iteration concept in mind, while iterators are made for external iteration.

To have an authoritative answer I've asked about this issue at the core-libs-dev mailing list and got a very exhaustive reply from Remi Forax, including this confirmation:

iterator() is not a 'real' method of Stream, it's a kind of escape hatch that you can use if you have an API that takes an Iterator as parameter but it will be slow.

Given that anyway Stream<T> provides all the methods in Iterable<T>, one might be tempted to try a cast (I've slightly rewritten the code chunk for better readability):

final Stream<String> s = storage.entrySet().stream()
                                           .sorted(comparing(Entry::getKey))
                                           .map(e -> String.format("MD5(%s)=%s", e.getKey(), e.getValue()));
Files.write(file, (Iterable<String>)s, Charset.forName("UTF-8"));

But this is clearly a naïve approach: you can fool the compiler, nevertheless you will get a ClassCastException at runtime. After all, Java is still a strongly typed language, both statically and dynamically, and the JVM cannot but tell you that Stream<T> doesn't extend Iterable<T>. A safe and quick way to “convert” a Stream<T> into an Iterable<T> would be to just add collect(toList()), but this would accumulate all the products into a memory buffer. No problem with smaller scenarios, but it could be an issue for larger amounts of data. And it would be a pity to waste memory for an operation that might be inherently pipeline-oriented.

Stream.sorted(), like in the code example above, is already buffering all data into a list, because it's required by the sorting algorithm. Anyway I'd like to discuss a general case in which there could be no sorting.

But there's a trick:

final Stream<String> s = storage.entrySet().stream()
                                           .sorted(comparing(Entry::getKey))
                                           .map(e -> String.format("MD5(%s)=%s", e.getKey(), e.getValue()));
Files.write(file, (Iterable<String>)s::iterator, Charset.forName("UTF-8"));

This compiles and works. What's happening here? s::iterator is a method reference which matches a Supplier<Iterator<T>>. By matching, in Java 8 we mean that the two things are both functional interfaces sharing the same “functional descriptor”: Java 8 doesn't care of the method names, but of the fact that they have the same parameters and return type (and eventually the throw clause). Since also Iterable<T> matches a Supplier<Iterator<T>>, s::iterator can be assigned to an Iterable<String>.

So, why the explicit cast (Iterable<String>)? It is required indeed, otherwise the compiler would complain again:

error: no suitable method found for write(Path,s::iterator,Charset)

The reason for this fact is more obscure. Again, Remi Forax explains that:

The conversion from a method reference to a functional interface doesn't work if the target type is parameterized by wildcard. This is specified like this in the Java spec. I consider that this is a bug but this is actually what the spec says. I hope we will be able to fix that in Java 10, but that just my opinion.

The problem is the wildcard, since Files.write() accepts an Iterable<? extends CharSequence>. So we have to live with that cast, that it's just a minor annoyance after all. Unless this RFE is accepted for Java 10...

A better approach

Note that first comment of the RFE: the idea has been suggested to write a specific Collector to do the job as an alternate solution - it is a smart idea IMHO, as what we're actually doing is a collection of the Stream products into a file. I've already posted about how to write a custom Collector. A possible solution is:

public final class FileCollector implements Collector<String, PrintWriter, Void>
  {
    private final PrintWriter pw;

    private final AtomicBoolean parallelChecker = new AtomicBoolean();

    public static Collector<String, ?, ?> toFile (final Path file,
                                                  final Charset charset,
                                                  final OpenOption ... openOptions)
      throws IOException
      {
        return new FileCollector(file, charset, openOptions);
      }

    private FileCollector()
      {
        throw new UnsupportedOperationException();
      }

    private FileCollector (final Path file, final Charset charset, final OpenOption ... openOptions)
      throws IOException
      {
        pw = new PrintWriter(Files.newBufferedWriter(file, charset, openOptions));
      }

    @Override
    public Supplier<PrintWriter> supplier()
      {
        return this::oneShotPrintWriterSupplier;
      }

    @Override
    public BiConsumer<PrintWriter, String> accumulator()
      {
        return PrintWriter::println;
      }

    @Override
    public BinaryOperator<PrintWriter> combiner()
      {
        return (a, b) -> { fail(); return null; }; // never called
      }

    @Override
    public Function<PrintWriter, Void> finisher()
      {
        return pw -> { pw.close(); return null; };
      }

    @Override
    public Set<Characteristics> characteristics()
      {
        return Collections.emptySet();
      }

    private PrintWriter oneShotPrintWriterSupplier()
      {
        if (parallelChecker.getAndSet(true))
          {
            fail();
          }

        return pw;
      }

    private void fail()
      {
        pw.close();
        throw new IllegalStateException("Can't be used with a parallel Stream!");
      }
  }

Basically, we're saying that this collector can be applied to a Stream of Strings, it uses a PrintWriter as the accumulator and doesn't produce a Java object as the result (that's why I used Void as the third type parameter). The implementation is straightforward, but there is a point that must be dealt with: parallelism. Collectors in fact are designed to work in parallel if the incoming Stream is parallel; but writing objects to a file can't be a parallel operation. Eventually, the incoming Stream must be turned into a sequential one before calling collect(); and our Collector should perform a safety check. Unfortunately the Collector itself never sees the Stream it is applied to; but we can assume that it is being run in parallel if the Supplier of the accumulator is called more than once (note that the check might be triggered after that some items have been already processed and written to the file). At this point, it is safe to assume (at least with the current implementation of the Java 8 runtime...) that the combiner is never called.

The code can be tested with TestNG:

private Collector<String, ?, ?> underTest;

...

@BeforeMethod
public void setup()
  throws IOException
  {
    underTest = FileCollector.toFile(file, Charset.forName("UTF-8"));
  }

...

@Test(invocationCount = 100,
      expectedExceptions = IllegalStateException.class,
      expectedExceptionsMessageRegExp = ".*Can't be used with a parallel Stream!")
public void must_fail_with_a_parallel_stream()
  {
    IntStream.range(0, 10000)
             .mapToObj(n -> "String #" + n)
             .collect(toList())
             .parallelStream()
             .collect(underTest);
  }

Note that not specifying CONCURRENT in the characteristics does not ensure that the Collector is run in a sequential fashion: it only means that the accumulator cannot be manipulated in a concurrent way, but with a parallel Stream the runtime might still use multiple accumulators in parallel (synchronizing the calls to the Collector that manipulate them). As per Java 8, there is no way to surely force a Collector to run in a sequential fashion with a parallel Stream.

It's possible to write the Collector in a radically shorter fashion. Given that in the end it's just an aggregate of four lambdas, a factory method Collector.or() might be used by providing them inline. Note that this is possible even when there are status variables, as they can be turned into variables in the scope of the factory method. Since lambdas can be usually written in a single line, the result is shorter. Below the shorter code, even though I'm unsure what version is more readable, especially considering a reader that is at his first experience with Java 8.

Lambdas can access variables declared in the enclosing scope, but they must be final, as it happens with inner classes. The compiler doesn't require them to be declared final, it suffices that they are not re-assigned (“effectively final”). Nevertheless I prefer to always use the final keyword every time something is final, for better readability.

public final class FileCollector
  {
    public static Collector<String, ?, ?> toFile (final Path file,
                                                  final Charset charset,
                                                  final OpenOption ... openOptions)
      throws IOException
      {
        final PrintWriter pw = new PrintWriter(Files.newBufferedWriter(file, charset, openOptions));
        final AtomicBoolean parallelChecker = new AtomicBoolean();

        return Collector.of(() -> safeGetPrintWriter(parallelChecker.getAndSet(true), pw),
                            PrintWriter::println,
                            (a, b) -> safeGetPrintWriter(true, pw), // never called
                            pw2 -> { pw2.close(); return null; });
      }

    private FileCollector()
      {
        throw new UnsupportedOperationException();
      }

    private static PrintWriter safeGetPrintWriter (final boolean condition, final PrintWriter pw)
      {
        if (condition)
          {
            pw.close();
            throw new IllegalStateException("Can't be used with a parallel Stream!");
          }

        return pw;
      }
  }

With the new Collector this point the original code can be refactored into:

private void store (final Path targetPath, final Map<String, String> storage)
  throws IOException
  {
    final Path folder = targetPath.resolve(".it.tidalwave.solidblue2");
    final Path file = folder.resolve("fingerprints-j8.txt");
    Files.createDirectories(folder);
    log.info("Storing results into {} ...", file);
    storage.entrySet().stream()
                      .sorted(comparing(Entry::getKey))
                      .map(e -> String.format("MD5(%s)=%s", e.getKey(), e.getValue()))
                      .collect(toFile(file, Charset.forName("UTF-8")));
  }

One relevant part of Remi's comment was about performance. Perhaps in most cases we can safely ignore the performance hit (for instance, when we have just a few lines to write). Since I've started grokking with the Java Micro Benchmarking Harness (JMH) it could be a useful exercise to measure the performance of the alternate solutions of the problem I presented here. Stuff for a further post.

The whole project, made with Maven, is available at BitBucket; the source illustrated in this post is part of 1.0-ALPHA-3.

by Fabrizio Giudici and Emmanuele Sordini, September 2006

Some time ago I read somewhere that with Java there are ten thousands ways to create an image. Well, ten thousands is a bit more than the real thing, but sure there are many ways. This is because there is more than a single API to work with images - for instance:

the class Image is defined in AWT and represents a minimalist approach, just to deal with icons and little more;
the class BufferedImage is defined in Java 2D and is much more rich of semantics, as the programmer can manipulate bits, colors, perform filtering, and many more; furthermore, BufferedImage is the type of objects returned by the Image I/O API, the standard way to read and write images in a large number of formats;
the class PlanarImage is defined in JAI, the Java API for Advanced Imaging, the tool for serious image manipulators (such as the guys at NASA): not only this API features some complex operations, such as Fourier Transforms and such, but also supports sub-pixel processing, ROI (regions of interests) and tiling, the way for handling large images that don't conveniently fit in memory.

Add to this scenario ImageJ, a non-standard Java API which is very popular.

Having so many APIs is not a bad thing, as each API has a specific context. But a problem might arise if you need to integrate code from different developers that use different APIs. In this scenario you have probably to guess the algorithm from the existing code and re-implement it with your favourite API. This is an issue that I'm planning to address as I'm writing blueMarine, an open source application for photo management designed as an open platform, where users can (and are encouraged to) plug-in many extensions (I've also been contacted by a guy who's researching on image processing and would like to write his own code to handle images).

One solution of the problem could be... to add one more API! Obviously this API would not be another imaging engine, but an "abstraction layer", something that enables the programmer to work with images without knowing too much about the inner details. This is precisely what the Mistral project is about.

An experimental approach

Actually I've been involved in image manipulation in Java for some years now, as part of the above cited blueMarine project. Recently I've joined my friend Emmanuele Sordini in Pleiades, an experimental project about parallel image processing with the Sun Grid Compute Utility. It was a very pleasing and mind-opening experience, as Emmanuele and I approached the problem with different attitudes: Emmanuele is an expert in maths and such and had image processing experience mostly with other languages with Java; on the other hand I can handle complex maths only if somebody clearly explains them, while I'm mostly interested in the design and architecture perspectives.

We started working independently: Emmanuele first wrote a couple of prototypes of the algorithm we wanted to implement. The former prototype was written with ImageJ, the latter with JAI - we then focused on the latter having a preference for standard Java APIs, even though we will return to ImageJ in future for doing some comparisons. But for the sake of this discussion, we can assume that the choice of another developer could have been ImageJ.

My contribute on the project was to write a parallel implementation of the algorithm (details can be found here). I must confess that I'm a bit maximalist when I think of design: within the reasonable, I always strive for the most flexible and wide-purpose solutions. For what concerns exploting parallelism, my intention was to define a very simple design that could allow to run Emmanuele's code on a single PC as well as on the Sun Grid, taking advantage of all the computing resources of both contexts. After all, besides running it on the Sun Grid, I also want to integrate Pleiades in blueMarine.

Indeed we think that this is an interesting approach, as people is saying that we are going to face more and more parallel computing scenarios in future, and they can be "simple" multi-core systems or complex facilities such as the Grid. And in these days people can easily build a cheap distributed computing network by using opensource technologies such as Jini™ and Rio: definitely another scenario to deal with.

The abstraction layer

As an example is worth a thousands words, let's consider this JAI code sketch that should read a photo (from my Nikon D100 camera), crop it and compute the histogram:

import java.util.logging.Logger;  
import java.io.File;  
import java.io.IOException;  
import java.awt.RenderingHints;  
import java.awt.image.BufferedImage;  
import java.awt.image.DataBuffer;  
import java.awt.image.SampleModel;  
import javax.imageio.ImageIO;  
import javax.imageio.ImageReader;  
import javax.imageio.stream.ImageInputStream;  
import javax.media.jai.Histogram;  
import javax.media.jai.PlanarImage;  
import javax.media.jai.RenderedOp;  
import javax.media.jai.operator.CropDescriptor;  
import javax.media.jai.operator.FileLoadDescriptor;  
import javax.media.jai.operator.HistogramDescriptor; 
//  
// Loads the image  
// File file = new File("../images/20030701-0043.NEF");  
//  
// Doesn't work: the TIFF plugin gets instantiated before the NEF one, and  
// only the thumbnail is loaded. Unfortunately FileLoadDescriptor does not give  
// enough control on the ImageReader.  
// 
//PlanarImage image = FileLoadDescriptor.create(file.getAbsolutePath(), null, true, null);  
ImageInputStream iis = ImageIO.createImageInputStream(file);  
ImageReader ir = ImageIO.getImageReadersBySuffix("NEF").next();  
ir.setInput(iis);  
BufferedImage bufferedImage = ir.read(0);  
iis.close();  
PlanarImage image = PlanarImage.wrapRenderedImage(bufferedImage);  
//  
// Crops the image  
// 
image = CropDescriptor.create(image, 10.0f, 10.0f, 600.0f, 400.0f, null);  
//  
// Computes the histogram  
// 
SampleModel sampleModel = image.getSampleModel();  
int bandCount = sampleModel.getNumBands();  
int bits = DataBuffer.getDataTypeSize(sampleModel.getDataType());  
int[] bins = new int[bandCount];  
double[] min = new double[bandCount];  
double[] max = new double[bandCount];  
int maxxx = 1 << bits;  
 
for (int i = 0; i < bandCount; i++)
  {
    bins[i] = maxxx;
    min[i] = 0;
    max[i] = maxxx;
  }

RenderedOp op = HistogramDescriptor.create(image, null, 1, 1, bins, min, max, null);  
Histogram histogram = (Histogram)op.getProperty("histogram");  
//  
// Prints some information item from the histogram  
// 
for (int band = 0; band < bandCount; band++)
  {
    int[] frequencies = histogram.getBins(band);
    logger.info("band #" + band + ": min=" + histogram.getLowValue(band) + 
                                   " max=" + histogram.getHighValue(band) + " " + 
                                   frequencies.length + " samples");
  } 

The first thing that comes to our mind is that this code is too long: we are executing three operations here (load, crop and histogram), and we'd expect a little more than three lines of code (writing the least code is one of the trendy discussion all the world around, be it J2EE or anything else). Let us clearly state that we're not criticizing JAI at all: it's a powerful and wide-purpose API and it's quite obvious that it deals with a lot of details. From this point of view, JAI is just like JDBC, a low-level API, and there's nothing wrong with JDBC; but we do prefer to work with some less verbose high-level APIs, such as Hibernate (or the latest Java Persistence API), isn't it?

Well, this is the same example re-written with Mistral:

import java.util.logging.Logger; 
import java.io.File; 
import java.io.IOException; 
import it.tidalwave.image.EditableImage; 
import it.tidalwave.image.Histogram; 
import it.tidalwave.image.op.CropOp; 
import it.tidalwave.image.op.HistogramOp;  
// 
// Loads the image 
// 
File file = new File("../images/20030701-0043.NEF"); 
EditableImage image = EditableImage.read(file, 0); 
logger.info("Image loaded in " + image.getLatestOperationTime() + " msec"); 
// 
// Crops the image 
// 
image.execute(new CropOp(10, 10, 600, 400)); 
logger.info("Image cropped in " + image.getLatestOperationTime() + " msec"); 
// 
// Computes the histogram 
// 
Histogram histogram = image.execute(new HistogramOp()).getHistogram();  
histogram.compute(); 
logger.info("Histogram computed in " + image.getLatestOperationTime() + " msec"); 
// 
// Prints some information item from the histogram 
// 
for (int band = 0; band < histogram.getBandCount(); band++)
  {     
    int min = histogram.getMin(band);   
    int max = histogram.getMax(band);     
    int[] frequencies = histogram.getFrequencies(band);     
    logger.info("band #" + band + ": min=" + min + 
                                   " max=" + max + " " + 
                                     frequencies.length + " samples");  
  }

The code is much more compact and readable (12 lines versus 28). Furthermore, there's a plus: just three lines with the logger provide information about how long each operation was (a valuable feature for tuning an application). To get the elapsed time you don't have to deal with local variables and computing delta times: EditableImage just remembers how long the latest performed operation took. Later we will see that we will be able to get rid also of those logger.info() lines, still retaining statistics.

You could argue that choosing the HistogramOp as a paragon is not fair, as maybe this operation requires a longer-than-average preparation. Well, this is partly true, many operations can be prepared in less lines, but this is not so frequent. Remember that JAI is a low-level API, that is it provides (relatively) simple operations that probably needs to be combined in the real world. For instance, the common task of creating a smaller copy of a photo is not performed by JAI in a single step: different combinations of Scale, SubsampleAverage and FilteredSubsample may be needed according to the image type and the scale factor (see here and here). Mistral defines a SizeOp which encapsulates all this behaviour (BTW, at this point we could add that there are still sparse bugs in JAI which often triggers only with specific sets of parameters - see for instance bug #4857245 - and Mistral is a good place for inserting workarounds that won't clutter your application code).

The second thing you should notice are the import declarations: with Mistral, there's no trace of JAI-specific classes (nor specific of any other imaging API). Indeed JAI is still behind the scenes (if you want): EditableImage internally "translates" each operation (such as CropOp or HistogramOp) in a specific JAI implementation. The mapping is kept by a special ImplementationFactory, where you (or another programmer) could easily register alternate ways to perform the same operation. For instance, CropOp and HistogramOp can be implemented with ImageJ, and in this case the above example would "drive" ImageJ code. Thanks to the indirection brought to us by the ImplementationFactory we have achieved a substantial engine-independence - we are just coding a high level image manipulation algorithm.

ImplementationFactory instances can be easily registered at the application startup:

ImplementationFactoryRegistry registry = ImplementationFactoryRegistry.getInstance().
registry.registerFactory(new ImplementationFactoryJ2D());
registry.registerFactory(new ImplementationFactoryJAI());
registry.registerFactory(new ImplementationFactoryImageJ());

and this mechanism can be easily extended with a fully configurable approach, for instance using Class.forName().

So, the second step of Pleiades was me taking Emmanuele's code and refactoring it into the Mistral version, eventually adding some operations that I hadn't coded before, such as the Fast Fourier Transform and such. After some initial skepticism, Emmanuele appreciated the improved readability of the Mistral code over the original JAI version; so he switched on it and went on improving his idea with Mistral. In the meantime, without needing to understand much of what Emmanuele was doing, I was able to perform some more refactoring for performance reasons, reducing the computation time by several seconds. In other words, we achieved a good separation of responsibilities, algorithm versus implementation: in future Emmanuele will mostly work on the former, I will on the latter; everybody will do what he's able to do better. And we can plug in alternate implementations after the fact, just in case some other guy wants to use ImageJ or another stuff.

Exploiting parallelism

Now, the parallel thing. For the sake of simplicity, we just suppose that we have to execute the very same code above on a large number of images (tenths or thousands). Let's say that the above code is encapsulated in a method such as

public void process (File file)
  {
    // ...
  }

Our problem is something like:

for (int i = 0; i < 100; i++)
  {
    process(file[i]);
  }

In this form, this is pretty serial code. It's good from a modeling point of view, but for instance it can't exploit the dual core of my MacBook Pro, which can execute two tasks at the same time. And what about the Grid, where you have lots of available processors?

For my MacBook Pro we could do something like (this won't compile, it's just pseudo-code to render the idea):

int i = 0;

for (int j = 0; j < 2; j++)
  {
    Thread t = new Thread()
      {
        public void run() 
          {
            while (i < 100)
              {
                process(file[i++]);
              }
          }
      };
   
    t.start();
  }

while (i < 100) 
  {
    wait();
  }

Basically we've set up a couple of threads that consume all the files in the array. A real code which would compile and work is just a bit of more work, and we can make a thread pool as large as the number of processors in the system (that you get by calling Runtime.getRuntime().availableProcessors(). Fine, this would work also on the newest MacPro (with four cores) and in future multi-core systems.

But multi-core systems aren't the only way we could do parallel computing. We have already depicted a few different scenarios: Jini™ + Rio and the Sun Grid. This is really distributed computing in different Virtual Machines, and Thread isn't the right abstraction. Both these technologies have their own APIs, that we have to learn; but, above all, looks like we're forced to deal with different ways to do the same thing.

The correct way to go is to apply the correct design, and use abstraction. First of all, Mistral wraps the code in a special class called ImagingTask:

class MyImagingTask extends ImagingTask
  {
    public MyImagingTask (File file)  
      {
         // ...
      }

    public void run()
      {
         // ...
      }

    public EditableImage getResult() 
      {
        return ...;
      }
  }

Then we have an ImagingTaskProcessor that is an abstract object able to schedule an ImagingTask:

for (int i = 0; i < 100; i++)
  {
    ImagingTaskProcessor.getInstance().post(new MyImagingTask(file[i]);
  }

What does ImagingTaskProcessor.getInstance() return? Well, depends on what you want to do. It could return a simple local processor, based on a pool of threads; it could return a processor able to find distributed computing nodes implemented with Jini and Rio; it could return an implementation able to use the available processors on the Sun Grid. The important thing is that we have again separated the algorithm from the concrete implementation - and we can still plug in different implementations after the fact.

There are more things to consider, as you seldom deal with simple, independent tasks that just go parallel as in our example. In the real world you have dependencies (some tasks must be completed before others are launched), or what some technologies call "multi-phasing" (running different tasks in different phases). Mistral easily achieve this by using an ImagingTaskProcessorController which implements a callback method that is executed every time a task is completed. Look at the following example:

    public void notifyTaskCompleted (ImagingTask task)
       {
         if (task instanceof Phase1Task)
           {
             processor.post(new Phase2Task(task.getResult()));
           }
       }

This code schedules a phase 2 task that works on the result of a phase 1 task. It's a very limited example, as in the real world there should be a test condition to understand when the processing is over (otherwise you'll run forever), but renders the idea. The following example is a bit more complex:

    public void notifyTaskCompleted (ImagingTask task)
      {
        while (processor.getCompletedTaskCount(Phase1Task.class) >= 2)
          {
            EditableImage image1 = processor.popCompletedTask(Phase1Task.class).getResult();
            EditableImage image2 = processor.popCompletedTask(Phase1Task.class).getResult();
            processor.post(new Phase2Task(image1, image2));
          }
      }

Whenever there are at least two completed tasks from phase 1, their results are fed to a phase 2 task. You can find a slightly more complex example of a phase controller here.

Collecting statistics

When dealing with ImagingTasks, you can generate statistics in an implicit way, reducing ever more the number of lines of code. Instead of writing

class MyImagingTask extends ImagingTask
  {
    public void run()
      {
        File file = new File(...);
        EditableImage image = EditableImage.read(file, 0);
        logger.info("Image loaded in " + image.getLatestOperationTime() + " msec");
        image.execute(new CropOp(10, 10, 600, 400));
        logger.info("Image cropped in " + image.getLatestOperationTime() + " msec"; 
        Histogram histogram = image.execute(new HistogramOp()).getHistogram();  
        logger.info("Histogram computed in " + image.getLatestOperationTime() + " msec"); 
        // ...
      }
  }

you can write:

class MyImagingTask extends ImagingTask
   {
     public void run()
       {
         File file = new File(...);
         EditableImage image = read(file, 0, "my load operation");
         execute(image, new CropOp(10, 10, 600, 400), "my crop operation");
         Histogram histogram = execute(image, new HistogramOp(), "compute histogram").getHistogram();  
         // ...
       }
   }

It is semantically equivalent, but ImagingTask will keep track of the elapsed time keeping a record. If the same code is executed more than once, the statistics "my load operation", "my crop operation" and "compute histogram" will be updated each time, and the min/max/average values will be available to the programmer (usually these information are just logged). In a distributed environment, Mistral collects and aggregates statistics from all the computing nodes around.

ImagingTaskProcessor.getInstance().getStatistics().dump();

As a final note, we at last achieved our target, that is writing roughly three lines of code since we're executing three operations. The code works with any imaging engine, and in any local or distributed computing environment.

Conclusion

Mistral is based on a very simple but effective design. It enables you to concentrate on the imaging algorithm and to choose your favourite imaging engine (JAI, ImageJ or another) in a later time. It also makes you able to abstract the parallelism of your algorithm and take advantage of any distributed processing context with a little effort. Mistral is based on a known and very simple design pattern, the Master-Worker. It's simple but powerful for a certain class of distributed processing, such as the "embarrassingly distributed" algorithms, made of tasks which are largely reciprocally independent. The abstraction layer of Mistral also leads to a good separation of roles and responsibilities when writing the application.

In the real world there are a lot of details to deal with, but this is not a topic for this white paper. You can learn more by reading other documents about Mistral.

As a final word, at the moment Mistral is just work in progress. It works, as there are two applications (blueMarine and Pleiades) that are based on it, but it's not complete. The number of available operations is smaller than those of e.g JAI or ImageJ - but this is not a design limitation, just work in progress as Emmanuele and I are adding stuff as we need it. Also, some operations are less flexible than they could be (e.g. they don't deal with the ROI), but it's again just work in progress.